<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<topics>
  <topic>
    <title>Achaq&#039; Iboy</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>871</nid>
    <key>ACHAQ_IBOY</key>
    <ximenez_spa>achac yboy</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>achac yboy</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>According to Christensen (2007: note 807, p266), the name Achaq Iboy, señor principal de los ajaw k'iche', means "Droppings/Backside/Buttocks Armadillo."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajal Mes</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>680</nid>
    <key>AJAL_MES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahalmez</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahalmez</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez (13r) defines the name as "el q’hazía vasura" (he who makes trash). However, this translation flattens the spiritual significance of sweeping. Within K'iche' cosmovisión, the act of sweeping (<em>mes</em>) with a broom (<em>mesb'al</em>), is considered a way to keep demons from the underworld from entering the house. See Christenson (2007: note 239, p. 104), citing Tedlock (1996: note 92, p. 253).</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 88, página 213) ofrece otra interpretación: “Literalmente los nombres de estos Señores son: ‘Señor de la Basura’ y ‘Señor Apuñalador’. Sin embargo y por contexto Ajal Mes equivale a causante de desgracia, por provocar enemistad. La palabra clave en el texto k’iche’ es <em>tza</em> que es sinónima de <em>labal</em> y quiere decir ‘enemistad’ o ‘guerra’ (Basseta); en q’eqchi`el término <em>tza</em> quiere decir ‘demonio’ (Sam Juárez, <em>et al</em>, 2003). En el texto k’iche’ se dice <em>tza mes</em>, que tiene un significado literal de ‘enemistad de basura’, es decir enemistad surgida de la nada y que trae como consecuencia la muerte.” Después el destacado investigador observa que "los nombres de los Señores de Xibalba no son exactamente iguales", pues "Ajal Mes y Ajal Toq'ob son substituidos por Kik' Re, 'dientes sangrantes' y Kik' Rixk'aq, 'garras sangrantes' (2008, nota 154, página 222).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajal Puj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>675</nid>
    <key>AJAL_PUJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahal puh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahal puh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 236 p. 103): "<em>Ajal Puj</em>,<em> Ajal Q'ana</em>." <em>Ajal</em> is likely a loan word from Chol, meaning “evil spirit” (Campbell 1983, 81). <em>Puj</em> is “pus,” and q'ana is “yellowness, jaundice.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajal Q&#039;ana</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>676</nid>
    <key>AJAL_QANA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahal ꜫana</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahal ꜫana</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 236 p. 103) translates the name of this Lord of Xibalba as "Janudice Demon," following the meaning of q'ana, “yellowness, jaundice.” He also notes that like Ajal Q'ana's complement, Ajal Puj, Ajal Q'ana carries part of a name, Ajal, that "is likely a loan word from Chol, meaning “evil spirit” (Campbell 1983, 81)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajal Toq&#039;ob</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>681</nid>
    <key>AJAL_TOQOB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahaltocob</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahaltocob</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 240, page 104) translates the diety's name as "Stabbings Demon," derived from "the root toq' (to stab, to gore)."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 83, página 213) confirme la interpretación del "Señor Apuñalador," no obstante añade mayores informaciones. Escribe: “Literalmente los nombres de estos Señores son: ‘Señor de la Basura’ y ‘Señor Apuñalador’. Sin embargo y por contexto Ajal Mes equivale a causante de desgracia, por provocar enemistad. La palabra clave en el texto k’iche’ es <em>tza</em> que es sinónima de <em>labal</em> y quiere decir ‘enemistad’ o ‘guerra’ (Basseta); en q’eqchi`el término <em>tza</em> quiere decir ‘demonio’ (Sam Juárez, <em>et al</em>, 2003). En el texto k’iche’ se dice <em>tza mes</em>, que tiene un significado literal de ‘enemistad de basura’, es decir enemistad surgida de la nada y que trae como consecuencia la muerte.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Ajtzik Winaq</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>854</nid>
    <key>AJAW_AJTZIK_WINAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahau ahtzíc vínac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau ahtzic vinac </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 750, p. 256): "<em>Ajaw Aj Tzik' Winaq</em> (Lord Herald Person). Aj Tzik' is a “crier, proclaimer, speaker, herald, announcer.”</p>

<p>Por su parte Colop (2008: nota 362, página 255) observa que "el nombre propio del (Ajaw) Q’alel de los Nija’ib era Ke’ema y el del Ajtzik Winaq de los Ajaw K’iche’ era Uchaq’ Iboy."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Awilix</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>982</nid>
    <key>AJAW_AWILIX</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahau auílíx</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau aulix</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 552, page 198) translates the name of the deity Awilix, after whom the Lord of the Great House of the Nija'ib is named, as “you are watched over/cared for/commissioned.” He notes: "Throughout the text, the Quichés promise to watch over and care for their gods, providing them with offerings, sustenance, and worship (p. 290; lines 8344-8346, 8379-8388). Tedlock suggests that it may be derived from the Kekchi, kwilix/wilix, “swallow” (the bird) and reads the full name as Lord Swallow (D. Tedlock 1996, 297 n. 152). More recently, Akkeren (personal communication) has suggested that the Nihaib lineage originally came from the Pico de Orizaba area, known anciently by its Nahua name Awilizapan. It is possible that Awilix, the patron deity of the Nihaib derived the name of their god from this region and its principle mountain which bore the same name."</p>

<p>Carmack (198: page 50) cites Edmondson (1965), claiming that Awilix is a shortening of "C'abawil Ixchel," and says, "[l]ike the Gulf Coast peoples the Quichés associated this goddess with the moon," implying that Awilix is female.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Jaqawitz</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>863</nid>
    <key>AJAW_JAQAWITZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahau hacauítz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau hacavitz </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 762, page 257) translates "Ajaw Jaqawitz" as "Lord Hacavitz," and notes, "This is likely the priest of the god Hacavitz, the patron deity of the Ahau Quichés."</p>

<p>De los cuatro casas grantes "antes los Ajaw K'iche'," Colop (2008: 199) escribe: "Jaqawitz, el cuarto Señor".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw K&#039;iche&#039;</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>822</nid>
    <key>AJAW_KICHE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahau quiche</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau quiche</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2004, note 110, p. 271) notes, "The manuscript does not include the word 'K'iche'' here, referring to the Ajaw K'iche' lineage, although it is implied from the context."</p>

<p>The Ajaw K'iche' lineage was founded by the fourth -- and final -- deity in the hierarchical sequence, Majuk'utaj. It is the “third-ranking Quiché lineage,” according to Tedlock (1996), who helpfully defined the terms and their shifting places in the text. He writes: “<em>K’iche’</em>, the name of a people, a language, a town, and a kingdom.</p>

<p>As a people, the Quiché proper consist of those who descend from Jaguar Quitze [Balam Ki'tze'], Jaguar Night [Balam Aq'ab], and Not Right Now [Ik'ibalam]—that is to say, the Cauec, Greathouse, and Lord Quiché lineages—and who worship the gods Tohil, Auilix, and Hacauitz.</p>

<p>‘The three Quichés’ include the Quiché proper, as just described, together with two further lineages who god was Tohil, the Tams and Ilocs. This threesome is said to have been together ever since the time of Tulan, and to have shared the same language, which is also called Quiché.</p>

<p>Late in the narrative Quiché becomes a place name referring to the vicinity of Rotten Cane [Q'umaraq Aj], covering Rotten Cane itself, Bearded Place (half a kilometer south of Rotten Cane), and the site of the post-conquest town of Santa Cruz. The name can also be extended to the entire kingdom that was ruled from Rotten Cane.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw K&#039;otuja Undécimo</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>961</nid>
    <key>AJAW_KOTUJA_UNDÉCIMO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Ahau cotuha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Ahau cotuha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p><em>K'o Tuja</em> means "Lord Sweatbath" (Christenson 2007: note 874, p. 283). The 11th Lord of the Nija'ib line draws his name from the 5th and 8th generations.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Lolmet</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>861</nid>
    <key>AJAW_LOLMET</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahau lolmet</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau lolmet</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Según indica Allen Christenson (2004: nota 760, página 257), Ajaw Lolmet significa "Lord Emissary," y así se nombra el segundo señor principal de los K'iche' (Colop 2008: 199).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Nim Ch&#039;okoj</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>862</nid>
    <key>AJAW_NIM_CHOKOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahau ním chocoh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau nim chocoh </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Allen Christenson (2007: nota 889, página 286), observa que "The Nim Ch'okoj (Great Stewards) of the three principal Quiché lineages identify themselves here as the authors of the “word,” likely the Popol Vuh manuscript itself."</p>

<p>Ajaw Nim Ch'okoj, also written as "Nim Ch'okoj Ajaw," is the third great lord in this tradition, or "el tercer señor" (Colop 2008: 199).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajaw Q&#039;alel</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>853</nid>
    <key>AJAW_QALEL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ahau ꜫalel</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau ꜫalel</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>El primer señor principal de los Nija'ib: "U nab'e ajaw," entendido en inglés como "Lord Magistrate" (Christenson 2007: 301).</p>

<p>Según explica Colop (2008: nota 335, página 251): “El primero de estas nueve autoridades se llamaba Ajaw Q’alel siendo la primera palabra ‘señor’ y <em>q’alel </em>derivada de <em>q’alaj</em>, ‘claridad’, o sea el ‘Señor que ve las cosas con claridad’ o de <em>q’aq’</em>, ‘fuego’, por lo que significa poder. Esto ha sido traducido como ‘Señor capitán’ (Edmonson, 1971: 231) y ‘Señor ministro’ (D. Tedlock, 1996: 185). Carmack (1983: 228), sin embargo, dice: ‘El K’alel era un cargo con funciones judicales.’”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajbatenaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>806</nid>
    <key>AJBATENAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ah batenab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah batenaba </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 520, p. 193) translates <em>Aj B'atena Ja</em> as "They of the Ballgame Yoke House."</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajch&#039;umilaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>804</nid>
    <key>AJCHUMILAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahchamíla</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah chumila </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajkibaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>805</nid>
    <key>AJKIBAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahquíbaha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahquibaha </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajpop</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>820</nid>
    <key>AJPOP</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Señores de trono</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahpop </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajpop K&#039;amja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>821</nid>
    <key>AJPOP_KAMJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Señores de alfambra</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahpopcam </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajpop Sotz&#039;il</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>816</nid>
    <key>AJPOP_SOTZIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahpozotzíl</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah pozotzil </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajpop Xajil</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>817</nid>
    <key>AJPOP_XAJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahpoxa</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah poxa </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajq&#039;ukumatz</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>847</nid>
    <key>AJQUKUMATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahcucumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah cuꜫumatz </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajtojil</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>846</nid>
    <key>AJTOJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahtohíl</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahtohil </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"<em>Aj Tojil, Aj Q'ukumatz</em> (He of Tojil, He of Cucumatz). These are likely priests of the two major patron deities. <em>Q'ukumatz</em> (Quetzal Serpent) was one of the creator deities (see pp. 61, 68-72, 80-82; lines 25, 140-154)" (Christenson 2007: nota 742, página 254).</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 334, página 251) clarifica que "Ajtojil, era el cncargado del culto a Tojil; el cuarto en rango es Ajq'ukumatz, encargado del culto a Q'ukumatz, seguido por el Nim Ch'okoj Kaweq, el 'principal de los maestros de ceremonias de los Kaweq'."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajtz&#039;ikinaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>798</nid>
    <key>AJTZIKINAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ah q,íquínaha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah q,inquina </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christensen (p. 204, n. 512): "<em>Aj Tz'ikina Ja </em>(They of the Bird House) was the dominant lineage of the people today known oas the Tzutuhils [Tz'utujil], who occupied the land from the southern shores of Lake Atitlán south to the cacao-growing land of the Pacific Coast. Their capital was Chiya' (now called Chutinamit), located on a small hill at the base of San Pedro Volcano just across the bay to the northwest of the modern community of Santiago Atitlán. The group was likely composed of two separate lineage groups (the <em>Ah Tziquinahas </em>and the <em>Tzutuhils</em>), which were at times openly hostiel to one another (Orellana 1984, 81; Carlsen 1997, 75). The authors of the <em>Annals of the Cakchiquels </em>stated that the Tzutuhils succeeded in temporarily expelling the Ah Tziquinahas from their citadel south of Lake Atitlán in 1521 (Recinos and Goetz 1952, 117)."</p>

<p>Carlsen (2001, pp. 284–285): "Tz'utujil, which means 'flower of the maize plant,' is a language of the Greater K'iche'an (or K'iche'an-Mamean branch of the Eastern division of the Mayan language family." "Until the subsequent arrival of the Kaqchikel, the entire Lake Atitlán region, as well as extensive areas in the agriculturally rich piedmont region, was under Tz'utujil control. The exact nature of that control remains a point of scholarly debate. Sandra Orellana argues for a single Tz'utujil kingdom; in contrast, I propose the coexistence of competing Tz'utujil polities [one of which, presumably, would be the Ajtz'ikinajas].""When the Spanish arrived in 1524, much of the former Tz'utujil territory had been seized by the more numerous Kaqchikel. Led by Pedro de Alvarado, the Spanish force exploited preexisting regional hostility and enlisted the Kaqchikels as allies to defeat the Tz'utujils."</p>

<p>The prefix <em>aj- </em>refers to a person associated with a place, object, or activity, <em>tz'ikin </em>means "bird," and <em>ja </em>refers to "house." Thus this name can be translated as "those of the bird house."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ajtzik Winaq</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>860</nid>
    <key>AJTZIK_WINAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ahtzíc vínac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahtzic vinac </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 335, página 251): “El segundo sería el ‘Señor pregonero’ o ‘vocero’, deviniendo su título de Ajtzij Winaq como está en <em>El Título de Totonicapán</em>”.</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 759, page 257): "<em>Aj Tzik' Winaq</em> (Herald Person)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Akul Winaq</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>807</nid>
    <key>AKUL_WINAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> acul vínac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>acul vinac </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Alom</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>629</nid>
    <key>ALOM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>alom</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>alom</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 2, página 201) señala que "Alom viene de <em>ali</em>, 'niña', y <em>k'ajolom</em> viene de <em>k'ajol</em>, 'niño' o 'hijo de varón'. La partícula <em>-om</em> es un agentivo que hace referencia a su calidad de mujer que 'concibe' y al varón que 'engendra', respectivamente. Éstos son adjetivos que hacen referencia a la pareja creadora en una lectura antropomórfica".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 14, p. 52) confirms that "These are titles for the divine couple, Xmucane and Xpiyacoc (see p. 80; lines 557-558). Ximénez translated their Quiché names, Alom and K'ajolom, as simply 'Mother' and 'Father.' A more accurate translation for Alom, however, is 'She Who Has Borne Children,' from the perfect aspect of the root verb <em>al</em> (to bear children). The name of the male god, K'ajolom, specifically indicates his having begotten male offspring, thus 'He Who Has Begotten Sons.' Fray Bartolomé de las Casas wrote in the sixteenth century that the people of Guatemala worshiped as their principal gods 'the Great Father and the Great Mother that were in heaven,' apparently referring to this divine couple (Las Casas 1967, III.cxxiv.650)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Alonso de la Peña Montenegro</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1097</nid>
    <key>MONTENEGRO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el íllmo. Sor. Montenegro</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Alonso de la Peña Montenegro was bishop of Quito from 1653–1687, to whom was attributed the <em>Itinerario para parochos de indios, en que se tratan las materias más particulares, tocantes a ellos, para su buena administración</em>.</p>

<p>According to William B. Taylor,</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The nominal author, Alonso de la Peña Montenegro, bishop of Quito in the mid-seventeenth century, completed the text in 1663. It went through seven editions between 1668 and 1771 and circulated widely in Spanish america until the end of the colonial period. It is the manual that eighteenth-century curas and vicarios in New Spain were most likely to take with them into the field, appearing frequently in the inventories of property owned by parish priests and in the footnotes of treatises they wrote. …</p>

<p>Above all, it provided detailed descriptions of the responsibilities of priests in Indian parishes and what they needed to know to meet these responsibilities. Because Indians were perpetual minors, the priests and royal governors were to be their special guardians, and the precepts of the church were not to be applied to them with the same rigor as to non-Indians.</p>
</blockquote></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Amaq&#039; Tam</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>755</nid>
    <key>AMAQ_TAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>amactan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>amactan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The area settled by the Tamub. Christenson (page 225, note 590) translates: "<em>Amaq' </em>is 'nation,' <em>T'an </em>is 'bald, lacking plumage.' Most likely, however, this is an alternate or archaic spelling for the Tamub lineage. Thus the name of the place is simply 'Nation of the Tamub.' The Tamub lineage has a significant Pokom comonent, and in that language, Tamub may be read simply as 'the descendents' (Akkeren 2000, 125). Carmack identifies this site with a series of ruins known as Cruz Che located along a slope of Telec'uch Mountain west of Hacavitz. The remains of a diety shrine still known by its ancient name, Saqirib'al (Place of Dawn), is ocated on a peak of the mountain."</p>

<p>It is quite likely that Ximénez, by accident or deliberately, miswrote the name Amaq' Tan as "amac Dan" in a later instance of the name (folio 41r) to provide evidence for his theory that the K'iche's were descended from the biblical tribe of Dan.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Amaq&#039; Uq&#039;in k&#039;at</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>756</nid>
    <key>AMAQ_UQIN_KAT</key>
    <ximenez_spa>--</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>amac vquin cat</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The area initially settled by the Ilokab lineage. </p>

<p>Colop (página 153, nota 247) cita el <em>Título de Totonicapán</em>, explicando que "los Ilokab estaban en un cerro llamado 'Uq'uin,' que Carmack identifica como 'una aldea en el noroeste del pueblo de San Pedro Jocolipas' y también señala que en este lugar hay un sitio arqueológico." Colop traduce el nombre <em>Uq'in</em> como un producto del término <em>q'inom</em>,  "jocote," y <em>k'at </em>como "red," añadiendo que éste es también el nombre de un día del calendario Maya. "En consecuencia, el nombre del lugar podría estar asociado al inicio de una cuenta cíclica relativa al dia <em>k'at</em>."</p>

<p>Carmack also says that this was on Telec'uch Mountain, like the neighboring site of Amaq' T'an, from which it was separated by a canyon.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Antonio de Remesal</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1092</nid>
    <key>REMESAL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>M.R.P. Remesal</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Fray Antonio de Remesal, O.P. (1570–1619) era un fraile dominico y cronista de Centroamérica. Escribió una historia de la provincia de Chiapas y Guatemala en 1619 citada por Ximénez en sus Escolios.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Apóstol Santiago</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1085</nid>
    <key>SANTIAGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Apostol Santíago</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Saint James the Greater, so called as to distinguish him from the other apostle named Saint James, was an apostle of Jesus. According to tradition, he went on mission to what is now Spain, where he is now buried at Santiago de Compostela in Galicia.</p>

<p>Santiago el Mayor, llamado así para distinguirse del otro apóstol que se llama Santiago, era un apóstol de Jesucristo. Según la tradición, era misionero en lo que ahora es España, donde está enterrado en Santiago de Compostela en Galicia.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Arenas arrancadas</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1163</nid>
    <key>ARENAS_ARRANCADAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>las arenas</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>bocotahinac zanaieb</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of two names for what may be one or two places along the K'iche' forefathers' path across the sea from Tulan to the highlands. </p>

<p>Colop (página 151, nota 243) explica que "este 'pasaron del mar' no debe tomarse de manera literal. Es una figura para explicar el paso entre determinados lugares que se anegan en la época de la lluvia, o como dice Tedlock (301), 'en efecto, los nombres describen una calzada como las que cruzan lagos o áreas temporalmente inundadas para conectar varios sitios Mayas de las tierras bajas.'</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Awilix</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>718</nid>
    <key>AWILIX</key>
    <ximenez_spa> auílíx</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>avilix </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>According to Allen Christenson (2007: note 552, page 198), "In the Quiché language, this would read 'you are watched over/cared for/commissioned.' Throughout the text, the Quichés promise to watch over and care for their gods, providing them with offerings, sustenance, and worship (p. 290; lines 8344-8346, 8379-8388). Tedlock suggests that it may be derived from the Kekchi, kwilix/wilix, “swallow” (the bird) and reads the full name as Lord Swallow (D. Tedlock 1996, 297 n. 152). More recently, Akkeren (personal communication) has suggested that the Nihaib lineage originally came from the Pico de Orizaba area, known anciently by its Nahua name Awilizapan. It is possible that Awilix, the patron deity of the Nihaib derived the name of their god from this region and its principle mountain which bore the same name."</p>

<p>Carmack (198: page 50) cites Edmondson (1965), claiming that Awilix is a shortening of "C'abawil Ixchel," and says, "[l]ike the Gulf Coast peoples the Quichés associated this goddess with the moon," implying that Awilix is female.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>B&#039;ate</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1232</nid>
    <key>B'ATE</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/1921.jpeg?itok=eqEAczJE" width="100" height="62" alt="Kerr #1921. &quot;Ballgame with players wearing chest yokes. One wears deer headdress.&quot;" title="Kerr #1921. &quot;Ballgame with players wearing chest yokes. One wears deer headdress.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1921" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 244, pages 105-106) rightly points out the difficulty of documenting this object in alphabetic sources. He writes: "Unfortunately b'ate does not appear in any early colonial dictionaries, perhaps because the ballgame ceased to be played soon after the Spanish conquest. Thus the names for the equipment used in the game fell out of usage. From the description found later in the <em>Popol Vuh</em> text, the ball bounces off of this article in the process of playing the game. I have chosen to translate the word as 'yoke,' a well-known article of ballgame equipment throughout Precolumbian Mesoamerica. It is a U-shaped apparatus worn about the hips and used for striking the ball to keep it in play. Yokes were probably made of wood, although intricately carved stone replicas have been found in many parts of ancient Mesoamerica, particularly along the Gulf Coast of Veracruz."</p>

<p>However, iconographic evidence provides other clues. Justin Kerr's database includes <a href="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=2842">an early Classic era vessel that represents the divine ballplayers</a>; their yokes form the widest part of the object itself:</p>

<p><img alt="Kerr #2842" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="1" data-fid="217" data-media-element="1" height="429" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/2842.jpeg" title="Kerr #2842: &quot;Early Classic, with yoke as part of the vessel and ballplayers.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=2842" typeof="foaf:Image" width="350" /></p>

<p>(Kerr #2842)</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Balam Aq&#039;ab</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>705</nid>
    <key>BALAM_AQAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Balam acab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Balam acab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Balam Ki&#039;tze&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>704</nid>
    <key>BALAM_KITZE</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Balam quítze</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Balam qui tze </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Balam Kolob</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>810</nid>
    <key>BALAM_KOLOB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>balam colob</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>balam colob</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Balamija&#039;</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>808</nid>
    <key>BALAMIJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>balamíja</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>balamíja</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>barranco agitado</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>734</nid>
    <key>BARRANCO_AGITADO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>fuerte varranca</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>fuerte varranca</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (página 67, nota 95) dice que el lugar por donde pasaron Hun Hunahpu y Vucub Hunahpu para llegar a Xibalba estaba "lleno de estacas puntiagudas," y "espinas grandes," para hacer muy difícil el viaje. Los dos barrancos (el barranco agitado y el ruidoso) probablemente representaban obstáculos de acuerdo con sus nombres.</p>

<p>Tedlock (page 355) says "it could be east of San Pedro Carchá, where the Río Cahabón disappears into a system of caves and then emerges again."</p>

<p>Ximénez seems to have believed that the two canyons were merely two names of the same canyon, as he translates the K'iche' passage <em>nuzivan cul, cu zivan vbi </em>(<em>Nu' Siwan, K'ulk'u Siwan ub'i'</em> in Christenson's modern transcription) as <em>una varranca muy angosta q' se llamaba fuerte varranca.</em>​</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>barranco escondido</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>829</nid>
    <key>BARRANCO_ESCONDIDO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> barranca de el escondídízo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>evabal zivan </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>This was the name of Pa Awilix before it was settled by the K'iche' forefathers.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>barranco ruidoso</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>735</nid>
    <key>BARRANCO_RUIDOSO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>fuerte varranca</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cul, cu zivan </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (página 67, nota 95) dice que el lugar por donde pasaron Hun Hunahpu y Vucub Hunahpu para llegar a Xibalba estaba "lleno de estacas puntiagudas," y "espinas grandes," para hacer muy difícil el viaje. Los dos barrancos (el barranco agitado y el ruidoso) probablemente representaban obstáculos de acuerdo con sus nombres.</p>

<p>Tedlock (page 355) says "it could be east of San Pedro Carchá, where the Río Cahabón disappears into a system of caves and then emerges again.</p>

<p>Ximénez seems to have believed that the two canyons were merely two names of the same canyon, as he translates the K'iche' passage <em>nuzivan cul, cu zivan vbi </em>(<em>Nu' Siwan, K'ulk'u Siwan ub'i'</em> in Christenson's modern transcription) as <em>una varranca muy angosta q' se llamaba fuerte varranca.</em></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Bartolomé de las Casas</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1087</nid>
    <key>LAS_CASAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>fr. Bartolome de las casas</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Bartolomedelascasas.jpg?itok=UbM8vF0b" width="77" height="100" alt="Bartolomé de las Casas, Archivo General de las Indias, Wikimedia Commons." title="Bartolomé de las Casas, Archivo General de las Indias, Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, O.P. (1474 or 1484–1566) was a Dominican friar. A former <em>encomendero</em>, he eventually opposed the system of forced labor in which he had participated. His works, including his famous <em>Short Account of the Destruction of the Indies</em>, denounced the treatment of indigenous peoples by European colonizers. After a failed attempt at the "peaceful colonization" of Venezuela, he entered the Dominican Order, returning to the Americas as a priest and eventually bishop among the Maya in Guatemala. He was instrumental in the passage of the New Laws in 1542, which nominally if not particularly effectively reformed the <em>encomienda</em> system and gave certain protections to indigenous peoples. In 1547, he returned permanently to Spain, where he continued to advocate for indigenous peoples at court and in the Church.</p>

<p>Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, O.P. (1474 o 1484–1566) era un fraile dominico. Había sido encomendero, pero eventualmente se opuso del sistema de labor forzado en que había participado. Sus obras, incluyendo a su famosa <em>Brevísima relación de la destrucción de las Indias</em>, denunciaron al tratamiento de los indígenas por los conquistadores. Después del fracaso de su intento de "colonizar pacíficamente" a Venezuela, se juntó al orden dominico, y volvió a las Américas como cura y eventualmente obispo de los maya en Guatemala. Era clave en la institución de las Leyes Nuevas en 1542, que técnicamente, si no efectivamente, reformaron al sistema de encomienda y protegieron en cierto modo a los indígenas. Volvió permanentemente a España en 1547, y terminó su vida como abogado para los indígenas en la corte española y en la Iglesia.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Batz&#039;a</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>950</nid>
    <key>BATZA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Batza</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Batza</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"<em>Batz'</em>a proviene de <em>batz'-ja</em>, 'casa de mono', siendo <em>batz</em> 'mono', un día del calendario maya" (Colop 2008: nota 397, página 216).</p>

<p>For Christenson (2007: note 875, p. 283), <em>B'atz'a</em> is "Thread/Howler Monkey."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Belejeb Kej</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>839</nid>
    <key>BELEJEB_KEJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>beleheb queh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>beleheb queh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>El nombre del cuarto señor del linaje Nija'ib, Belejeb Kej, quiere decir el día "nueve venado" en el calendario maya (Colop 2008: nota 396, página 216).</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 873, p. 283) signals that the name <em>B'elejeb' Kej </em>or "Nine Deer" is a "day on the traditional 260 day calendar."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Belejeb Kej Noveno</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>956</nid>
    <key>BELEJEB_KEJ_NOVENO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Beleheb quíh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Beleheb quih</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><div>
<div>
<p>El nombre del noveno señor principal del linaje Nija'ib, Belejeb Kej, quiere decir el día "nueve venado" en el calendario maya, tal como indicaba el nombre del señor de la cuarta generación, el también nombrado Belejeb Kej (Colop 2008: nota 396, página 216).</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 873, p. 283) signals that the name <em>B'elejeb' Kej </em>or "Nine Deer" is a "day on the traditional 260 day calendar." The name of the 9th Lord of the Nija'ib generation repeats from the 4th.</p>
</div>
</div></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Bitol</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>628</nid>
    <key>BITOL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>bitol</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>bitol</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Sam Colop (2008: nota 1, página 201) observa que el nombre divino, aquí escrito en forma de quiasmo, significa "Literalmente el 'constructor' y 'creador'. <em>Tz'qa</em> y <em>bit</em> son raíces verbales 'construir' y 'crear'. <em>Tz'aq</em> quiere decur 'construcción' y <em>bit</em> 'creación'. El sufijo <em>-ol</em>, en ambos sustantivos, es marcador agentivo."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: 36) calls the relationship between Tz'aqol and Bitol, translated as "Framer" and "Shaper," respectively, "associative parallelism," or the use of the literary device of parallelism to show complimentary elements. Specifically, Tz'aqol and Bitol, "Framer and Shaper," are an example of "functional association," a poetic device "in which two elements act in a similar manner."</p>

<p>According to Christenson (2007: note 12, p. 51), <em>"B'itol</em> (Shaper) refers to one who makes something by modeling (i.e., pottery from clay, or a sculpture from carved stone), thus giving shape to an otherwise amorphous substance. The Framer and the Shaper are the most frequently mentioned gods involved in the creation of the world and its inhabitants. Their names imply that the creation involved giving frame and shape to matter that already existed rather than conjuring something out of nothing. This pair of gods was so important that soon after the Spanish conquest, Father Domingo de Vico used their Quiché names to refer to the God of the Old Testament (Carmack and Mondloch 1983, 206)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>camino amarillo</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>739</nid>
    <key>CAMINO_AMARILLO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>amarillo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ꜫana</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Palenque%20Temple%20XIX%20D4%20k%27an.jpg?itok=QRFfjM9H" width="100" height="96" alt="k&#039;an. Photo credit: Jorge Pérez de Lara (in Stuart 2005: 209)" title="Palenque Temple XIX, West Passage, glyph D4 (k&#039;an + yax = tz&#039;ak)" /></image>
    <description><p>The yellow path ("camino amarillo" or "ꜫana be," in Ximénez's script, and "q'ana b'e" in modern orthography) is one of the four cosmic routes of the universe ("cahib be"). Along with the red path ("camino rojo" or "ꜫaꜫabe"), black path ("camino negro" or "cahib be"), and white path ("camino blanco" or "zaqui be"), these four routes represent the spiritual pathways and cardinal points of the K'iche' cosmovisión (14r). In <em>Veiled Brightness: A History of Ancient Maya Color</em>, Stephen Houston et al. (2009: 35) observe that "yellow" (<em>*q'an</em>), "is homophonous with, and perhaps equivalent to, a term for 'precious,'" and that the term is generally shared among Mayan languages, deriving as it does from "Common Mayan."</p>

<p>Each physical route at the cross-roads ("cruzíjada" or "pacahib xalcat be") leads to a different spiritual path, one that is brought into order by a particular divine force. <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/content/cuatro-en-espacio-y-tiempo">The four-part division into the cardinal points reflects the four "cornerings," "sidings," "measurings," and "stakings" of the world, as understood in Maya cosmology as an act of creation, or coming into being</a>. For example, the opening lines of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> use parallel structure to describe the four corners of the earth. Allen Christenson notes that the balanced quatrain's "four-fold symmetry" might be one way in which the aesthetics of the text mirror "the four-fold nature of the universe" (<em>Literal Poetic Translation</em>, fn10p15). The key lines are, in Christenson, "Its four cornerings, / Its four sidings, / Its measurings, / Its four stakings", ll. 66-69.</p>

<p>In Sam Colop's translation of the text, we find: "Es grande su descripción / y el relato de cómo se terminó de crear todo el Cielo y la Tierra: / sus cuatro esquinas / sus cuatro lados, / su medici[on / sus cuatro ángulos / en las cuatro esquinas / en los cuatro lados, como se dice por parte de Tz'aqol, Bitol" (2-3). De esta forma el destacado historiador k'iche' señala que el texto sagrado suele hablar de los cuatro caminos (rojo, negro, blanco, amarillo) "según el orden cósmico con que se nombran los cuatro lados del Universo: Oriente, Poniente, Norte y Sur" (2011: nota 149, página 221).</p>

<p>Because each cardinal direction is linked to specific color symbolisms, color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>The <em>camino amarillo/q'ana b'e</em> is the only path whose color properties are replaced by another color, <em>green-blue/raxa</em> when the Hero Twins emerge from Xibalba. Alexandre Tokovinine (2012: 286) points out that yellow (<em>k'an</em>, in Yukatek, the likely language of Maya hieroglyphic writing) is also an outlier within color patterns that emerge among visual writing traditions. He writes, citing Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness </em>(2009: 37-38), "<em>K'an</em> is the only color glyph that is possibly hat is possibly borrowed from a pan-Mesoamerican set of symbols." When <em>k'an</em> is connected with <em>yax</em> (blue-green) in Mesoamerican graphic writing systems, the meaning of the "complementary pair" becomes "a widespread concept of 'precious' and 'glorious,'" an idea that is expressed <em>"</em>as a unity of all <em>yax</em> and <em>k'an</em>" in Yukatek, and as <em>räxa</em> and <em>q'äna</em> in Kaqchiken (Tokovinine 2012: 294).</p>

<p>Generally, <em>k'an</em> as color is associated with "states of ripeness" (Houston et al. 2009: 37) and, specifically, to the yellow-hued maiz god, <em>Ajan</em>, and "the corncob logogram" that usually symbolizes the divine figure (Tokovinine 2012: 293). Over time, the "sign that became 'yellow'" signaled places of prestige and importance, as in the term <em>k'anche</em> (yellow + tree = "seat of honor") (Houston et al. 2009: 37). In this way, the symbolic meaning of "yellow" (<em>k'an</em>) extends beyond "yellow" color properties.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>camino blanco</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>738</nid>
    <key>CAMINO_BLANCO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> zaqui</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>blanco </ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/sak%20co%CC%81dice%20madrid%20108.png?itok=GBQ4z4GZ" width="100" height="87" alt="Sak (white): Códice Madrid 108A" title="Sak (white): Códice Madrid 108A" /></image>
    <description><p>The white way ("camino blanco" or "zaqui be" in Ximénez's script) is one of the four cosmic routes of the universe ("cahib be"); along with the red path ("camino rojo" or "ꜫaꜫabe"), black path ("camino negro" or "queca be"), and yellow path ("camino amarillo" or "cut eana be"), these routes represent the spiritual pathways and cardinal points of the K'iche' cosmovisión (14r).</p>

<p>Each physical route at the cross-roads ("cruzíjada" or "pacahib xalcat be") leads to a different spiritual path, one that is brought into order by a particular divine force. <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/content/cuatro-en-espacio-y-tiempo">The four-part division by cardinal points reflects the four "cornerings," "sidings," "measurings," and "stakings" of the world, as understood in Maya cosmology</a>. For example, the opening lines of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> use parallel structure to describe the four corners of the earth. Allen Christenson notes that the balanced quatrain's "four-fold symmetry" might be one way in which the aesthetics of the text mirror "the four-fold nature of the universe" (<em>Literal Poetic Translation</em>, fn10p15). The key lines are, in Christenson, "Its four cornerings, / Its four sidings, / Its measurings, / Its four stakings", ll. 66-69.</p>

<p>In Sam Colop's translation of the text, we find similar expressions of these markings in cosmological terms: "Es grande su descripción / y el relato de cómo se terminó de crear todo el Cielo y la Tierra: / sus cuatro esquinas / sus cuatro lados, / su medici[on / sus cuatro ángulos / en las cuatro esquinas / en los cuatro lados, como se dice por parte de Tz'aqol, Bitol" (2-3). Compare with Ximénez: "ronohel cah vleu, vcah tzucuxic, vcah xucutaxic retaxic, vcah cheexic"/"q’ seacabo de formar todo el cielo, y la tierra, su ser cuadrado, su ser repartido en cuatro partes, su ser señalado, su ser amojonado con estacas, su ser medido a mecates, o cuerdas, y su ser estirada la cuerda en el zielo, y en la tierra; q’es dicho de cuatro esquinas, y cuatro lados por el formador, y criador" (1r). De esta forma el destacado historiador k'iche' señala que el texto sagrado suele hablar de los cuatro caminos (rojo, negro, blanco, amarillo) "según el orden cósmico con que se nombran los cuatro lados del Universo: Oriente, Poniente, Norte y Sur" (2011: nota 149, página 221).</p>

<p>In other words, each cardinal direction is linked to specific color symbolisms, such that color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>In this four-part cosmology, the "camino blanco" is associated with the north (<em>xaman</em>, in the Yukatek of the glyphs). White, written as <em>*saq</em> in proto-Mayan, <em>sak</em> in Yukatek and lowland Mayan languages and hieroglyphic scripts, and <em>saq</em> in K'iche', generally refers to "hues that are particularly pale, clear, even 'clouded' in the sense of a cataract" (Houston et al. 2009: 32). Iconographically, <em>sak </em>is associated with flowers, seeds, and sprouting, suggesting some of the rich ways in which the color symbolizes the beginning of life; however, it is just as often linked to cords that bind, restrict, and end life. As Alexandre Tokovinine (2012: 294) observes, "The connection between cords and the term <em>sak</em> is not as unusual as it might seem in the context of the above-mentioned term <em>sak ik'</em>, which denotes part of the human soul breathing out at death."</p>

<p>In <em>Veiled Brightness</em> (32-33), Houston et al. report on historical and ethnographic data that helps to explain the wide "economy of expression" that Mayan communities ascribe to <em>saq: "</em>When asked, Lacandon Maya say that white stands apart from other colors, without the same sense of gradation or loose resemblance to other shades (Vargas Melgarejo 1998: 87). In the Lancondon language and the closely related Yukatek, as well as in Ch'olti' and Ch'orti', the term often means 'artificial' or something devised by human arrangement and skill; Colonial Tzotzil adds the concept of 'beauty' (Vargas Melgarejo 1998: 87). Yukatek may explain why: <em>sakal </em>means 'woven thing' or 'to weave' (Barrera Vásquez 1980: 710), so that the cluster of extensional meanings plausibly results from the working of white native cotton into textiles by means of dexterous hands. For the Yucatec Maya and related groups, <em>sak  </em>as 'artificial' makes sense, too. Cloth working could have been understood as the epitome of human manufacture." It is worth noting that weaving was the work of skilled Maya women, and, thus, that the semantic loading of <em>sak </em>might also refer broadly to ideas of human agency, the transformation of matter, and the continuation of life in ways that the color term "white" or "blanco" does not convey in English or Spanish. See Kellog (2005).</p>

<p>From the details of daily life (weaving cloth) to broad cosmological significance ("Milky Way"), the <em>camino blanco</em> is a key element of pre-Columbian, colonial-era, and modern Maya expressions of color symbolism. Historically, they were made of white stones that made paths passable at night, using only the stones' reflection from the moon. Beyond their physical orientation, the paths are considered animate networks that connect the people of this world with spirits from beyond. For a longer discussion of the <em>sacbe</em> system and its significance in matters physical and cosmological, see Allan Burns, "The Road Under the Ground: the Role of Europe and Urban Life in Yucatec Mayan Narratives" in the Journal of Folklore (34) 1992, and Justine M. Shaw, <em>White Roads of the Yucatán: Changing Social Landscapes of the Yucatec Maya</em> (Tuscan: U of AZ Press, 2008).</p>

<p>Today, artists like <a class="ProfileHeaderCard-screennameLink u-linkComplex js-nav" href="https://twitter.com/Tzutukan"><span dir="ltr">@<strong>Tzutukan</strong></span></a> give voice to these deep tradtions in new media, from Twitter to hip hop. "<a href="https://actitudmusic.bandcamp.com/track/saq-bey">Saq b'ey/Vía láctea</a>", the second track on his <a href="https://actitudmusic.bandcamp.com/album/jun-winaq-rajawal-q-j-tributo-a-los-20-nawales">Jun Winaq´Rajawal Qíj / Tributo a los 20 Nawales</a>, suggests how Mayan artists are honoring the spiritual wisdom of their ancestors and reinterpreting the past in contemporary terms.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>camino negro</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>737</nid>
    <key>CAMINO_NEGRO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> queca be</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>uno negro </ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/och%20k%27in.png?itok=H4_nWw4f" width="100" height="90" alt="oeste" title="ochk&#039;ihn / oeste / west" /></image>
    <description><p>The black path ("camino negro" or "queca be," in Ximénez's script) is one of the four cosmic routes of the universe ("cahib be"); along with the red path ("camino rojo" or "ꜫaꜫabe"), white path ("camino blanco" or "zaqui be") and yellow path ("camino amarillo" or "cut eana be"), these routes represent the spiritual pathways and cardinal points of the K'iche' cosmovisión (14r).</p>

<p>Each physical route at the cross-roads ("cruzíjada" or "pacahib xalcat be") leads to a different spiritual path, one that is brought into order by a particular divine force. <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/content/cuatro-en-espacio-y-tiempo">The four-part division into the cardinal points reflects the four "cornerings," "sidings," "measurings," and "stakings" of the world, as understood in Maya cosmology as an act of creation, or coming into being</a>. For example, the opening lines of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> use parallel structure to describe the four corners of the earth. Allen Christenson notes that the balanced quatrain's "four-fold symmetry" might be one way in which the aesthetics of the text mirror "the four-fold nature of the universe" (<em>Literal Poetic Translation</em>, fn10p15). The key lines are, in Christenson, "Its four cornerings, / Its four sidings, / Its measurings, / Its four stakings", ll. 66-69.</p>

<p>In Sam Colop's translation of the text, we find: "Es grande su descripción / y el relato de cómo se terminó de crear todo el Cielo y la Tierra: / sus cuatro esquinas / sus cuatro lados, / su medici[on / sus cuatro ángulos / en las cuatro esquinas / en los cuatro lados, como se dice por parte de Tz'aqol, Bitol" (2-3).  De esta forma el destacado historiador k'iche' señala que el texto sagrado suele hablar de los cuatro caminos (rojo, negro, blanco, amarillo) "según el orden cósmico con que se nombran los cuatro lados del Universo: Oriente, Poniente, Norte y Sur" (2011: nota 149, página 221).</p>

<p>In this way, each cardinal direction is linked to specific color symbolisms, such that color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>According to Alexandre Tokovinine (2012: 283), in addition to these four main color vocabularies, there are also, among many Lowland Mayan languages, "single words with non-color primary meaning and compounds with basic color terms," both of which use what R.W. Casson calls "metonymic innovation" to convey specific ideas about color properties (R.W. Casson, "Russet, Rose, and Raspberry: The Development of English Secondary Color Terms," <em>Journal of Linguistic Anthropology</em> 4: 5-22). In other words, speakers of these Mayan languages define terms like <em>soot </em>(or sib'ik in Maya Ch'orti') as "purple," "dark blue," and "black" (citing C. Wisdom, <em>Materials on the Chorti Language</em>. University of Chicago Library, Chicago, 1950:635). Likewise, Maya Yukateko has two words for forms of indigo, <em>b'oox</em>, which also means "black," and <em>ch'doh</em>, which also means "blue" (citing Victoria Bricker, "Color and Texture in the Maya Language of Yucatan," <em>Anthropological Linguistics</em> 41 (3): 283-307, p. 284). See also Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness: A History of Ancient Maya Color</em>, Austin: University of Texas Press, 1999: 20-24).</p>

<p>Mayan writing systems are complex and diverse, and colors do not appear in a fixed or rigid order (Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness</em>, 1999: 28). Nevertheless, some associations persist between color names and spatial-temporal orientations. The color black, written as <em>ink'</em>, <em>ik' </em>or <em>ek'</em> in classic-era and colonial Maya Yukateko, and as <em>éek' </em>today, is associated with the west. Within a month-long count, the color black aligned with the months Uo and Ch'en, broken up by the color red, symbolized by the month Zip (Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness</em>, 1999: 27).</p>

<p>Unlike some of the color color-cardinal points, <em>ihk'</em>, the logogram or word sign that signifies "black," as Tokovinine (2012: 286) writes, is also essentially a representation of the color itself as a spot of blackness" (citing Stephen Houston et al., V<em>eiled Brightness</em>, 34-35). In some iconographic traditions, such as those studied by Houston et al., the graphic-word symbol for "black" seems to refer to caves, or dark underground spaces. In other cases, such as the glyphs studied by David Stuart at Palenque's Temple XIX, the writing has gone undeciphered. Tokovinine (2012: 286) thus concludes, "significance of the logogram for the color black extends beyond the notion of color into a broader range of meanings that includes hollow objects."</p>

<p>This symbolic understanding of <em>ihk'</em> as the color of caves and underground laberinths may explain why it is the camino negro that leads to Xibalba, home of the Lords of the Underworld. As Allen Christenson explains (2007: note 258, page 109), "the brothers were tricked into following the black, or west, road—a premonition of their defeat and death since this is the road that the sun takes when its sinks into the underworld."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>camino rojo</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>736</nid>
    <key>CAMINO_ROJO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ꜫaꜫabe</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>colorado </ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/elk%27in%20%28codex%20madrid%20108b%29.png?itok=_sA-Wk6k" width="100" height="84" alt="elk&#039;in (lak&#039;iin)" title="elk&#039;in (lak&#039;iin | este | east)" /></image>
    <description><p>When the Hero Twins first arrive at the crossroads of Xilbaba, they face four possible paths: the red way, black way, white way, and yellow way. Ximénez calls them, in colonial K'iche', "hun ꜫaꜫabe, hun cut queca be, zaqui be hun, hun cut eana be cahib be" (14r); he translates these names straightforwardly into Spanish as "camino rojo," "camino negro," "camino blanco," and "camino amarillo." When the twins emerge from Xibalba, the "camino amarillo" (yellow road/cahib be) becomes a "camino verde" (green road/raxa be), indicating an important relationship between color, space, and time (23v).</p>

<p>Each physical route at the cross-roads leads to a different spiritual path, one that is brought into order by a particular divine force. <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/content/cuatro-en-espacio-y-tiempo">The four-part division into the cardinal points reflects the four "cornerings," "sidings," "measurings," and "stakings" of the world, as understood in Maya cosmology as an act of creation, or coming into being</a>. For example, the opening lines of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> use parallel structure to describe the four corners of the earth. Allen Christenson notes that the balanced quatrain's "four-fold symmetry" might be one way in which the aesthetics of the text mirror "the four-fold nature of the universe" (<em>Literal Poetic Translation</em>, fn10p15). The key lines are, in Christenson, "Its four cornerings, / Its four sidings, / Its measurings, / Its four stakings", ll. 66-69.</p>

<p>In Sam Colop's translation of the text, we find: "Es grande su descripción / y el relato de cómo se terminó de crear todo el Cielo y la Tierra: / sus cuatro esquinas / sus cuatro lados, / su medici[on / sus cuatro ángulos / en las cuatro esquinas / en los cuatro lados, como se dice por parte de Tz'aqol, Bitol" (2-3). De esta forma el destacado historiador k'iche' señala que el texto sagrado suele hablar de los cuatro caminos (rojo, negro, blanco, amarillo) "según el orden cósmico con que se nombran los cuatro lados del Universo: Oriente, Poniente, Norte y Sur" (2011: nota 149, página 221).</p>

<p>Each cardinal direction is linked to specific color symbolisms, such that color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>This should not suggest, however, that there is an always-fixed or rigid order of associations; rather, there are general patterns that repeat themselves across diverse and complex writing systems of the Maya world (Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness</em>, 1999: 28). For example, the color red (written as "kaq" in modern K'iche', and as "chak" in modern Yukatekan), is associated with the east. In hieroglyphic writing, the glyph for "east" ("este" in Spanish, and "elk'in" or "elk'inh" in Classic and colonial-era Yukatek spelling, and written as "lak'iin" today) includes a signifier that we also find in the glyph for the god Chak. On the use of Yukatekan in hieroglphyic writing systems, see Macri and Looper, <em>New Catalog of Maya Hieroglyphs,</em> and Johnson, <em>Translating Maya Hieroglyphs</em>.</p>

<p>As various scholars have argued, adding the word "red" to the name of a plant or animal does not necessarily mean that the being has "red" properties (see for instance Houston et al., <em>Veiled Brightness</em>, 21; cited in Tokovinine, "Writing color," 286). Instead, the presence of color (literally, "colorado," in Spanish, often translated as "red," in ways that are correct and incorrect) maps onto specific objects and symbolic associations. In the case of "red" (chak), we find glyphs that link blood, Chak, and nobility. An inscription in Copán (Altar U: K4-5; Stela 8: D4-5), shows a queen's name that is written as "Chak [5993 | unknown]-ki ye xook ki," or "the tooth of the shark, Chak [5993 | unknown]" (Tokovinine, "Writing color," 286). Tokovinine suggests that the undeciphered glyph may represent a fish spine, often used in bloodletting ceremonies; this association would preserve the symbolic link between red hue, the Chak god, and royal ritual (Tokovinine, "Writing color," 288).</p>

<p>In addition to blood, the color red is linked to heat, in a broad symbolic web that includes fire, lightning, and the sun; such meanings extend to rain (both because storm clouds are linked to lightning and because the rains often come from the east in Yucatán), and to flowers. The objects themselves are usually colored yellow (k'an), but they share graphic markings of "chak," perhaps referring to prestige or greatness, as in the expression of "chak ch'ok," a man who has accomplished much in his young life (Tokovinine, "Writing color," 291). The camino rojo could convey all of these significations -- east, heat, and blood, and, thus, fertility, sexuality, and noble ceremonies of succession that involved both life-giving and life-taking elements.</p>

<p>Colonial writers misunderstood these color properties not only because they tried to read color within their own conceptual frameworks, but also because they misunderstood the ways in which Mayan speakers orient themselves in space. On Spanish maps, "north" is often found at the top, perhaps reflecting the navigational or maritime origins of maps that both directed transoceanic ships and were created in response to new imperial crossings (see for instance Monardes 1574: 166-166v).</p>

<p>But as Amara Solari has convincingly shown, Mayan cartography used circular models of space and time before and after the Spanish conquest. These round maps often placed "east" at the top of the wheel, perhaps reflecting agricultural orientations toward the rising of the sun (Solari, "Circles of Creation"). In a k'atun wheel from the <em>Chilam Balam de Chumayel</em>, for instance, "lak'in" or "east" is placed at the top of the circle. Spanish writers conflated "east" and "north," because they assumed that "north" would be at the top of the wheel.</p>

<p>As such, the "camino rojo" or "ꜫaꜫabe/kaq bej" of the <em>Popol Wuj </em>is tied to physical geographies, such as eastward-facing paths along which Maya people exchanged goods, services, and ideas with other Mesoamerican communities, as well as spiritual routes that connected the living and the created with the spirit worlds of ancestors and creators.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>camino verde</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>747</nid>
    <key>CAMINO_VERDE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>verde</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>verde</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Palenque%20Temple%20XIX%20D4%20yax.jpg?itok=cGY1_wbD" width="100" height="96" alt="yax" title="yax: blue/green color signifier from Temple XIX, Palenque (note k&#039;an to the far right)" /></image>
    <description><p>The "green way" is unlike the other four cosmic routes of the universe -- the red way (camino rojo/ꜫaꜫabe, or kaq bej in modern orthograph), black way (camino negro/queca be/q’eq bej), white way (camino blanco/zaqui be/saq bej), and yellow way (camino amarillo/ꜫana be/q’än bej).</p>

<p><a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/content/cuatro-en-espacio-y-tiempo">These four routes refer to the four cardinal points; the color symbolism often aligns with particular directions</a>. In hieroglyphic writing traditions from Mesoamerica, we often find that red is associated with the east; black, the west; white, the north; yellow, the south (Johnson 2013: 242). Although these colors refer to much more than cardinal points, there is a core geographic orientation (Houston et al. 2009; Tokovinine 2012). In other words, because each cardinal direction is linked to specific color symbolisms, color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>But the "green way" (camino verde/raxa be/räxal bej) is unlike these other four cases.</p>

<p>For one, its range of meanings is quite broad. The word "räxal" (rax) means both "blue" and "green," such that speakers of K'iche' and other Mayan languages distinguish between, as Christenson (2007: note 22, page 53) puts it, “'<em>räx</em> like the sky', for blue, or 'räx like a tree' for green." Christenson (2007: note 832, page 272), glossing the prayer that K'iche' leaders offer to <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/node/11">Juraqan</a> and <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/node/647">Uk'u'x Kaj Uk'u'x Ulew</a> explains that <em>räxal</em>, or "green/blueness,” connotes "vitality, newness, freshness, fertility," and that its meanings change when combined with other color properties. For example, "The combination of green and yellow is still used ceremonially to refer to the concept of 'abundance. Thus in the prayers of Quiché <em>aj q'ij</em> priests, the litany of deities they invoke include the “green shoulder, yellow shoulder of the world,' described as “the procreative powers of the earth” (Bunzel 1952, 266)."</p>

<p>For another, its written name seems to have changed to reflect some of the ways in which blue/green objects were used. As Houston et al. (2009: 40) explain in their study of the term <em>yax </em>(blue/green) in hieroglyphic inscriptions, "Maya scribes decided at some point to clarify the spelling further by inserting the [xa] syllable, a sign that owes its origin to the depiction of a rattle" and suggests onomatopoeia, because "the [xa] recalls the sibilant tones of gourd rattles."</p>

<p>Sam Colop (2011: nota 149, página 221) explica que el "camino verde" representa "el 'centro' y que sustituye al color amarillo 'sur'", precisamente en el momento en que los gémelos divinos vuelvan a pasar por la encrucijada de Xibalba, el mismo espacio por el cual Junajpu y Wuqub Jujapu ya pasaron. Ahí, pues, "Se sigue una oposición de colores comenzando con el negro, camino que marcó la muerte de sus padres, luego viene el blanco, el rojo y el verde, siendo este último el 'camino de la vida' y centro del orden cósmico maya. De aquí que el orden con que se nombra a los caminos en este pasaje, tiene una intencionalidad subyacente: no perecer, como efectivamente sucede."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Carlos V</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1067</nid>
    <key>CARLOS_V</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el emperador carlos quínto</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/carlos%20v.jpg?itok=vQemdgsh" width="83" height="100" alt="Charles V, painted by Titian" title="Charles V, painted by Titian, Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Charles V (1500–1558) was the ruler of the Spanish Empire from 1516–1556, the Holy Roman Empire from 1519–1556, and the Habsburg Netherlands from 1506–1555.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Casa de Hielo</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>741</nid>
    <key>CASA_DE_HIELO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> casa donde arrodillaban</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xuxulim ha </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Casa de Jaguares</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>742</nid>
    <key>CASA_DE_JAGUARES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>casa de leon tígres</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>balami ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Tedlock (page 345) says that this house may be a sign of the Mayan zodiac. He also says, "Jaguar House is also the name of a people belonging to a group of thirteen allied tribes the Quichés regarded as having come (like themselves) from the east."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Casa de los Chayes</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>744</nid>
    <key>CASA_DE_LOS_CHAYES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>casa de navajas</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chaim ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>As with the other trial houses of Xibalba, Tedlock (page 354) believes that this location may represent a period of the Mayan zodiac.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Casa de Murciélagos</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>743</nid>
    <key>CASA_DE_MURCIÉLAGOS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>casa de murzíelagos</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tzotzi ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Tedlock (page 340) says that this house "possibly correspond[s] to a position on the Mayan zodiac. Bat House is also the name of a lordly Cakchiquel lineage, otherwise known as Macaw House, whose founders stole fire from the Quichés rather than pledge themselves as sacrifice victims."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Casa Oscura</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>740</nid>
    <key>CASA_OSCURA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>casa obscura, casa de obscuridad</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quecuma ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Tedlock (page 341) says this may correspond to a sign of the zodiac.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ch&#039;amiyabaq</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1119</nid>
    <key>CHAMIYABAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chamia bac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chamia bac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2004: line 3666) spells the name of the god, Ch'ami'ya B'aq, and translates the meaning as "Staff Bone." In his prose translation (2007: note 226, page 101), he adds, "<em>Xbaquiyalo</em>. The likely etymology of this name is <em>x-</em> (lady), <em>baqi</em> (bone), <em>ya'</em> (water/river), <em>lo</em> (perhaps), yielding Lady Bone Water. Tedlock notes that in Yucatec, bak ha' (also “bone water”) is the snowy egret or snowy heron, and thus translates the name as “Egret Woman” (D. Tedlock 1996, 250 n. 91)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ch&#039;amiyabaq</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>678</nid>
    <key>CHAMIYABAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chamia bac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chamia bac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>El nombre del dios Ch'amiyabaq significa, conforme a la explicación de Sam Colop (2011: nota 82), es "Señor de la Vara de Hueso", ya que <em>Ch'amiy </em>o <em>ch'amiya</em>, "con <em>-a</em> final como inserción vocálica, quiere decir 'vara' o 'cetro', símbolo de autoridad. <em>Baq</em> es 'hueso'." El nombre de su par, Ch'amiyajolom, significa "Señor de la Vara de Hueso."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: 116) translates the name as "Bone Staff," and the name of Ch'amiyajolom as "Skull Staff," because "As emblems of office, Quiché political and religious leaders carry staffs that are often topped with ornate silver carvings symbolizing divine power" (note 237).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ch&#039;amiyajolom</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1122</nid>
    <key>CHAMIYAJOLOM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chamía holom</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chamiaholom</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Jolom means “head” and “skull” (Christenson 2007: note 631, page 233). Christenson translates the name Ch'amiyajolom as "Skull Staff," because "As emblems of office, Quiché political and religious leaders carry staffs that are often topped with ornate silver cavings symbolizing divine power" (note 237, page 116).</p>

<p>Sam Colop (2011: nota 82) afirma que "<em>Ch'amiy </em>o <em>ch'amiya</em>, con <em>-a</em> final como inserción vocálica, quiere decir 'vara' o 'cetro', símbolo de autoridad' y de la misma manera <em>jolom</em> "es 'cabeza', pero en este caso es calavera'', el cual nombre será "Señor de la Vara de Calavera", y su par, Ch'amiyabaq, "Señor de la Vara de Hueso."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ch&#039;amiyajolom</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>679</nid>
    <key>CHAMIYAJOLOM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chamia holom</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chamia holom</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ch&#039;ipi Kaqulja</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>645</nid>
    <key>CHIPI_KAQULJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chípa caculha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chípa caculha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Cha&#039;j</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1231</nid>
    <key>CHA'J</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/8209%20chichen%20itza%20ball%20court.jpeg?itok=QpPR_O6B" width="100" height="67" alt="Kerr #8209" title="Kerr #8209. &quot;Maya. Chichen Itza. Portion of wall of ball court. Sacrifice, beheading of ballplayer. blood.&quot; " /></image>
    <description><p>Tedlock points out that <em>cha’j</em> is used for the game ball in Xib’alb’a while <em>kik’</em><em> </em>-- which also means "blood" or "resin" --  refers only to the ball of Juajpu and Xb’alanke.  </p>

<p>Perhaps this wordplay solidifies a semantic connection for the Maya, allowing<em> kik</em><em> </em>to refer to balls and, more distantly, to humans’ interaction with the supernatural through sacrifice or ball game challenges.</p>

<p>The ball in Xib’alb’a further differs from a normal ball in that it appears to the boys to be a skull. It was previously described as being coated with crushed bone; Tedlock says that what is played off as “mere decoration” by the Lords is actually a fundamental and sinister difference.  Reference to this bone-ball as <em>kik’, </em>the word for “ball” easily associated with blood and death, seems fitting for this particular object despite the more customary use of <em>cha’j </em>for Xibalban game balls.</p>

<p><em>Ch'aj</em>, the more generic word for ball, is reserved for reference to balls used by the Lords of Xib'alb'a. Considering the connection between the <em>kik'  </em>and sacrifice, perhaps <em>cha'j</em> are used by Xib'alb'ans because there is no need for them to establish a connection with the supernatural -- they are the supernatural. The distinction bewteen <em>cha'j </em>and <em>kik' </em>further supports the idea that rubber and the ballgame represent the other mode of reaching the divine: blood and sacrifice.</p>

<p>As part of his explanation of the <a href="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=2803">ballgame imagery in vase #2803</a>, Justin Kerr includes Alexandre Tokovine's essay, "<a href="http://www.mayavase.com/alex/alexballgame.html">An Epigrapher's View</a>."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chak</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>16</nid>
    <key>KAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ꜫaꜫ</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Chak%20elk%27in.png?itok=kxcTnAG2" width="100" height="78" alt="Chak elk&#039;in" title="Chak elk&#039;in (Chak, este | Chak, east)" /></image>
    <description><p>When the Hero Twins first arrive at the crossroads of Xilbaba, they face four possible paths: the red way, black way, white way, and yellow way. Ximénez expresses these paths in colonial K'iche' as "hun ꜫaꜫabe, hun cut queca be, zaqui be hun, hun cut eana be cahib be" (14r).</p>

<p>In hieroglyphic traditions from Mesoamerica, these colors refer to the four cardinal points. The red god, Chak (Kaq in contemporary K'iche'), is associated with the east, written as "elk'in" or "elk'inh" in colonial Yukatek orthography, and "lak'iin" in contemporary spelling. Although we do not know the language of the glyphs, most scholars believe it to be Yukatekan or Ch'olan Maya (Macri and Looper, <em>New Catalog of Maya Hieroglyphs</em>, 5-9).</p>

<p>Scholarly attempts to connect cardinal points and color symbolism among Maya communities are complicated by the intervention of colonial Spanish authors, whose own cultural frameworks influenced their translations of Mayan languages. As Alexandre Tokovinine has argued, "colonial dictionaries translate <em>chak</em> as <em>rojo</em> and <em>colorado</em> (Barrera Vázquez et al. 1995:76), but the color term <em>colorado</em> means not just 'red' but 'colored,' indicating the presence of color in general." He continues to ask, "To what extent is the Spanish notion of redness imposed here on the Maya one?" ("Writing color: Words and images of colors in Classic Maya inscriptions," 286).</p>

<p>Perhaps the best way to explain the relationship between color and cardinal point is by expanding our definition of "color" -- not only, in the Spanish or English adjectival sense of "hue" or "shade" (As the <a href="http://www.rae.es">RAE</a> puts it, "Sensación producida por los rayos luminosos que impresionan los órganos visuales y que depende de la longitud de onda"), but also as it is understood within Mesoamerican conceptual frameworks. Color is a logogram -- that is, a symbol that refers to a concrete concept and object. In the case of "red," these symbolic associations encompass heat, fire, and the sun, which rises in the east (Tokovinine, "Writing color," 287-291). The red god, Chak, is represented in graphic terms with a liquid emanating from his mouth; most scholars analogize the liquid to blood (Tokovinine, "Writing color," 287).</p>

<p>As such, color serves as a mechanism through which Maya speakers situate themselves in geographic or physical space and connect with the spirit world of the nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida</em>, esp. 30-33).</p>

<p>This image of the Ch'a-Chak ceremony (return + rain) may illustrate these principles, and their deep traditions within indigenous communities of Mesoamerica:</p>

<p><img alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=7037" class="media-element file-default media-wysiwyg-align-right" data-delta="1" data-fid="168" data-media-element="1" height="135" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/kerr%207037%20possible%20cha%20cha%27k%20ceremony.jpeg" style="float:left" title="Kerr image #7037: possible rain ceremony (Ch'a-Chak)" typeof="foaf:Image" width="300" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(Kerr Database #7037; <a href="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=7037">http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=7037</a>)</p>

<p>Una vez llegados al cruce de los cuatro caminos del inframundo de Xibalba, los dos muchachos, Jun Junajpu y Xbalamke, topan con un paisaje notable: tienen que elegir entre el camino rojo, el camino negro, el camino blanco y el camino amarillo. Según explica el padre Ximénez en el idioma k’iche’, los cuatro caminos son “hun ꜫaꜫabe, hun cut queca be, zaqui be hun, hun cut eana be cahib be" (14r).</p>

<p>Cabe señalar que éstos son más que colores en el mundo maya. En la escritura jeroglífica mesoamericana, el color significa el punto cardinal. La lengua fuente de este sistema de escritura es probablemente el maya yukateko o el maya ch'ol, aunque de eso no tenemos noticia cierta (Macri y Looper, <em>New Catalog of Maya Hieroglyphs</em>, 5-9). </p>

<p>Tampoco sabemos precisamente cuál es la relación entre el color y el punto cardinal, pues las fuentes coloniales tienen varios niveles de mediación e intervención de los escritores españoles a lo largo de los siglos XVI-XVIII. Los frailes y fiscales utilizaban sus propios matices culturales para descifrar la cosmovisión maya. Como así observa Alexandre Tokovinine, citando a su vez varias investigaciones (p.e., Barrera Vázquez et al. 1995:76), los escritores coloniales solían traducir la palabra <em>chak</em> como <em>rojo</em> o <em>colorado</em>, así negando una diferencia importante entre el color bermejo-carmín (“rojo”) y la presencia de un color (“colorado”). Por lo tanto el destacado investigador nos pregunta hasta qué punto la interpretación española influye en su representación del color (“Writing color: Words and images of colors in Classic Maya inscriptions,” 286).</p>

<p>Resulta que los marcos teóricos occidentales son insuficientes para poder entender la compleja relación entre el color y el punto cardinal en el <em>Popol Vuh</em>, una de las diversas fuentes que indica que el color es cómo el mayahablante se ubica geográficamente en el entorno físico y espiritualmente en el mundo de los nawales (May K’iche’ Winaq B’elejeb’ Aj | unión de escritores mayas, <em>Raxalaj mayab' k'aslemalil | Cosmovisión maya, plenitud de la vida,</em> esp. 30-33).  Por ende, hay que expandir la definición del “color”, pues en la cosmovisión mesoamericana se entiende que el color no es un simple adjetivo que se refiere a la “Sensación producida por los rayos luminosos que impresionan los órganos visuales y que depende de la longitud de onda”, como así se define la <a href="http://www.rae.es">Real Academia Española</a>. Es más bien un logograma, o un símbolo gráfico que se refiere a un concepto y un objeto particular según las normas del particular sistema de escritura. </p>

<p>Por ejemplo, la palabra “rojo”, así matizado en términos mayas, abarca una amplia definición simbólica o metafórica en la cual el tono se asocia al calor, el fuego y el sol, que nace en el este (Tokovinine, “Writing color”, 287-291). Por tanto, el dios rojo, Chak (o Kaq en la ortografía moderna del idioma k’iche’) se asocial con el este o el oriente, mejor conocido en el idioma maya yukateko como “elk’in” o “elk’inh” (o más bien “lak’iin” en la ortografía moderna). </p>

<p>De la misma forma, el dios Chak frecuentemente tiene un líquido en la boca; debido al vínculo metafórico entre el color rojo, el punto cardinal y la fuerza divina, los investigadores deducen que el líquido es la sangre (Tokovinine, “Writing color”, 287). Esta red simbólica indica la complejidad y la riqueza de las asociaciones imaginativas, geográficas y espirituales entre el color y el punto cardinal en la cosmovisión maya.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chamalkan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>726</nid>
    <key>CHAMALKAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chamalcan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chamalcan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chi Chaq&#039;</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1173</nid>
    <key>CHI_CHAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chíchat</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chiq chac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the four divisions of the citadel of Chi K'ix. </p>

<p>Colop (página 189, nota 316) ofrece dos posibilidades para su traducción: "lugar seco" y "lugar mojado, en referencia directa a alguno de los sitios ubicados a la orilla del río que atraviesa el lugar."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chi K&#039;ix</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1172</nid>
    <key>CHI_KIX</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quix</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chiquix</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The citadel founded by the sons of the forefathers after abandoning Jaqawitz. </p>

<p>Colop (página 189, nota 314) traduce el nombre como "lugar de las espinas." Cita a Alain Ichon, diciendo, "sería el sitio <em>Kawinal </em>ubicado en ambas márgenes de río Blanco a unos 3 kilómetros antes de confluir con el río Negro o Chixoy, en jurisdicción de Cubulco, Baja Verapaz."</p>

<p>También según Colop (página 189, nota 315) la ciudadela se dividía en cuatro secciones o "montañas," enumeradas más adelante. </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chi Pixab</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>753</nid>
    <key>CHI_PIXAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> çerro de el mandaro</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chi pixab </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Mountain on whose top the K'iche's and other lineages met to hold counsel. Later the site of the forefathers' fast while waiting for the arrival of the sun.</p>

<p>Colop (página 150, nota 241) lo traduce como "lugar del consejo." Así es que el nombre resalta uno de los principios y valores mayas, según consta José Yac Noj en su presentación <em>Orientaciones Pedagógicas Salud y Nutrición Raxalaj K’aslemalil. Ukab’Ruk’u’xTijonik</em>, Segundo Básico, ACEM. Maya Na’oj 2012). "Pixab'" significa "tomo consejo, tomar consejo."</p>

<p>Christenson (page 220, note 577) translates Chi Pixab as "Place of Counsel or Instruction." He goes on to note, "Carmack identifies this as a mountain on the border between San Andrés Sajcabaja and San Bartolomé Jocotenango (Carmack 1981, 66). Here the nearby territory was divided between the major lineage groups—the Quichés, Tamub, and Ilocab settled the region to the north, centered on the mountain of Hacavitz [Jaqawitz]; the Ah Tsiquinahas (Tz'utuhils) settled the coastlands around Lake Atitlán; the Rabinals chose the mountains of the Rabinal basin to the east. The Cakchiquels at this time served as a lineage of vassal warriors and occupied a band of territory sitauted between the Quichés and and the Ah Tziquinahas, centered on the mountains above Chichicastenango. These mountain redoubts were apparently chosen for their defensive potential."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chichicastenango</title>
    <type>lugar</type>
    <nid>1062</nid>
    <key>CHICHICASTENANGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>EL REAL PATRONATO DEL PUEBLO DE STO. THOMAS CHÍCHÍCASTENANGO</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Santo_Tomas_Church%2C_Chichicastenango.jpg?itok=zNXPQRuc" width="75" height="100" alt="Iglesia de Santo Tomás, Chichistenango, Guatemala. Photo by ManfredWinslow, Wikimedia Commons." title="Iglesia de Santo Tomás, Chichistenango, Guatemala. Photo by ManfredWinslow, Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, known today simply as Chichicastenango, is a town in the Guatemalan highlands. Fray Francisco Ximénez was a parish priest in Chichicastenango when he compiled the manuscript of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> presented here in 1701 and 1702. Then as now, the population of Chichicastenango is majority K'iche'. Ximénez writes in his <em>Historia de la provincia</em> (folio 1, side 1) that it was in this town that he encountered the "Historias" that we now call the <em>Popol Vuh</em>: "estando en el Curato de Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, hallé que era la Doctrina que primero mamaban con la leche y que todos ellos casi lo tienen de memoria" (folio 1, side 1).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chimalmat</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>659</nid>
    <key>CHIMALMAT</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chimalmat</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chimalmat</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Según informa Sam Colop (2011: nota 55, página 210), "Chimalmat es palabra k'iche'; <em>chi</em> es preposición y <em>malmatik</em> es verbo que indica correr detrás de algo. D. Tedlock (1996: 241) asocia a Chimalmat con la 'Osa Menor', lo cual concuerca con su pareja Wuqub Kak'ix, 'Osa Mayor'".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 170, page 83) disagrees with Colop. He suggests that the name Chimalmat "is almost certainly derived from the Nahuatl chimalmatl, meaning 'shield bearer,' a fairly common name for female deities. In Aztec legend, she was the mother of the Toltec priest-ruler Ce Acatl Topiltzin Quetzalcoatl. Chimalmat is also one of the names for the mother of the Aztecs’ patron god, Huitzilopochtli, as well as the female bearer of cult objects in Aztec migration accounts. Alternatively, the name may be Quiché in origin, consisting of <em>chi</em> (preposition “at, in, to, on, from, etc.) and <em>malmat</em> (Basseta: to walk with haste) or <em>malmot</em> (Coto: “to appear unexpectedly,” particularly with regard to a phantasm)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chipi Kakulja</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>15</nid>
    <key>CHIPI_CACULHA</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chipicaculha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Chomija&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>709</nid>
    <key>CHOMIJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chumíha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chumíha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Corazón del lago</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>637</nid>
    <key>CORAZÓN_DEL_LAGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa> vguxcho</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vqux cho </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>En el actual idioma k'iche', se escribe el título "corazón del lago", según apunta Sam Colop en su versión poética del texto (1999: 2), "Uk'ux Cho." De forma paralela, el título "corazón del mar", el cual también se refiere al poder del dios creador Q'ukumatz, será "Uk'ux Palo."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 21, page 53) connects these sacred attributes, "Heart of the Lake, Heart of the Sky," with what are perhaps "titles for Sovereign and Quetzal Serpent, who are associated with water (see p. 68; lines 140-143; Recinos and Goetz 1953b, 76). <em>K'ux</em> may refer to either 'heart' or 'spirit.' This pair of deities thus embodies the inward powers of large, standing bodies of water. The <em>Popol Vuh</em> states that prior to the creation the world consisted of a vast expanse of placid waters from which all things emerged (p. 67; lines 129-136).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Corazón del mar</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>638</nid>
    <key>CORAZÓN_DEL_MAR</key>
    <ximenez_spa> vguxpalo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vqux palo </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>En el actual idioma k'iche', se escribe el título "corazón del mar", según apunta Sam Colop en su versión poética del texto (1999: 2), "Uk'ux Palo." De forma paralela, el título "corazón del lago", el cual también se refiere al poder del dios creador Q'ukumatz, será "Uk'ux Cho."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 21, page 53) connects these sacred attributes, "Heart of the Lake, Heart of the Sky," with what are perhaps "titles for Sovereign and Quetzal Serpent, who are associated with water (see p. 68; lines 140-143; Recinos and Goetz 1953b, 76). <em>K'ux</em> may refer to either 'heart' or 'spirit.' This pair of deities thus embodies the inward powers of large, standing bodies of water. The <em>Popol Vuh</em> states that prior to the creation the world consisted of a vast expanse of placid waters from which all things emerged (p. 67; lines 129-136)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Cuatro Casas Grandes</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>1010</nid>
    <key>CUATRO_CASAS_GRANDES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quatro casas grandes</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The Lords of the Four Great Houses are Ajtzik Winaq Ajaw, Lolmet Ajaw, Nim Ch'okoj Ajaw, and Jaqawitz.</p>

<p>With the three Great Houses that preceed them in the text -- Kaweq, Ajaw K'iche', Nija'ib -- the final section of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> reaffirms the number seven.</p>

<p>In Mayan epigraphic systems, the number seven is represented as a large scroll that passes underneath the eye and curls under the forehead. This image and its numeral signifier is repeated in several buildings of the Dzibilchaltun (Writing Upon Stone) site in Yucatán, most notably the Seven Dolls Complex. Dzibilchaltun is located 21 kilometers from the present-day center of Mérida, Yucatán. For an extensive discussion of Maya numbers, mathematics, and cosmological repetition, see Colin Renfrew and Iain Morley's edited volume <em>The Archaeology of Measurement: Comprehending Heaven, Earth and Time in Ancient Societies</em> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Dan</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>905</nid>
    <key>DAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Dan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Dan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>This “pueblo” of Dan is not found in subsequent translations of the <em>Popol Wuj </em>like that of Adrián Recinos or Sam Colop. In addition, the name is not phonetically consistent with toponyms or lineages in K’iche’. While the origin and exact meaning of this reference is unknown, Ximénez cited Dan’s appearance in the <em>Popol Wuj</em> in his other works as a way of supporting his theory on the place of native peoples in Christian salvation history.</p>

<p>In the <em>dedicatoria, prólogo y notas</em> to his <em>Primera parte del Tesoro de las Lenguas Cakchiquel, Quiché y Zutuhil, en que las dichas Lenguas se traducen a la nuestra, española</em>, Ximénez lays out his belief that the peoples of Guatemala and Mexico descend from the tribe of Dan, one of the twelve biblical tribes of Israel. “[S]upuesto de que ella provienen todas las tribus deste reino de Guatemala y de el de México, como ellos dicen en sus ‘historias’” (a reference to the “historias” we now call the <em>Popol Vuh</em>), he writes,  the tribe of Dan’s conspicuous absence from the enumeration of the elect in the book of Revelation makes sense. He continues, “son muy pocos o ningunos los que ellos se salvan…no hay duda que es muy especial el modo que Dios tiene en salvar a éstos y muy recóndito al entendimiento humano” (Edición Academia de Geografía e Historia de Guatemala, 1985, folios 3 verso and 4 recto). For Ximénez, it appears that a link between the tribe of Dan and the native peoples of Guatemala and Mexico could explain the exclusion of both groups from salvation history as he knew it.</p>

<p>It is quite likely that, in whatever K'iche' source Ximénez may have been working from, "Dan" was a reference to Amaq' Tan, the territory of the Tamub lineage in the region settled by the K'iche' forefathers. Ximénez may have assumed "Tan"<em> </em>to be a corruption of "Dan," or even deliberately altered it to provide evidence for his theory of the Israelite origins of the K'iche'.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Dios</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1068</nid>
    <key>DIOS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Díos</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>God is the sole deity in Christian theology (among others), in which he consists in a Trinity of three Persons: Father, Son (or Jesus Christ), and Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>The compiler of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> manuscript, Fray Francisco Ximénez, was a Catholic priest. Catholic beliefs on God are summarized in the religion's statement of faith, also known as the <a href="http://www.usccb.org/beliefs-and-teachings/what-we-believe/index.cfm">Credo or Nicene Creed</a>.</p>

<p>Dios es la única deidad en la teología cristiana (entre otras), en la cual consiste en una Trinidad de tres Personas: Padre, Hijo (o Jesucristo), y el Espíritu Santo.</p>

<p>El compilador del manuscrito del <em>Popol Vuh</em>, Fray Francisco Ximénez, era un sacerdote católico. Las creencias católicas sobre Dios se puede encontrar resumidos en su profesión de fe, mejor conocida como el <a href="http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism_sp/p1s1c3a2_sp.html#El credo">Credo o el Credo Niceno</a>.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Domingo</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1142</nid>
    <key>DOMINGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Domgo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/domingo.jpg?itok=toEnsskh" width="71" height="100" alt="Saint Dominic by Fra Angelico" title="Saint Dominic by Fra Angelico" /></image>
    <description><p>Saint Dominic (1170–1221) was the founder of the Order of Preachers.</p>

<p>Santo Domingo (1170–1221) era el fundador del Orden de Predicadores.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Don Cristóbal</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>965</nid>
    <key>DON_CRISTÓBAL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Don chrístoual</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Don christoual</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Don Pedro de Robles</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>967</nid>
    <key>DON_PEDRO_DE_ROBLES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Don Po. de Robles. es el q’Reyn agora</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>D. Pedro de robles ahau ꜫalel</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"Pedro de Robles is known to have taken office soon after 1554, therefore the <em>Popol Vuh</em> must have been written sometime between the years 1554 and 1558" (Christenson 2007: 29, "History of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> Manuscript.")</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Donadiu</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1276</nid>
    <key>DONADIU</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Aluarado</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Donadiu</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/225px-Alvarado.jpeg?itok=g2hq_6b4" width="56" height="100" alt="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_de_Alvarado" title="Retrato de Alvarado con la cruz de la Orden de Santiago." /></image>
    <description><p>Según apunta Sam Colop (nota 390, página 259): "Tonatiuh conforme al diccionario de Karttunen (1992) quiere decir 'el Sol' y nos refiere a tóna que quiere decir 'hacer calor o Sol'. Probablemente, el sobrenombre de Pedro de Alvarado no se refiera al color de su cabello, como tradicionalmente se ha dicho, sino a su práctica de 'quemar' a sus víctimas".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 857, page 278) also notes the conflation of "T" and "D" sounds in the name that Ximénez writes as "Tonatiuh", or "Don Alvarado" in modern Spanish orthography. He writes: "Donadiu (or Tonatiu) was the name given to Don Pedro de Alvarado, the Spanish captain of Hernán Cortés who conquered the highland Maya region of what is today Guatemala. This is the Quiché Maya version of Tonatiuh (Nahua for 'sun, heat'), the name by which Alvarado was known to the Aztecs and his Tlaxcalan mercenaries. He likely received this nickname because of his blonde hair, a physical trait unknown in the Precolumbian New World (other than albinos, which are still called 'children of the sun' in many Quiché communities). The name may have had further significance for the Quichés, however. Earlier in the <em>Popol Vuh</em> text, the appearance of a new sun represented the death of the old world and the establishment of new, divinely-sanctioned political power. Alvarado as the new 'sun' destroys the old world and its gods inaugurating a new age. For this reason, Jesus Christ as the newly-established patron deity is equated with the sun throughout the Maya world (La Farge and Byers 1931, 113-114; La Farge 1947, 104; Mace 1970, 24; Thompson 1970, 234; Vogt 1970, 4; Morley et al. 1983, 465; Cook 1986, 140, 148; Tarn and Prechtel 1986, 174, 180-181; Freidel et al. 1993, 292; Cook 2000, 215-219)."</p>

<p>Such syncretic readings of the past are not limited to Santa Cruz del K'iche'. Christenson (2007: note 857, page 278) continues, "At Jacaltenango, there is a myth for the foundation of the town in which Christ’s birth is associated with the first rise of the sun, whose rays kill his enemies who had tried to hide in caves and under water. This allows Jacaltenango to be founded in the center of the world. La Farge and Byers suggest that this myth is a syncretized version of the account of the dawn in the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, which also ended the previous age and turned its inhabitants to stone (La Farge and Byers 1931, 113-114)."</p>

<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--v2OYi2Q3Rk/UOMg59R2pMI/AAAAAAAABQI/NDLSHeaGY6k/s1600/MNU2013-01-01_1_Santiago-Atitlan_Altarpiece_IM-Allen-Christenson.bmp">"At Santiago Atitlán, Maya sculptors carved a vessel bearing a sun on the left and right sides of the community’s colonial era church altarpiece</a>. In his explanation of the sun vessels, one of the sculptors, Diego Chávez Petzey, said that the sun on the left represents a tortilla, because maize is the Maya 'sun.' The sun on the right is the Christian eucharistic Host. He went on to say that life cannot exist without sacrifice. Maize must be crushed on a grinding stone before it can be made into tortillas. The wheat in the sacramental Host must also be ground and baked. The sun can only rise in the east after it has been buried in the west: 'Tortillas, the Host, Jesus Christ, and the sun give life because they are first killed. Tortillas and bread result from the death of maize and wheat so that they can give us life. They are therefore gods.' Nicolás Chávez Sojuel, who also worked on the altarpiece carvings, told me that when the Spaniards came the earth died along with the ancient gods and kings. When I asked him how the world could die, he replied: 'The earth has died many times. Each time the world and its gods are reborn to new life and they regain their former power and new gods are added .... The saints today have Spanish names because the old earth died in the days of the Spanish conquerors. When the spirit keepers of the world appeared again they were the saints, but they do the same work that the old gods did anciently' (<a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=mHxaBAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Christenson 2001</a>, 135)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>dos muchachos</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>666</nid>
    <key>DOS_MUCHACHOS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>dos muchachos</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caib qaholab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Echave</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1156</nid>
    <key>ECHAVE</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The Newberry Library <a href="https://i-share.carli.illinois.edu/nby/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?DB=local&amp;v1=1&amp;BBRecID=137083">catalog record</a> for the Ximénez manuscript describes Escolio 5 verso as “an apostrophe praising the Dominican Order, dated Aug. 14, 1734 and signed ‘Echave’.” According to Ruud van Akkeren, “El mencionado Echave es fray Ignacio de Echave. Aparece por primera vez el 20 de julio 1732 y por última vez el 4 de diciembre 1735.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>el baño de Tojil</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>834</nid>
    <key>EL_BAÑO_DE_TOJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>baño de el tohíl</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ratinibal tohil</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>A river at which Tojil, Awilix, and Jaqawitz came to bathe in human form.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Escarbador</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>649</nid>
    <key>ESCARBADOR</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xecotcovach</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xe cotcovach </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Espíritu Santo</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1071</nid>
    <key>ESPIRITU_SANTO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el espírítu Sto.</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez refers to the Holy Spirit as "el espíritu Sto.," "el espíritu de Díos" or "la tercera persona de la Santísima Trinidad." The Holy Spirit is characterized as the creative force of God in the biblical text of Genesis, which Ximénez compares to the creation account that begins the <em>Popol Vuh</em>.</p>

<p>In Christianity, the Holy Spirit is the third Person of the Trinity. The Catholic statement of faith, or Nicene Creed, says of the Holy Spirit:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the giver of life,<br />
who proceeds from the Father and the Son,<br />
who with the Father and the Son is adored and glorified,<br />
who has spoken through the prophets.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>En el cristianismo, el Espíritu Santo es la tercera persona de la Trinidad. La profesión de la fe católica dice de él:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Creo en el Espíritu Santo,<br />
Señor y dador de vida,<br />
que procede del Padre y del Hijo,<br />
que con el Padre y el Hijo recibe<br />
una misma adoración y gloria,<br />
y que habló por los profetas.</p>
</blockquote></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Fray Alonso de Noreña</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1104</nid>
    <key>NORENA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>N. Pe. Noreña</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Fray Alonso de Noreña, O.P. was the provincial superior (or prior provincial) of Guatemala. His most significant work was <a href="https://archive.org/details/fratrisalphonsiv00alon">a collaboration with Augustinian friar Alonso de Vera Cruz</a> on the practices of various mendicant orders in Spanish America.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Fray Domingo de Vico</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1096</nid>
    <key>VICO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Domíngo de Víco</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Fray Domingo de Vico, O.P. (d. 1555) was a Dominican friar who was assigned to work with Fray Bartolomé de las Casas to enforce the reformatory New Laws of 1542. De Vico wrote three works that were influential for Ximénez: <em>Theologia Indorum</em> (<em>Theology of the Indians</em>); a treatise on evangelization in Guatemala called <em>Tratado de ídolos</em> (<em>Treatment of Idols</em>), and a dictionary of the Kaqchikel language. In his own works, Ximénez responded to de Vico's work, occasionally citing it (as in his theological treatises) and often challenging it (as in his linguistic studies).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Fray Juan de San José</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1093</nid>
    <key>FRAY_JUAN_DE_SAN_JOSE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>R. Pe. fr. Juo.-de S. Joseph</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Fray Juan de San José seems to have been one of Ximénez's mentors in Guatemala. Amid this discussion of how to handle the possible demonic dangers in K'iche' celebrations, Ximénez mentions his advise: "me lo aconsejo así un Relígíoso docto, y de exemplar vída, q'auía gastado muchos aS. admínístrando índíos q'murío ya decrepíto llamado el R. Pe. fr. Juo.-de S. Joseph demí sagrado hauíto."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Guatemala</title>
    <type>lugar</type>
    <nid>1078</nid>
    <key>GUATEMALA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Reyno de Gualta.</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The "Kingdom of Guatemala" (which Ximénez refers to as "Reyno de Gualta.") was an administrative division of the Spanish Empire, officially established in 1609.</p>

<p>El "Reino de Guatemala" (que Ximénez escribe como "Reyno de Gualta.") era una división administrativa del Imperio Español, oficialmente establecido en 1609.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Hermanos Artesanos</title>
    <type>grupo de deidades</type>
    <nid>909</nid>
    <key>HERMANOS_ARTESANOS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun batz y hun chouen</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun batz hun chouen</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Recinos (1949: segunda parte, nota 4) cita la definición léxica del <em>Diccionario de Motul</em>, la cual indica que "Ah chuen, en maya, significa artesano."</p>

<p>Por su parte, Sam Colop (2008: nota 71) apunta que <em>Batz'</em> es "un día del calendario" y <em>Chowen</em> "es su equivalente en idioma yucateco."</p>

<p>Los sabios abuelos Jun Junajpu e Ixbaqiyalo les enseñaban "las artes y el trabajo," tal como Sam Colop (2008: 62) traduce la expresión del idioma k'iche' al castellano, incluso las artes bellas (la música, la escritura-pintura) y las artes técnicas (la ofebrería en plata, oro y sagradas piedras preciosas como el jade). Cabe recordar que en el idioma k'iche' el dominio de las letras, mejor conocida como <em>ajtz'ib</em>, abarca toda clase de literalidades gráficas o "escritura sin letra", como así la denomina Walter Mignolo (2003: 319).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Hombres de maíz</title>
    <type>grupo de deidades</type>
    <nid>1265</nid>
    <key>HOMBRES_DE_MAIZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>los primeros hombres q’fueron formados</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%20database%200634.jpeg?itok=hvZ6ygsd" width="100" height="33" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=634" title="Kerr vase #634. “A vase carved to resemble a woven basket. The motif is the Maize God being reborn from a split in the earth. The ajaw glyph substitutes for the turtle carapace or ballcourt. Compare with K5226 and K5761.”" /></image>
    <description><p>The importance of maize to Mayan cultures is well represented in the <em>Popol Wuj</em>. Below we provide insights from other primary and secondary sources so that readers may appreciate the profound technological and sociohistorical implications of maize cultivation in daily life and spiritual paths, including the creation of the first human beings -- "las primeras gentes creadas y formadas," Balam Ki'tze', Balam Aq'ab, Majuk'utaj, e Ik'i Balam (Colop 2011: 130).</p>

<p>Although the exact date of the beginning of corn cultivation in Mesoamerica is still uncertain, scholars have estimated that it was widely cultivated in northern Belize by 3400 B.C.; however, this date leaves some 2400 years between the first traces of nomadic agriculture in the region and the appearance of early sedentary Maya cultures founded on the systematic cultivation of maize (García Marín 102-103). In his study of the use of plants in Classic Mayan cave rituals, Christopher T. Morehart highlights the correlation between the intense population growths seen during the Late Classic period and the expanded distribution of Chapalote-Nal Tel, a group of maize varietals featuring short ears and eight to twelve rows of kernels. Specifically, as Morehart proposes, the shorter maturation period of those varietals would have allowed the potential for multiple harvests per year and a higher annual yield of maize (7).</p>

<p>Technology plays a crucial if often overlooked role in the development and expansion of Mayan civilizations. Of specific interest here are two separate but related technological discoveries that most significantly impacted the successful growth of Mayan societies: the production of lime and the development of nixtamalization, the process through which limewater is used to remove mycotoxins from maize. Scholars such as Michael D. Coe have convincingly argued that without the development of the <em>nixtamal </em>process, the establishment of settled civilizations in Mesoamerica would have been difficult, if not impossible (13). As Michael Blake points out, the routine consumption of non-nixtamalized maize can result in severe protein and vitamin B deficiency; however, “ancient Americans must have solved this problem…because otherwise they would not have been able to rely on maize” as the primary nutritional source of their diet” (184). Lori E. Wright also notes that the process substantially increases the calcium content in maize, which remains the primary source of calcium in many modern Mayan communities (206). Thus, the transformation of maize was an essential discovery that allowed for the sustained nourishment of Mayan peoples and ultimately enabled permanent communities to be established. In addition, as Isabel Villaseñor Alonso and Luis Barba Pingarrón point out, the production of lime used in the nixtamalization process was no minor accomplishment, as:</p>

<p>“La producción de cal requiere del entendimiento empírico de las transformaciones que sufre el material calcáreo durante su producción, así como también del dominio del fuego y de la obtención y control de altas temperaturas para lograr alta eficiencia en los cambios químicos que se llevan a cabo durante la  calcinación. Debido al tiempo de exposición y a las altas temperaturas que requiere este material, la producción de cal es una actividad demandante de combustible y fuerza laboral” (12).</p>

<p>Thus, the notion of <em>hombres de maíz </em>at the center of the <em>Popol Wuj </em>is not only indicative of the spiritual significance and respect that the Maya have for maize; it also speaks to the importance of the technological advancements perfected by early Mayan communities to ensure the development and subsequent expansion of their civilization.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>ictericia</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>677</nid>
    <key>ICTERICIA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>chuꜫanal</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chuꜫanal</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ik&#039;ibalam</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>707</nid>
    <key>IKIBALAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Iquibalam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Iquibalam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ik&#039;oq&#039;ij</title>
    <type></type>
    <nid>882</nid>
    <key></key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ik&#039;oq&#039;ij</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1161</nid>
    <key>IKOQIJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>luzero</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>icoquih</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/calendario%20maya.png?itok=LTRwVVhc" width="100" height="94" /></image>
    <description><p>This astronym probably refers to Venus, the morning star and an important entity in Mesoamerican cosmology. </p>

<p>As Christenson (2007: 205) points out, K'iche' people, like central Mexican intellectuals and other Maya communities, were well-known as astrologers and observers of the constelations. They connected their observations of the cosmos to the practices of daily life, and used micro- and macrological correspondences to create order and balance in a chaotic world.</p>

<p>The appearance of the Ik'oq'ij star illustrates this tendency. According to Christenson, <em>Ik'oq'ij  </em>means "Accompanies/Bears/Passes Before Sun," indicating that K'iche' observers saw "the planet Venus as morning star." He goes on to cite Bartolomé de Las Casas, who wrote that “after the sun, which they held as their principal god, they honored and worshiped a certain star (I could not learn which star this was) more than any other denizen of the heavens or earth, because they held it as certain that their god,  Quezalcóvatl, the highest god of the Cholulans, when he died transformed into this star" (Las Casas 1967: III, clxxiv, p. 201; cited in Christenson 2007: 205).</p>

<p>Justin Kerr's database includes some <a href="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_list.php?rowstart=10&amp;search=&amp;vase_number=&amp;date_added=&amp;vase_type=&amp;ms_number=&amp;site=&amp;icon_elements=Venus%20glyph,%20star%20glyph%20T510&amp;display=10">28 images of the Venus Star constellation</a>. Below we include one, image #3034 ("Museum number 1986.2.10 Rio Hondo style full face version of the water lily jaguar with star signs. The glyph for jaguar appears in the eyes. <a href="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1652">See K 1652 for codex style version of this jaguar</a>.")</p>

<p><img alt="Kerr #3034. Museum number 1986.2.10 Rio Hondo style full face version of the water lily jaguar with star signs. The glyph for jaguar appears in the eyes. See K 1652 for codex style version of this jaguar." class="media-element file-default" data-delta="1" data-fid="234" data-media-element="1" height="228" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/3034.jpeg" title="Kerr #3034. Museum number 1986.2.10 Rio Hondo style full face version of the water lily jaguar with star signs. The glyph for jaguar appears in the eyes.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=3034" typeof="foaf:Image" width="550" /></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ilokab</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>815</nid>
    <key>ILOKAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ílocab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ílocab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Istayul_Nija&#039;ib</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>841</nid>
    <key>ISTAYUL_NIJAIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>íztayul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>íztayul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: 283) writes the name of the 7th Lord of the Nija'ib line as "Iztayul." There is also an Istayul or Iztayul who is the 5th generation of the family line of Balam K'onache'.</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixbaqiyalo</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>671</nid>
    <key>IXBAQIYALO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xbaquíyalo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xbaquíyalo</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixkakaw e</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>691</nid>
    <key>IXKAKAW_E</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xcacauix</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xcacauíx </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixkik&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>688</nid>
    <key>IXKIK</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xquic</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xquíc </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixmukane</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>642</nid>
    <key>IXMUKANE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Xmucane</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Xmucane</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/xmukane%20co%CC%81dice%20dresde%20folio%2074.jpg?itok=GF8wUGsx" width="100" height="78" alt="Ixmukane&#039;" title="Ixmukane, Códice Dresde, f. 74" /></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2011: nota 8, página 202) explica el significado del nombre de la abuela, según la traducción del padre Ximénez, "quiere decir 'entierro o fosa'". Por su parte Adrián Recinos (1953: 83) afirma que "estos nombres equivalen a 'los dios mexicanos Cipactonal y Oxmoco, los sabios que según la leyenda tolteca inventaron la astrología judiciaria y compusieron la cuenta de los tiempos, o sea el calendario'. Edmonson (1971: 5) asocia estos nombres a los términos náhuatl <em>yexpoacoc</em> y <em>yexomocane</em> que traduce como 'bisabuelo', 'bisabuela' y agrega que es extraño que al nombrar al orden usual k'iche'; por lo que sugiere revertir el order en una eentual reconstrucción de estos nombres." Cita a Munro Edmonson, <em>The Book of Counsel: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute. Publicación número 35. New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971.</p>

<p>According to Allen Christenson (2007: note 27, pp. 54-55), "The name <em>Xmucane</em> may be derived from <em>x-</em> (feminine marker, diminutive) plus muqik (to bury, to cover, plant in the ground), thus giving a possible reading of 'She Who Buries or She Who Plants,' referring to the planting of a seed in the earth or a developing child in the womb. Ximénez wrote that native priests in his day called upon Xmucane and Xpiyacoc for inspiration, particularly concerning the birth of infants and midwifery (Ximénez 1929-31, I.i.6). Alternatively the name may be derived from the verb<em> muqunik</em> (to see, look). Xmucane and Xpiyacoc are referred to as seers several times in the text (see pp. 79- 80; lines 511-517; 522-23). Akkeren suggests that the name should be derived from Yucatec and read as 'Curved/Buried is your Tail.' He associates her with a scorpion deity based on the name of a scorpion textile motif at Rabinal—<em>muqje</em> (tail in highland Maya languages is <em>je</em>, however its lowland Maya equivalent is <em>ne</em>), as well as an entry in the Ritual of the Bacabs referring to a scorpion entity as <em>bul moc a ne</em> (well-curved is your tail) (Arzápalo Marín 1987, 385-386; Akkeren 2000, 262-264). It may be fruitless to seek for a single meaning for such deity names as these. Particularly with regard to names and archaic words used in ceremonial contexts, Quichés derive a host of meanings from them, including puns and other word plays. Thus Barbara Tedlock points out that each named day in the traditional highland Maya calendar has a range of potential meanings, all of which are equally valid depending on context. For example, in interpreting a divinatory outcome, the meaning of the day <em>C'at</em> may be derived from <em>c'atic</em> (to burn), <em>pa c'at</em> (in nets), or <em>c'asaj c'olic</em> (to be in debt) (B. Tedlock 1982, 110). This is one reason I prefer to leave such names untranslated. Xmucane is likely the Quiché version of the grandmother goddess of the Maya lowlands (Goddess O, Chac Chel, Ix Chel). Like God N, the grandmother Goddess O is associated both with the forces of destruction and creation. On folio 74 of the Dresden Codex she is shown pouring out water from an inverted jar, symbolic of the destruction of the world by flood (Lee 1985, 77; Taube 1992, 101; Thompson 1972, 99). A skeletized version of this goddess wearing a crossed-bone skirt is paired with God N on the columns of the Lower Temple of the Jaguars at Chichen Itza. She is paired with God N as well on the upper columns of the Temple of the Warriors, suggesting a close association. Despite her destructive aspect, Goddess O is also considered the great creatrix, the principle deity of creation, divination, medicine, childbirth, midwifery, and weaving (Tozzer 1941, 129, 154; Taube 1992, 101; Akkeren 2000, 241), all aspects characteristic of the grandmother goddess Xmucane."</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixpuch&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>728</nid>
    <key>IXPUCH</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xpuch</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xpuch</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixq&#039;anil</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>690</nid>
    <key>IXQANIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xcanil</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xcanil</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixtaj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>727</nid>
    <key>IXTAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xtah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xtah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixtoj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>689</nid>
    <key>IXTOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xtoh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xtoh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ixtziya&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>692</nid>
    <key>IXTZIYA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> tu q&#039;eres</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tziya </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>jaguar batidor</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>652</nid>
    <key>JAGUAR_BATIDOR</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tucumbalam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tucumbalam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>jaguar masticador</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>651</nid>
    <key>JAGUAR_MASTICADOR</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cotzbalam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cotzbalam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jaqawitz</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>831</nid>
    <key>LUGAR_DE_JAQAWITZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> zero hacauítz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caꜫha hacavitz </ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/370px-Postclassicguatemalahighlands.png?itok=8A3d00n8" width="100" height="68" alt="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitinamit" title="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitinamit" /></image>
    <description><p>The mountain on which Jaqawitz, the god given to Majukutaj, was deposited, and where the K'iche' forefathers constructed their first permanent settlement. This site became the most important early center of the K'iche' kingdom. </p>

<p>Christenson (page 224, note 585) notes, "<em>Jakawitz </em>in Cholan languages means 'First/Beginning Mountain' tying it to the first mountain of creation. In Quiché, the verb <em>jaq </em>means "to open," which may recall the mountain of Paxil (Split Mountain) that contained the maize used to create the first human beings.</p>

<p>In the <em>Título Yax </em>(Carmack and Moldoch 1989, folio 2r, 107 n. 135), which is far more consistent in its use of the modified Latin alphaebet developed by Father Francisco de la Parra in the sixteenth century and used by scribes throughout highland Guatemala, the name of the deity placed on the mountain is Q'aq'awitz (Fire Mountain). This suggests that Hacavitz, like Tohil, is primarily a fire deity. This reading is also consisten with the description of his mountain, <em>nima q'aq' ja </em>(great fire house).</p>

<p>Christenson's interpretation here is perhaps slightly at odds with Carmack, who believes Jaqawitz to be a version of a Gulf Coast merchant diety.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jaqawitz</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>719</nid>
    <key>JAQAWITZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> hacauítz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hacauitz </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Carmack (1981: page 50) says this diety "was possibly related to the merchant deity of the Gulf Coast peoples. The <em>Popol </em><em>Vuh </em>informs us that bees and wasps were the symbol of this god, just as they represented the merchant deity of the coastal peoples."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jesucristo</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1069</nid>
    <key>JESUCRISTO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Xpto.</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/402px-Cristo_crucificado.jpg?itok=aF-7tHGS" width="67" height="100" alt="Cristo crucificado, de Diego Velázquez, c. 1632" title="Cristo crucificado, de Diego Velázquez, c. 1632. Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez uses the abbreviation "Xpto." for "Cristo" or "Christ," originating in the Greek word "<em>Χριστός</em>" ("Christós").</p>

<p>In Christianity, Jesus Christ is the son of God and redeemer of humanity. The Catholic statement of belief professed by this text's author, Francisco Ximénez, reads:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I believe in one Lord Jesus Christ,<br />
the Only Begotten Son of God,<br />
born of the Father before all ages.<br />
God from God, Light from Light,<br />
true God from true God,<br />
begotten, not made, consubstantial with the Father;<br />
through him all things were made.<br />
For us men and for our salvation<br />
he came down from heaven,<br />
and by the Holy Spirit was incarnate of the Virgin Mary,<br />
and became man.<br />
For our sake he was crucified under Pontius Pilate,<br />
he suffered death and was buried,<br />
and rose again on the third day<br />
in accordance with the Scriptures.<br />
He ascended into heaven<br />
and is seated at the right hand of the Father.<br />
He will come again in glory<br />
to judge the living and the dead<br />
and his kingdom will have no end.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>En el cristianismo, Jesucristo es el hijo de Dios y el redentor de la humanidad. La profesión de la fe católica, apoyada por el autor de este texto, Fray Francisco Ximénez, dice:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Creo en un solo Señor, Jesucristo,<br />
Hijo único de Dios,<br />
nacido del Padre antes de todos los<br />
siglos: Dios de Dios, Luz de Luz,<br />
Dios verdadero de Dios verdadero,<br />
engendrado, no creado,<br />
de la misma naturaleza del Padre,<br />
por quien todo fue hecho;<br />
que por nosotros, los hombres, y<br />
por nuestra salvación bajó del cielo,<br />
y por obra del Espíritu Santo se<br />
encarnó de María, la Virgen, y se<br />
hizo hombre;<br />
y por nuestra causa fue crucificado<br />
en tiempos de Poncio Pilato;<br />
padeció<br />
y fue sepultado,<br />
y resucitó al tercer día, según las<br />
Escrituras,<br />
y subió al cielo,<br />
y está sentado a la derecha del Padre;<br />
y de nuevo vendrá con gloria para<br />
juzgar a vivos y muertos,<br />
y su reino no tendrá fin.</p>
</blockquote></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1090</nid>
    <key>SEPULVEDA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el Doctor Sepulueda</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Juan_Gine%CC%81s_de_Sepu%CC%81lveda.jpg?itok=s5hoeKAf" width="61" height="100" alt="Retrato de Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda, 1791." title="Retrato de Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda, 1791. Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda (1494–1573) was a theologian and philosopher. He famously debated Bartolomé de las Casas at Valladolid, defending the enslavement of indigenous peoples.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Julisnab</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1045</nid>
    <key>JULISNAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>huliznab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>huliznab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. According to Christenson (page 96, note 176), "the identity of this mountain is unknown. Edmondson identifies it with Tajumulco, a volcano in the district of Huehuetenango, Guatemala."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Julisnab</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>665</nid>
    <key>JULISNAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>huliznab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>huliznab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jumeta Ja</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1175</nid>
    <key>JUMETA_JA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>humetabs</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>humetaha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the four divisions of the citadel of Chi K'ix.</p>

<p>Colop (página 189, nota 316) lo traduce como "corteza del río," pero añade que se puede leerlo también como "casa de corteza de árbol."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Batz&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>669</nid>
    <key>JUN_BATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun batz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun batz</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2870a%20hun%20batz.jpeg?itok=ZhOT0MGX" width="74" height="100" alt="Kerr #2870a" title="Kerr #2870a. &quot;Maya. stone. height 55.6 cm Excavated Copan structure 9N-82. Monkey scribe, Pauahtun. He sits with paint brush and shell paint container... Published The Blood of Kings p. 151. See 2870b &amp; c for other views&quot;" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 224, page 101) notes, "<em>B'atz'</em> is the Quiché word for the howler monkey. It is also one of the named days from the traditional highland Maya calendar." In the traditional calendar, <em>B'atz' </em>follows <em>Q'anil</em>, <em>Toj</em>, and <em>Tz'i'</em>, the gods that Ixmukane invokes in her milpa ceremony (ibid, note 315, page 126).</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 311, page 125) explains the ceremony as such: "This passage likely refers to female manifestations of three of the days in the traditional highland Maya calendar—<em>Toj</em>, <em>Q'anil</em>, and <em>Tz'i'</em> (Ruud van Akkeren, personal communication). These are consecutive days, although the order should be <em>Q'anil</em>, <em>Toj,</em> and then <em>Tz'i</em>'. Modern <em>aj q'ij </em>priests invoke the days of the calendar in their prayers and ceremonies as lords and attribute to them specific power to bless or to punish. Thus they conceive of the days as living beings with personalities and specific spheres of influence. <em>Toj</em> is 'tribute or payment.' Metaphorically it may also be 'punishment or illness' caused by sin."</p>

<p>He continues: "In her note on <em>Toj</em>, as one of the named days in the traditional Quiché calendar, Ruth Bunzel quotes an <em>aj q'ij</em> priest collaborator: '<em>T'oj</em> (enfermedad, sickness). Symbolizes the suffering which is caused by sin. ‘This is a bad day, a day of sickness. On the day <em>t'oj</em> one burns incense in the house for the Lord of Sickness. <em>T'oj</em> is also a day for calling sickness to punish an enemy. If divination comes out in 7 <em>qanil</em>, 8 <em>toj</em>, 9 <em>ts'i'</em> it is bad. These are bad days. The content of <em>qanil</em> is corn, or the milpa, <em>toj</em> is sickness, <em>ts'i'</em>, 'dog,' some shameless act. When one has a sickness of the body that is like a worm eating the flesh, we call this <em>xu jut qanil</em>, which is a worm that is found sometimes in the milpa [maizefield]. When this worm gets into the body and eats at the flesh then it is because of these days. For this sickness comes from stealing corn or else it may be due to sorcery, for they are the days of sorcery also. For instance, if a man finds that his milpa has been robbed he goes to his milpa at midnight, breaks off an ear of corn and places a candle between the two halves, and asks San Jacinto and San Augustín, the patrons of the milpa to punish the robber, and he calls the days 7 <em>qanil</em>, 8 <em>t'oj</em>, 9 <em>ts'i'</em> to punish him. Then after a time the man who has stolen the corn will suffer from this disease, which is like cancer and ulcers. This is the meaning of these days' (Bunzel 1952, 282-283)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Chowen</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>670</nid>
    <key>JUN_CHOWEN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun chouen</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun chouen</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2870b%20hun%20chowen.jpeg?itok=fiqVKMrI" width="80" height="100" alt="Kerr #2870b" title="Kerr #2870b. &quot;Maya. stone. height 55.6 cm. Excavated Copan structure 9N-82. Monkey scribe, Pauahtun. He sits with paint brush and shell paint container. . Published The Blood of Kings p. 151. See 2870a &amp; c for other views&quot;" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 225, page 101) notes, "Chouen is derived from the Yucatec Maya word <em>chuen</em>, meaning 'howler monkey.' In addition, <em>aj chuen</em> is a title meaning 'artisan' (Barrera Vásquez 1995, 110), a reading consistent with the artistic nature of these twins. Twin monkey scribes appear frequently in Classic Maya art as patrons of writing. It is also the Yucatec Maya day name that corresponds to the day <em>B'atz'</em> in the Quiché calendar."</p>

<p>Iconographic evidence supports the traditional connection between Jun Chowen, master artisan, and the act of writing, as represented in monkey scribes:</p>

<div class="media media-element-container media-default"><div id="file-219" class="file file-image file-image-jpeg">

        <h2 class="element-invisible"><a href="/files/kerr-2870c-maya-stone-height-556-cm-excavated-copan-structure-9n-82-monkey-scribe-pauahtun-he">Kerr #2870c. "Maya. stone. height 55.6 cm. Excavated Copan structure 9N-82. Monkey scribe, Pauahtun. He sits with paint brush and shell paint container. Published The Blood of Kings p. 151. See 2870b &amp; a for other views"</a></h2>
    
  
  <div class="content">
    <a href="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/2870c%20monkey%20scribe.jpeg"><img alt="Kerr #2870c" title="Kerr #2870c. &quot;Maya. stone. height 55.6 cm. Excavated Copan structure 9N-82. Monkey scribe, Pauahtun. He sits with paint brush and shell paint container. Published The Blood of Kings p. 151. See 2870b &amp; a for other views&quot;" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="1" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/2870c%20monkey%20scribe.jpeg" width="473" height="600" /></a>  </div>

  
</div>
</div></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Junajpu</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>7</nid>
    <key>JUN_JUNAJPU</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hunhunahpu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hunhunahpu</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%205615%20jun%20junajpu%27s%20head%20in%20a%20cacao%20tree.jpeg?itok=YIXIH3o-" width="100" height="60" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=5615" title="Kerr #5615: &quot;After his beheading by the Lords of the Otherworld, Hun Hunaphu&#039;s head is hung in a cacao tree.&quot;" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 163, page 81) notes the difficult nature of interpreting the name of the father of the Hero Twins. He writes, "The father of the culture hero Hunahpu is named Hun Hunahpu, which if translated literally would mean 'One One Master of the Blowgun,' a needlessly redundant reading unless Hunahpu were meant to be read as a single untranslated name."</p>

<p>Tedlock (1996: 351) prefers the translation "One Hunahpu," to refer to the figure who is "the father, by Egret Woman [Ixbaqiyalo], of One Monkey [Jun Batz] and one Artisan [Jun Chowen]; later, both One and Seven Hunahpu [Jun Junajpu, Wuqub Junajpu] become the fathers, by Blood Moon [Ixkik'], of twins named Hunahpu and Xbalanque. By bringing the face of the deceased Seven Hunahpu back to life, the twins initiate morning-star appearances of the planet Venus that begins on days named Hunahpu."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Kame</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>672</nid>
    <key>JUN_KAME</key>
    <ximenez_spa>huncame</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>huncame</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Tijax</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1083</nid>
    <key>JUN_TIJAX</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>huntíhax</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>According to Ruud van Akkeren, "Jun Tijax," or "One Flintknife," is a name of the god Tojil. He characterizes Tojil as "essentially a god of sacrifice" who "may appear as a sacrificial knife." According to Ximénez, he had been equated with Saint Paul the Apostle.</p>

<p>Citing Ximénez, Ruud van Akkeren attributes this equivalence to the figures' similar iconography: "The Toj of Rab’inal chose San Pablo as their new patron saint because he carried a sword in his hand, which is confirmed by Ximénez who writes that San Pablo was known as Jun Tijax."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Jun Toj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>724</nid>
    <key>JUN_TOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> toh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun toh </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Junajpu</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>655</nid>
    <key>JUNAJPU</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun ahpu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun ahpu</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%201226%20itz%27am%20yej%20wuqub%20caquix%20hun%20ahaj_0.jpeg?itok=rl3Ws0gf" width="100" height="35" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1226" title="Kerr image #1226: ITZ&#039;AM YEJ (Itzam Ye) (Vucub Caquix) in the tree and Hun Ahaj shoots at him with his blowgun" /></image>
    <description><p>Junajpu "is a day on the traditional highland Maya calendar, dedicated to the memory of ancestors" (Christenson 2007: note 223, page 113).</p>

<p>Tedlock (1996: 344) notes that Hunahpu, sometimes spelled <em>Junajpu</em> or <em>xjunajpu</em> ("little Hunahpu") refers to "a hunger and ballplayer, the elder twin brother of Xbalanque. Their mother is Blood Moon and their fathers, who jointly conceived them, are One and Seven Hunahpu. The astronomical roles of Hunahpu include that of the planet Venus, which still bears his name when it appears as the morning star, and that of the sun that appeared on the first day of the present age. Hunahpu is also the name of one of the volcanoes made by Zipcana, possibly the Volcán de Acatenango, which forms twin peaks with the Volcán de Fuego."</p>

<p>Por su parte Sam Colop (2011: nota 51, página 209) señala que el nombre <em>Junajpu</em> literalmente quiere decir "Un Cerbatanero", pues <em>jun</em> es "uno," <em>-aj</em> "es el agentivo y <em>pu</em> es apócope de <em>pub</em>, 'cerbatana'". Cabe recordar que Adrián Recinos (1953: nota 3, página 165) explica el significado así: "<em>Hunahpú</em> sería, en consecuencia, el cazador universal, que proveía al hombre de sustento; <em>hun</em> tiene también en maya la acepción de general y universal. Pero posiblemente los quichés que descendían directamente de los mayas, quisieron reproducir en el nombre <em>Hunahpú</em> el sonido de las palabras mayas <em>Hunab Ku</em>, 'el único dios', que servían para designar al dios principal del panteón maya, que no podía representarse materialmente, por ser incorpóreo. La pintura de un cazador podría haber servido en los tiempos antiguos para representar el fonema <em>Hunab Ku</em> que encerraba una idea abstracta, la de un ser espiritual y divino. El procedimiento es común en la escritura pictográfica precolombina. <em>Hunahpú </em>es también el nombre del vigésimo día del calendario quiché, el día más venerado de los antiguos, equivalente al maya <em>Ahau</em>, señor o jefe, y al náhuatl <em>Xóchitl</em>, flor y sol, símbolo del dios sol o <em>Tonatiuh</em>".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Junajpu Utiw</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>632</nid>
    <key>JUNAJPU_UTIW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun ahpu vtiu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun ahpu vtiu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Junajpu Wuch&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>631</nid>
    <key>JUNAJPU_WUCH</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun ahpu vuch</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun ahpu vuch</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Juraqan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>11</nid>
    <key>HURACAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>huracan</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%201120%20a%20twin%20confronts%20god%20k.jpg?itok=Z-DvSxbn" width="100" height="25" alt="Kerr database #1120: A Twin confronts God K" title="Kerr 1120: A Twin confronts God K" /></image>
    <description><p>As Christenson (2007: page 59, footnote 56) explains, there is a complex etymological and conceptual link between Jun Raqan (juraqan/hurricane) and the creator diety, Uk'u'x Kaj (Heart of Sky); they are sometimes referred to as one in the same. According to Christenson, Uk'u'x Kaj "appears to be the principal god in the <em>Popol Vuh</em> account. He is the only deity to appear in every phase of the creation, as well as throughout the mythologic and historical portions of the text. K'ux refers to the heart as the source of the 'vital spirit' of a thing, or that which gives it life. According to Coto’s dictionary, it is also believed to be the center of thought and imagination. This deity, therefore, combines the powers of life and creativity, which are believed to exist in the midst of the heavens. During each creative period, Heart of Sky is the deity who first conceives the idea of what is to be formed. Other deities then carry out his will by giving it material expression."</p>

<p>And yet, the rich etymologies embedded in the name Jun Raqan, Christenson (2007: page 60, footnote 62) adds, are "too complex and obscure to give a definitive translation. In its simplest interpretation, Juraqan means 'One Leg.' Belief in a one-legged god was widespread throughout Precolumbian Mesoamerica. An important example was the Maya god K'awil (God GII of the Palenque Triad, who was often depicted with one anthropomorphic foot and the other a serpent), associated with kingship and the sky. Raqan, however, may also refer to the length or height of an object. The following line uses the name to refer to a bolt of lightning as a long flash of light. Coto interprets raqan as something 'long or gigantic in size.' According to Dennis Tedlock’s Quiché collaborators, 'leg' may also be used as a means of counting animate things, in the same way that we refer to the counting of 'head' of cattle. 'One Leg' might therefore mean 'one of a kind' (D. Tedlock 1983a, 138). The god’s name would thus refer to his unique nature as the essential power of the sky. In addition, the homophonous word huracán was used along the Gulf Coast of Mexico and the West Indies to refer to powerful swirling winds. The modern English hurricane may be derived from the Taino version of this word (Recinos 1950, 83 n. 7; Hunt 1977, 242; D. Tedlock 1996, 223). This interpretation is consistent with the god’s nature as the 'heart of the sky,' the eye of the hurricane forming the divine axis around which time and creation revolve in endless repetitive cycles of birth and destruction."</p>

<p>Por su parte el destacado investigador-escritor k’iche’ Sam Colop (2008: página 26, nota 21) apunta que la voz “raqan”, así formada por los morfemas <em>jun</em>, ‘uno’, y <em>raqan</em> ‘su--pie’, tiene un significado que “es más amplio” que la palabra ‘huracán’ implica. Por ejemplo, el lexicográfico Coto observa que “raqan” quiere decir “gigante” o “grande”, así señalando “la fuerza y poder de las tormentas tropicales, conocidas como huracanes. Es más Brinton propone que ese término maya pasó a las Antillas donde la escucharon los navegantes europeos y luego pasó a formar parte de vocabulario de las lenguas indoeuropeas.”</p>

<p>Observamos semejantes conceptos de luz y poder en los nombres de diversas deidades del texto k'iche'. Por ejemplo, según escribe el sabio Colop (2008: página 27, nota 21) el significado de la deidad Raxa Kaqulja, o ‘Rayo hermoso’, señala etimológicamente y conceptualmente “la hermosura de su contraparte envueltos en plumas de quetzal en el mar reposado. Nótese que a ‘Corazón del Cielo’ se le identifica como ‘Huracán’, que implica su fuerza acuática en un espacio donde sólo existía el mar y el Cielo y luego se enumeran tres manifestaciones de esa fuerza.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ajolom</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>630</nid>
    <key>KAJOLOM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>qaholom</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>qaholom</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 2, página 201) señala que el nombre <em>K'ajolom</em> "viene de <em>k'ajol</em>, 'niño' o 'hijo de varón'", y que en esta manera el dios K'ajolom forma la necesaria parte complimentaria a la diosa Alom, cuyo nombre "viene de <em>ali</em>, 'niña'". Sigue el destacado traductor: "La partícula <em>-om</em> es un agentivo que hace referencia a su calidad de mujer que 'concibe' y al varón que 'engendra', respectivamente. Éstos son adjetivos que hacen referencia a la pareja creadora en una lectura antropomórfica".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 14, p. 52) confirms that Ximénez translated the names of the "divine couple, Xmucane and Xpiyacoc," as "simply 'Mother' and 'Father,'" and that such a translation flattens the important and highly gendered lines of transmission signified by their names. He writes, "A more accurate translation for Alom, however, is 'She Who Has Borne Children,' from the perfect aspect of the root verb <em>al</em> (to bear children). The name of the male god, K'ajolom, specifically indicates his having begotten male offspring, thus 'He Who Has Begotten Sons.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ayala&#039;</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>749</nid>
    <key>KAYALA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cayala</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cayala</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the places (along with Paxil) where maize originates.</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 193, note 455): “<em>K’ayala’ </em>means ‘bitter or stagnant water.’ This is perhaps related to the notion of the primordial waters of creation which the highland Maya often associate with seawater or brackish ponds, out of which the frist mountains emerged. Among modern Quichés, <em>k’alaya’ </em>is the water mixed with lime that women use to add to ground maize dough (Akkeren, personal communication).”</p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 145) has maize originating in “Split Place” (Paxil) and “Bitter Water Place” (K’ayala’).</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;enech Ajaw</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>714</nid>
    <key>KENECH_AJAW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quenech</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quenech</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ikab</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>868</nid>
    <key>KIKAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> quícab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quicab </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;o&#039;ajaw</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>844</nid>
    <key>KOAJAW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>qoahau</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>qoahau</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;o&#039;akul</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>939</nid>
    <key>KOAKUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Coacul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Coacul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ko' quiere decir "noble", así es que el título señala la nobleza y grandeza de esta segunda generación del linaje de los Nija'ib (Colop 2008: 216).</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;o&#039;akutek</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>843</nid>
    <key>KOAKUTEK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>qoacutec</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>qoacutec</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ko' quiere decir "noble", así es que el título señala la nobleza y grandeza de esta segunda generación del linaje de los Nija'ib, tal como es el caso de su complemento K'o'akul (Colop 2008: 216).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ochajuj</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>943</nid>
    <key>KOCHAJUJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cochahuh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cochahuh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 871, p. 283) translates <em>K'o Chajuj</em> as "Lord Guardian."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 395, página 216) señala que <em>k'o</em> quiere decir "noble", y que <em>chajuj </em>"probablemente se origina de <em>chaj</em>," término que significa "ocote, pino", o sea "el que enciende."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ojaj</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>813</nid>
    <key>KOJAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cohah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cohah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;oka&#039;ib</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>840</nid>
    <key>KOKAIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> qocaíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>qocaib </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;okamel</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1000</nid>
    <key>KOKAMEL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Cocamel</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Cocamel</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 405, página 217) traduce el nombre <em>K'okamel</em> como "honorable mortal", pues <em>k'o</em> significa "honorable" y <em>kamel</em> quiere decir "mortal."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 883, page 285) translates <em>K'o Kame'l </em>as "Lord Humble."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;okosom</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>993</nid>
    <key>KOKOSOM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Cocozom</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Cocozom</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Según apunta Sam Colop (2008: nota 402, página 217), el nombre <em>K'okosom </em>"probablemente quiere decir 'honorable mojado'".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 880, p. 285) points out, "The manuscript reads <em>qo cozom</em>. This is most likely <em>K'o Q'osom</em> (Lord Thicket/Bramble/Chaff) The precise meaning of this name is unclear, however, because of the limitations of the Latin alphabet used. <em>Cozom</em> may also be read as <em>Kosom </em>(Fatigued/Perplexed); <em>K'osom</em> (Reclined); or <em>Qosom </em>(Turkey Ruffling His Wings)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;onache&#039;</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>838</nid>
    <key>KONACHE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>conache</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>conache</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;otuja</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>867</nid>
    <key>KOTUJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cotuha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cotuha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p><em>K'o Tuja</em> means "Lord Sweatbath" (Christenson 2007: note 874, p. 283).</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;otuja Octavo</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>953</nid>
    <key>KOTUJA_OCTAVO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Cotuha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Cotuha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p><em>K'o Tuja</em> means "Lord Sweatbath" (Christenson 2007: note 874, p. 283). The name of the 8th Lord of the Nija'ib family line repeats from the 5th generation.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;otz&#039;ibaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>945</nid>
    <key>KOTZIBAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cotzíbaha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cotzibaha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Según apunta Sam Colop (2008: nota 395, página 216), <em>ko'</em> señala el estado noble del señor principal de los Nija'ib, mientras la voz k'iche' <em>tz'iba-aj </em>significa "casa de la pintura" o "casa de la escritura".</p>

<p>Allen Christenson (2007: note 872, p. 283) translates <em>K'o Tz'ib'a Ja</em> as "Lord Writing/Painting House."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;oyabakoj</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1001</nid>
    <key>KOYABAKOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Coyabacoh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Coyabacoh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 884, p. 285) translates <em>Co Yaba Coh </em>(in colonial orthography), and <em>K'o Yab'a Koj</em> in contemporary K'iche', as "Lord Sick Puma."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 406, página 217) confirma la interpretación de Edmondson, quien mantiene que el nombre <em>K'o Kab'a Koj</em> es un apodo, así formado de <em>K'o,</em> "honorable"<em> y yabakoj</em>, "puma enfermo." Añade que <em>Yabakoj</em> "es también el nombre antiguo de Cuyotenango Suchitepequez". Cita a Munro S. Edmonson, <em>The Book of Council: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute Publication vol. 35 (New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>K&#039;ulba</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1177</nid>
    <key>KULBA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>culba</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>culba</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the four divisions of the citadel of Chi K'ix</p>

<p>Colop (página 189, nota 316) dice que este nombre viene de <em>k'ulba't, </em>traduciéndolo como "monjón" o "límite."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ka&#039;</title>
    <type>herramienta</type>
    <nid>1257</nid>
    <key>KA'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/mexilore.jpg?itok=gARP6Wp2" width="100" height="90" /></image>
    <description><p><img alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1272" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="1" data-fid="209" data-media-element="1" height="450" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/1272.jpeg" title="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1272. Kerr #1272: &quot;Plate. Woman grinding on a metate with mano. A man smoking watches. She could be grinding either corn for masa or tobacco.&quot;" typeof="foaf:Image" width="450" /></p>

<p><img alt="http://research.mayavase.com/portfolio_hires.php?search=metate&amp;amp;date_added=&amp;amp;image=5177ff&amp;amp;display=8&amp;amp;rowstart=0" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="2" data-fid="210" data-media-element="1" height="281" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/images/5177ff.jpeg" title="http://research.mayavase.com/portfolio_hires.php?search=metate&amp;amp;date_added=&amp;amp;image=5177ff&amp;amp;display=8&amp;amp;rowstart=0. Kerr Portfolio #5177, &quot;http://research.mayavase.com/portfolio_hires.php?search=metate&amp;amp;date_added=&amp;amp;image=5177ff&amp;amp;display=8&amp;amp;rowstart=0&quot;" typeof="foaf:Image" width="450" /></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kabraqan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>658</nid>
    <key>KABRAQAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cabracan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cabracan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kaj</title>
    <type>herramienta</type>
    <nid>1252</nid>
    <key>KAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>As is apparent from manifold sources beyond the <em>Popol Wuj</em> itself, agriculture, especially of corn, is extremely important to Maya culture.  Instruments used to plant gardens include the axe (<em>kaj</em>) used to make a clearing and the hoe (<em>mixk'ina'</em>) used for tilling the earth. When the Hero Twins are tasked with planting, their magic causes these tools to do their work for them, while they enjoy blowgun hunting . Although their true purpose does not seem to be that of the farmer, Juajpu and Xb’alanke’s use of these objects in the context of cultivating a crop is notable as failure to produce corn would result in starvation for the ancient Maya. It seems Junajpu and Xb'alanke's use of magic to avoid their labors is frowned upon. The food the grandmother serves them afterwards is characterized as an unjust reward obtained through trickery:</p>

<p>Ma qitzij ab'ixik chikib'ano /  Xaloq' chib'e ya'oq ki wa</p>

<p>(Not true maize farming they would do/ Without cause she would go to give their food)</p>

<p>They even go so far as to dirty themselves with mud and wood chips so that it appears they have been hard at work. This description might characterize their actions as improper, especially as they are later punished by the animals’ re-thicketing of their cleared and planted field.</p>

<div>
<div>
<p> </p>
</div>
</div></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kak&#039;ixaja&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>711</nid>
    <key>KAKIXAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>caqúíxa ha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caqúíxa ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kanchajeleb</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>809</nid>
    <key>KANCHAJELEB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> can chaheleb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>canchahe leb </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kaqapaloja&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>708</nid>
    <key>KAQAPALOJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>caha paluma</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caha paluma</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kaqchikeleb</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>797</nid>
    <key>KAQCHIKELEB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ꜫaꜫchíqueles</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caꜫchiqueleb </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the thirteen allies of the K’iche’s, whose principle lineage was the Sotz’ila Ja, or “Bat House” (Christenson p. 217 n. 566), who stole fire from the K’iche’ forefathers. Their patron god was Chamalkan, interpreted by Tedlock (p. 356) as “Snake Tooth.” </p>

<p>According to Tedlock (p. 338), the Kaqchikels are “a people who border the Quiché on the south and east and speak a language of the Quichean family. They belong to a group of thirteen allied tribes the Quichés regarded as having come (like themselves) from the east. One of the Cakchiquel citadels, Nettles Heights, was conquered by the Quiché lords during the reign of Quicab.”</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 204 note 511): “At the time of the Spanish conquest, the Cakchiquels were centered at their capital city of Iximche’. The Tlaxcalan allies of the Spaniards called this citadel<em> Quauhtemallan, </em>from which the present-day name of the country, Guatemala, is derived.”</p>

<p>Carlsen (2001, p. 85): "The Kaqchikel arrived in highland Guatemala sometime in the Late Postclassic period. According to the sixteenth-century document <em>The Annals of the Kaqchikels, </em>the source of the that migration was the legendary Tulán. That document, written in Kaqchikel using Spanish characters, is consistent with the <em>Popol Vuh </em>in this regard ... the Kaqchikels entered the highlands on the heels of the other Maya, most notably the Tz'utujil [Ajtz'ikina ja]. Arriving in 1524, the Spaniards under Pedro de Alvarado quickly exploited these ethnic divisions. In particular, the foreigners aligned themselves with Kaqchikel in their war against both K'iche' and Tz'utujil" (<em>Oxford Encyclopedia of Mesoamerican Cultures</em>).</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kaquilja Jun Raqan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>644</nid>
    <key>KAQUILJA_JUN_RAQAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>caculha huracan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caculha huracan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kaweq</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>818</nid>
    <key>KAWEQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> los quechees</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cavec queche </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kawinal</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1178</nid>
    <key>KAWINAL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cauínal</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cavinal</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the four divisions of the citadel of Chi K'ix.</p>

<p>Colop (página 189, nota 316) dice, "es propiamente el nombre de aquel sitio arqueológico [donde probablemente ubicaba Chi K'ix] y puede leerse como <em>ka- </em>'dos' y <em>winal </em>cognado yukateko del k'iche' <em>winaq</em> 'persona', equivale a '2 cuentas de 20,' es decir, 'cuarenta.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kawisimaj</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>869</nid>
    <key>KAWISIMAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> cauízímah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cavizimah </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kawkeb</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>826</nid>
    <key>KAWKEB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>caoqueb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caoqueb</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ke&#039;ema</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>959</nid>
    <key>KEEMA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quema</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>queema</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez originally writes "Queema" as the name (53r), and later changes it to "Quema" (56r). It is unclear whether this change represents a scribal error or a better understanding of how the K'iche' name ought to have been sounded in the Spanish transcription. The word <em>kema</em> translates as "loom," according to Christenson (2007: nota 876, página 283). Although weaving is women's work, and the communication of messages through colors and patterns is a feminine mode of meaning-making, Lord Keema is classified as a male figure in the text: "Quema, as he is called now, was the tenth generation." On indigenous women's literacies, see Susan Kellog, <em>Weaving the Past</em>.</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 398, página 216) observa la discrepancia entre la ortografía del nombre del señor principal en los folios 53r y 56r, pues el fraile Ximénez escribe "Queema" y "Quema." El destacado traductor también apunta que el nombre "antes se tradujo como 'tejido'".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kik&#039;</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1230</nid>
    <key>KIK'</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quic</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quic</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/1288.jpeg?itok=x_S2dZKd" width="100" height="36" alt="Kerr #1288" title="Kerr #1288. &quot;Ball game with Hun Hunahpú and journey to Xibalba.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1288" /></image>
    <description><p>The Mesoamerican ball game famously provides the central mode of conflict between Xib’alb’a and the two sets of brothers in the <em>Popl Wuj</em>. Although the exact rules and purpose of the game are unknown, it is clear that it held significance far beyond that of a simply recreational activity. Whittington asserts that, due to the game’s prevalence in the <em>Popol Wuj</em>, “this story of creation and activities of the gods and humanity becomes inseparable from the ballgame.” As the game is both a physical space and a practice shared by humans and Xibalbans, it seems to hold a deep ceremonial role in Mesoamerican cosmovisions.</p>

<p>Athletic prowess is symbolically passed down to the Hero Twins from their fathers through the physical objects used to play the game: yokes (<em>b'ate),</em> kilts or hides (<em>tz’u’m)</em>, armguards (<em>pach' q'ab')</em>, panaches of feather (<em>yachwach</em>), headbands (<em>wach sot</em>), and the ball itself (<em>kik’</em> or <em>cha’j</em>). These are collectively called their “implements” (<em>chokonisan</em>) or “equipment” (<em>etz’ab’al)</em>, which Christenson translates as "finery" (2007: 106).</p>

<p>The game itself is strongly connected to the practices of bloodletting and sacrifice; this is clear in the toponym <em>Pusb’al Cha’j</em><em> </em>(“Place of Ballgame Sacrifice”). The meaning of the place maps on to the modern words <em>pusunik</em> (to sacrifice), <em>pus</em><em> </em>(to cut into pieces or wound) along with the word <em>cha’j </em>(ball or ball game). From archaeological evidence, we know that the actual ball game played by the ancient Maya “had the potential to end in sacrifice” and, as Mary Miller suggests, is depicted as “the ultimate place of transition” between life and death in the <em>Popol Wuj</em>. </p>

<p>One epithet used in reference to a ball may point to the game’s religious or sacrificial role. After felling the message-bearing falcon, the twins agree to heal his eye from their shot before receiving his message; they cover the wound with a piece of rubber taken from their game ball. They then name this bit of rubber: "Lotz Kik' xub'i'naj kumal," which Christenson (2004: 121) translates as "<em>Lotz Kik’</em> it was named by them."</p>

<p>It is worth noting that Tedlock and Xiloj translate the expression differently. Their translation reads “Blood of Sacrifice.”  In his notes, Tedlock defines <em>lotz </em>as “to puncture, let blood” and <em>kik’ </em>as either “blood” or “resin.” The Christenson dictionary offers a different translation of <em>lotz</em>, “to smear,” but similarly defines <em>kik’ </em>as rubber or a rubber ball. Additionally, mutations of <em>kik’ </em>such as <em>silob’ -kik’el </em>and <em>cha’ -kik’el </em>are defined by Christenson as “to move blood” and “to speak blood,” respectively – both are alternatively defined as “means of receiving a supernatural message.”</p>

<p>It is not difficult to understand how rubber – and the sticky resin from which it is made – might be practically and lexically intertwined with blood, the sap drained from human bodies rather than trees. Although Christenson and Tedlock offer different interpretations of <em>lotz</em>, they are conceptually linked in the realm of sacrificial bloodletting: letting blood and smearing some substance are not too semantically distant.</p>

<p>In combination with the double-meaning of <em>kik’</em>, the epithet <em>Lotz Kik’ </em>evokes more images of blood beyond that of the falcon’s wounded eye. The falcon, carrying a message intended for Junajpu and Xb’alanke from the Lords of Xib’alb’a, establishes a connection between Xib’alb’a and <em>uwach ulew </em> – perhaps not coincidentally on the ball court. Connections which can be drawn between blood, sap, rubber, the ball itself, the ball game, and, finally, the practice of sacrificial bloodletting seem fitting, as the ball game is characterized throughout the <em>Popol Vuj</em> as the vehicle through which Xibalbans interact with earth-dwellers.</p>

<p>Tedlock points to another relevant distinction; he says that <em>cha’j</em> is used for the ball in Xib’alb’a while <em>kik’</em> refers only to the ball of Juajpu and Xb’alanke.  Perhaps the wordplay surrponding the many meanings of <em>kik'</em> solidifies a semantic connection for the Maya, allowing <em>kik’ </em>to be used to refer to balls and, more distantly, to humans’ interaction with the supernatural through sacrifice or ball game challenges.</p>

<p>The ball in Xib’alb’a further differs from a normal ball in that is appears to the boys to be a skull – previously described as being coated with crushed bone; Tedlock says that what is played off as “mere decoration” by the Lords is actually a fundamental and sinister difference.  Reference to this bone-ball as <em>kik’, </em>the word for “ball,” is easily associated with blood and death, and it seems fitting for this particular object, even though <em>cha’j </em>is typically used for Xibalban game balls. The connection between blood and sap us not unique to the treatment of the game ball; not unlike a ball, sap from a tree was formed into a round shape to fool the Xibalban Lords into false appeasement through Ixkik’s supposed death: "K'ate puch xuwon rib' / K'olok'ik xuxik. (Then also congealed/ round it became)."</p>

<p>The sticky, dark sap was formed into a round shape – the positional root <em>k’ol </em>-- to mimick the human heart. Tedlock does not include a note on why he translates the verb <em>xuwon </em>as “congealed.” However, as the passage discusses round things, it might be assumed to hold a connection with <em>won</em>, a positional root meaning “round” which has connotations of pity and abandonment. Perhaps this description of the false heart metaphorically ties into the realities of Ixkik’s life; how her father shunned her and how her mother-in-law nearly does the same. The heart is also referred to in an elegant phrase: "U k'exel u kik'el (her blood’s substitute)."</p>

<p>Since <em>kik’el</em> is what is described as substituted, it must refer to Ixkik’s blood and not to the sap which replaced it. <em>Kik’</em>, therefore, is not merely sap that is “like blood;” the phrasing goes so far as to characterize it as the blood itself, the blood that would have been flowing through Ixkik’’s veins and comprising her extracted heart. As a daughter of Xib’alb’a whose name is simply <em>kik’</em> with a prefix <em>(i)x</em> meaning “female” or “moon,” it is significant that Ixkik’’s blood shares the same label as the sap of a tree.</p>

<p>Furthermore, the Lords of Xib’alb’a are quite pleased with the aroma produced from the sacrificial burning of the supposed heart. Blood sacrifices being an important practice in the Maya world connecting humans to deities, the ability of the sap to fool the Lords in sacrifice may point to the significance of rubber as a material which allows humans to interact with and appease supernatural entities.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kik&#039; Re</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>697</nid>
    <key>KIK_RE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quíc xíc</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quíc xíc</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kik&#039; Rixk&#039;aq</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>698</nid>
    <key>KIK_RIXKAQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>quíc ríx ꜫaꜫ</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quíc ríx ꜫaꜫ</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Komajkun</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>996</nid>
    <key>KOMAJKUN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>comah cun</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Comahcun</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 403, página 217) afirma que el nombre <em>Komajkun</em> se compone de las voces <em>komaj</em>, "sangre", y <em>kun</em>, "raíz verbal de 'curar'", y de esta forma "probablemente quiere decir médico de los males de sangre." La interpretación de Allen Christenson (citado abajo) indica el contrario, es decir que el nombre del dios significa "no es médico", debido al prefijo <em>ma</em>, o 'no'.</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 881, p. 285) translates <em>Co Mahun</em>, as it is written in colonial K'iche', as such: "<em>Aj Kun</em> is a 'healer/doctor. The m- prefix is a negative marker, which would make the name read something like 'Not a Healer.' As a verb, <em>maj</em> is “to seize, steal, grasp.” Thus an alternative might be 'Seizes Medicine.'" Colop (cited above) suggests the contrary, because he reads <em>Comah </em>(or <em>Komaj</em> in contemporary spelling) as "blood," and <em>hun</em> (here interpreted as <em>kun</em>), as "to cure or heal."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kuchuma Kik&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>13</nid>
    <key>KUCHUMA_KIK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cuchumaquic</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cuchumaquic</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kuchuma Kik&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1121</nid>
    <key>KUCHUMA_KIK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cuchu maquíC</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cuchumaquic</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 235, page 103) explains the name of this god as: "Kuchuma Kik' (Gathered Blood) is still known by Quiché storytellers as a cruel lord of the underworld who gathers blood shed upon the ground as a result of injury, illness, or violence. This blood is then served to his fellow lords at a banquet."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kumatz</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>801</nid>
    <key>KUMATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cumatz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the thirteen allied lineages. <em>Kumatz </em>means “snake” or “serpent” in K’iche’ (see e.g. <em>Q’ukumatz</em>)</p>

<p>Christenson (pp. 204–205, note 515): “The Cumatz also settled near the present-day town of Sacapulas (Recinos 1950, 171 n. 6). The Cumatz settlement may be the site of Chutixtiox, located on a hill at the center of the Sacapulas basin approximately three kilometers west of the modern town of Sacapulas (Fox 1978, 71–77). The Cumatz were subjugated by the Quichés early in the fifteenth century as part of the Lord Quicab’s campaign of expansion (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 93; Recions 1957, 141).”</p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 355) adds that the Spanish knew the Kumatz by the Nahuatl-derived version of their name, Coatecas, and resettled them near Sacapulas along with the Lamakib’.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Kuwatepech</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>880</nid>
    <key>KUWATEPECH</key>
    <ximenez_spa> cuuatepech</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cauatepech </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Kuwatepech es el señor principal de la generación undécima del linaje Kaweq; el otro señor principal de esta generación es Wuqub' No'j.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>la gran hondonada</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>733</nid>
    <key>LA_GRAN_HONDONADA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ním xob carchah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ním xob carchah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>La isla española</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1066</nid>
    <key>LA_ISLA_ESPANOLA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>la isla española</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/hispaniola.png?itok=w8Msjsd_" width="100" height="100" alt="Hispaniola" title="Hispaniola. Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>"La isla española" (the Spanish island), today known as Hispaniola (its Latin name), is a Caribbean island shared by the nations of Haiti and the Dominican Republic.</p>

<p>"La isla española," hoy conocido como La Española (en castellano) o Hispaniola (en latín), es una isla caribeña compartida por las naciones de Haití y la República Dominicana.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Lakamib</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>800</nid>
    <key>LAKAMIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> lamaquíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>lamaquib </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Lamakib</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>1319</nid>
    <key>LAMAKIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the thirteen allied lineages.</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 204, note 514): “The Lamacs, like the Cumatz with whom they are paired in this passage, apparently settled the area of present-day Sacapulas (Recinos 1950, 171 n. 6; Fox 1978, 76). There is a site known as Lamak-Zacapulas approximately five leagues north of Sacapulas (Villacorta and Villacorta 1930, 94; Fox 1978, 90)."</p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 346) adds that the Lamakib’ were resettled to Sacapulas during the colonial period.</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Lolmet Kejnay</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>850</nid>
    <key>LOLMET_KEJNAY</key>
    <ximenez_spa> chítuy Lolmet queh nayí</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chituy lolmet queh nay </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Allen Christenson (2004: nota 745, página 255) traduce el nombre Lolmet Kej Nay así: "Emissary of the Deer House," pues "Lolmet (or Lolmay) is an emissary or ambassador.' Kej is deer. Na[y] is the Lowland Maya version of the Quichéan Ja[y] (house)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>los de la bóveda azul</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>640</nid>
    <key>LOS_DE_LA_BÓVEDA_AZUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ah raxatzel chu qhaxic</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah raxatzel chu qhaxic</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2011: nota 6, página 202) explica así el origen conceptual de la ‘bóveda azul’: “Esto viene de que <em>ajraxa laq, ajraxa tzel</em>, metáfora asociada a lo plano y verde de la Tierra y de la bóveda cósmica. <em>Laq</em> literalmente es ‘plato’ y <em>tzel</em> es recipiente de forma redonda. Esto quiere decir, los guías espirituales mitológicos que ofrecen ceremonias a la Tierra y al Cielo. El color azul está asociado a la bóveda del Cielo.”</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 22, page 53) explains the connection between the "Creator of Green Earth" ("los de la superficie plana" in Spanish, and "ajraxa tzel" in K'iche'), its chiasmic counterpart, "Creator of the Blue Sky" ("los de la bóveda azul" in Spanish, and "ajaraxa laq" in K'iche') as such: "These are likely titles for Xpiyacoc and Xmucane (see p. 80; lines 565-566). They literally mean 'blue/green plate' and 'blue/green bowl.' The Quiché language has only one word, räx, for both blue and green. When distinguishing between the colors, modern Quiché people are forced to say 'räx like the sky' for blue, or 'räx like a tree' for green. This same type of dichotomy appears here. The 'blue/green plate' refers to the green surface of the earth covered with vegetation, and the arch of the sky is envisioned as an inverted 'blue bowl.' The earth is specifically likened to a plate on p. 71 (lines 205-206)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>los de la superficie plana</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>639</nid>
    <key>LOS_DE_LA_SUPERFICIE_PLANA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ah raxalaꜫ</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ah raxalaꜫ</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><div>
<div>
<p>Colop (2011: nota 6, página 202) explica así el origen conceptual de la 'superficie plana' y su importante vínculo con la 'bóveda azul', aquí comunicado con el uso de la técnica retórica del quiasmo. Escribe: “Esto viene de que <em>ajraxa laq, ajraxa tzel</em>, metáfora asociada a lo plano y verde de la Tierra y de la bóveda cósmica. <em>Laq</em> literalmente es ‘plato’ y <em>tzel</em> es recipiente de forma redonda. Esto quiere decir, los guías espirituales mitológicos que ofrecen ceremonias a la Tierra y al Cielo. El color azul está asociado a la bóveda del Cielo.”</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 22, page 53) explains the connection between the "Creator of Green Earth" ("los de la superficie plana" in Spanish, and "ajraxa tzel" in K'iche'), its chiasmic counterpart, "Creator of the Blue Sky" ("los de la bóveda azul" in Spanish, and "ajaraxa laq" in K'iche') as such: "These are likely titles for Xpiyacoc and Xmucane (see p. 80; lines 565-566). They literally mean 'blue/green plate' and 'blue/green bowl.' The Quiché language has only one word, räx, for both blue and green. When distinguishing between the colors, modern Quiché people are forced to say 'räx like the sky' for blue, or 'räx like a tree' for green. This same type of dichotomy appears here. The 'blue/green plate' refers to the green surface of the earth covered with vegetation, and the arch of the sky is envisioned as an inverted 'blue bowl.' The earth is specifically likened to a plate on p. 71 (lines 205-206)."</p>
</div>
</div></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Lugar de Awiliz</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>830</nid>
    <key>LUGAR_DE_AWILIZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> en auílís</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>pa vlix </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"At Awilix." The site where Balam Acab deposited the god(dess) Awilix.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Lugar de Jaqaqitz</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>786</nid>
    <key>LUGAR_DE_JAQAWITZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>caꜫha hacavitz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>lugar del sacrificio</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>745</nid>
    <key>LUGAR_DEL_SACRIFICIO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>--</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>--</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Majuk&#039;utaj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>706</nid>
    <key>MAJUKUTAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Mahucutah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Mahucutah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 479, p. 184) notes that name of this deity is "problematic." As he explains, "Carmack believes that it is derived from the lowland Maya word for 'Traveler,' or 'One Who Does Not Stay' (Carmack 1981, 49). Tedlock translates it as 'Not Right Now' based on the Quiché <em>ma</em>, 'not,' and <em>jukotaj</em>, 'right away/in a moment' (Basseta). Akkeren (personal communication) suggests that the name is derived from the Mam <em>jukotaj</em> (elder, eminent one). Coto lists <em>hu cotah</em> as 'one crown, ring, or similar round object' (Coto 1983, 474). In many highland Maya languages, such as Tz’utujil, the prefix <em>Ma</em> may be honorific, meaning something like 'mister, or sir.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Majukutaj Hombre</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>987</nid>
    <key>MAJUKUTAJ_HOMBRE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Mahucutah. el primer hombre</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Mahucutah nabe vinac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 479, p. 184) translates the name of the deity, from whom the first grandfather of the K'iche' line takes his name, as "problematic." As he explains, "Carmack believes that it is derived from the lowland Maya word for 'Traveler,' or 'One Who Does Not Stay' (Carmack 1981, 49). Tedlock translates it as 'Not Right Now' based on the Quiché <em>ma</em>, 'not,' and <em>jukotaj</em>, 'right away/in a moment' (Basseta). Akkeren (personal communication) suggests that the name is derived from the Mam <em>jukotaj</em> (elder, eminent one). Coto lists <em>hu cotah</em> as 'one crown, ring, or similar round object' (Coto 1983, 474). In many highland Maya languages, such as Tz’utujil, the prefix <em>Ma</em> may be honorific, meaning something like 'mister, or sir.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Makamob</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1044</nid>
    <key>MAKAMOB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>macamob</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>macamob</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96; note 175): "Volcán Zunil in the district of Quetzaltenango, Guatemala."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Makamob</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>664</nid>
    <key>MAKAMOB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>macamob</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>macamob</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>María</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1076</nid>
    <key>MARIA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Ma. SSma.</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Mary, whom Ximénez refers to as "SSma." (<em>Santíssima</em>, Most Holy) or "Ma. SSma." (<em>Madre Santíssima</em>, Most Holy Mother), is the human mother of Jesus Christ. She is also known as the "Blessed Virgin Mary," having conceived Jesus of the Holy Spirit.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Me&#039;awn</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>731</nid>
    <key>MEAWN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>meauan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>meauan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Sipakna is crushed under this mountain after being tricked by Hunahpu and Xbalanque. Christenson (page 105, note 202) says of it, "Meauan was identified by Brasseur and Recinos as a mountain west of Rabinal, Guatemala. It is likely the mountain known today as Miagua, located some 20 km. northwest of Rabinal and bordering the Chixoy river. If this identification is correct, Akkeren suggests that that Meauan may be a contracted form of <em>me'al ajaw </em>(daughter lord), the Quiché version of the Kekchi origin of the town's name, Rab'inal (Place of the Lord's Daughter).</p>

<p>Colop (página 54, nota 65) dice, "conforme a Recinos, esa montaña 'se levanta al poniente del pueblo de Rabinal, en la región del río Chixoy.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Medicina de Tojil</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1166</nid>
    <key>MEDICINA_DE_TOJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>guarda de el tohil</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cunabal tohil</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>A hidden canyon (<em>ewab'al siwan</em>) beneath the mountain Pa Tojil. Given the name "Medicine of Tojil" by the forefathers.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>México</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1171</nid>
    <key>MEXICO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Mexíco</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Mexico</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Comalcalco.jpeg?itok=1d_cpa66" width="100" height="75" alt="http://www.wikiwand.com/es/Comalcalco_(zona_arqueológica)" title="Comalcalco: &quot;Casa de los comales&quot; en náhuatl, sitio arqueológico del presente estado de Tabasco" /></image>
    <description><p>Carmack (1981, p. 44) suggests that the <em>Popol Vuh </em>describes the journey of the K'iche' forefathers from a Chontal-speaking epi-Toltec center on the coast of the Gulf of Mexico, probably in the modern-day Mexican states of Veracruz or Tabasco.</p>

<p>The mention of "Mexico" in the <em>PV </em>seems to support this, saying "[t]his they said among themselves as they remembered their older borthers and their younger brothers, the Yaqui people. These dawned there in Mexico, as it is called today. Thus surely a portion of them remained there in the East, they whose names are Tepeu and Oliman" (Christenson, 231).</p>

<p>It is worth pointing out that "Tepeu" and "Oliman" are both names of Nahua origin, like "Mexico" itself. Although the Gulf Coast region would not be placed to the east of the K'iche' area on a modern map, the authors of the <em>PV </em>seem to have regarded it as such. On the complex ways in which speakers of Mayan languages orient themselves in space, and how indigenous cartographies and spatial vocabularies were misunderstood by colonial Spanish authorities, see Solari, "Circles of Creation."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Mixk&#039;ina&#039;</title>
    <type>herramienta</type>
    <nid>1253</nid>
    <key>MIXK'INA'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The centrality of maiz cultivation in Mesoamerica is well-documented in the <em>Popol Wuj</em>. Below we provide background information on some of the key tools and technologies used in Maya agriculture.</p>

<p>Instruments used to plant gardens include the axe (<em>kaj</em>), used to make a clearing, and the hoe (<em>mixk'ina'</em>), used for tilling the earth. When the Hero Twins are tasked with planting, their magic causes these tools to do their work for them, while they enjoy blowgun hunting. Although farming does not seem to be their primary purpose or role in the text, Juajpu and Xb’alanke’s use of these objects in crop cultivation is notable; failure to produce corn would result in starvation for the ancient Maya.</p>

<p>It seems that Junajpu and Xb'alanke's use of magic to replace true labor is frowned upon. For example, the food the grandmother serves them afterwards is characterized as an unjust reward obtained through trickery:</p>

<p>Ma qitzij ab'ixik chikib'ano /  Xaloq' chib'e ya'oq ki wa</p>

<p>(Not true maize farming they would do/ Without cause she would go to give their food)</p>

<p>They even go so far as to dirty themselves with mud and wood chips so that it appears they have been hard at work. This description might characterize their actions as improper, especially as they are later punished by the animals’ re-thicketing of their cleared and planted field.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>murciélagos decapitadores</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>650</nid>
    <key>MURCIÉLAGOS_DECAPITADORES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>camalotz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>camalotz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nakxit</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>845</nid>
    <key>NAKXIT</key>
    <ximenez_spa> nacxít</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nacxit </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Described as a great lord from the east, Nacxit is responsible for distributing the signs and symbols of lordship (Ximenez Folio 48V).</p>

<p>Among others, Tedlock (1996: 315) and Christenson (2007: 241) point to the Nahuatl roots of the name Nacxit, <em>naui </em>("four") and <em>icxitl</em> ("foot"). While both scholars also identify this name as being one of the titles held by the god Quetzalcoatl, Tedlock claims that "Nacxit's 'populous domain,' as it is called in the PV, was probably a kingdom in Yucatán ruled by a lineage claiming Toltec descent" (315). For Christenson, the name's origins suggest a possible reference to "to the extent of his power to the four cardinal directions of the earth" (241). </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nija&#039;ib</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>823</nid>
    <key>NIJAIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> níhaíbab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nihaibab </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nik&#039;aqaj Taq&#039;aj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>720</nid>
    <key>NIKAQAJ_TAQAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> nícahtacah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nicacahtacah </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nim Ch&#039;okoj Kaweq</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>848</nid>
    <key>NIM_CHOKOJ_KAWEQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ním chocoh cuec</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nim chocoh cavec </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Whereas Christenson(2003) identifies the ch'okoj as someone "charged with providing the food and drinks for state functions, as well as making pronouncements and public discourses" (269), Tedlock highlights the potentially political play on words, noting that "ch'okoj" places emphasis on the act of sitting itself, thus suggesting that the Totonicapán authors mockingly refer to him as a "Master of Sitting" rather than a "Master of Ceremonies." </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nim Ch&#039;okoj Nija&#039;ib</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>857</nid>
    <key>NIM_CHOKOJ_NIJAIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ním chocoh níhaíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nimchocoh nihaibab </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 254, p. 256): "Great Steward Nijaibs." In the body of the text, he translates the name as "Great Steward of the Nihaibs."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252): "maestro de las ceremonias de los Nija'ib."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nim Xo&#039;l</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>752</nid>
    <key>NIM_XOL</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>A place passed through by the K'iche's on their way to Chi Pixab'. </p>

<p>Colop traduce el nombre como "Gran Hondonada," y se pone de acuerdo con Tedlock que es otro nombre para <em>Nim Xob Karchaj, </em>en la región del moderno San Pedro Carchá.</p>

<p>In modern K'iche', <em>-xo'l </em>refers to a "space between" in prepositional phrases, e.g. <em>chuxo'l le keb' ja </em>"between the two houses."</p>

<p>Christenson translates this name quite differently, as "Honor and Respect." Like Tedlock and Colop, he identifies it with "the place where Hun Hunahpu and his sons played ball," and asserts that therefore "the origin of the progenitors is defined as the homeland of the patron heroes described in the first half of the <em>Popol Vuh </em>text."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nima Ch&#039;okoj</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>872</nid>
    <key>NIMA_CHOKOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>nim chocoh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nim chocoh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nima K&#039;amja</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>856</nid>
    <key>NIMA_KAMJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>nima camha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nima camha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252): señala que el nombre de este señor principal de los Nija'ib quiere decir "principal en línea de sucesión."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 752, p. 256) writes the name Nima K'am Ja as, "Great Reception House."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Nima Lolmet Ye&#039;oltux</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>859</nid>
    <key>NIMA_LOLMET_YEOLTUX</key>
    <ximenez_spa> níma lolmet yeoltux</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>nima lolmet yeoltux </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Orden de Predicadores</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>1063</nid>
    <key>ORDEN_DE_PREDICADORES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>SAGRADO ORDEN DE PRAEDICADORES</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Seal_of_the_Dominican_Order.png?itok=oUfSML_L" width="100" height="100" alt="Seal of the Order of Preachers" title="Seal of the Order of Preachers. Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>The Order of Preachers (also known as the Dominican Order, and whose members are commonly called<em> </em>Dominicans or <em>dominicos</em>) is a Catholic religious order founded by Santo Domingo de Guzmán during the Albigensian Crusade and approved by Pope Honorius III in 1216. The order's charism, or main focus, historically centers around intellectual and educational activity in support of orthodox Catholic teaching. Besides their contributions to theology and philosophy, particularly in the forms of Scholasticism and Thomism, the order's members have played a major role in the legal tradition of the Catholic Church from the medieval Inquisition to the development of international law among missionaries to the Americas in the colonial era.</p>

<p>Fray Francisco Ximénez, the author of the earliest extant manuscript of the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, was a member of the Dominican Order and undertook his work on the text as part of his order's broader mission to preach Catholicism to the Maya and combat what they saw as heretical native beliefs. Néstor Quiroa writes:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>"The <em>Popol Vuh</em> serves as a manifestation of the religious encounter and conflicts between the Dominican Order and the Maya-Quiché. The violent subjugation of the Maya population of the highlands, conducted by Pedro de Alvarado in 1524, was followed by their spiritual conquest. This task was bestowed on the monastic [<em>n.b. "mendicant"</em>] orders, namely, the Franciscans, Mercedarians, and predominately the Dominicans or the Order of Preachers. Upon arrival, the Dominicans implemented the method of peaceful conversion first practiced in the American territory by Dominican Friar Pedro de Córdoba. Later, Friar Bartolomé de Las Casas was successful in Las Verapaces, or the true peace, region in the northern section of the country. In addition to learning the native languages and cultures of the neophytes, the Dominicans believed that the information contained in the native narratives could be used by missionary friars to Christianize them effectively. Preserving the indigenous narratives represented for the missionaries an advantage for the eradication of the indigenous religion and the establishment of Christianity, while also presenting a conflict, since it preserved the very thing it attempted to extirpate."</p>
</blockquote></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pa Tojil</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>754</nid>
    <key>PA_TOJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> patohíl</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>patohil </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"At Tojil," the site of Tojil's deposition by Balam Kitze. </p>

<p>Christenson (page 225, note 588) notes that "[t]his is likely the mountain still known today as Pa Tojil, located on the south side of the Chujuyup Valley (Fox 1978, 58; Carmack 1981, 65)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pach&#039; q&#039;ab&#039;</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1234</nid>
    <key>PACH'_Q'AB'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/1209.jpeg?itok=H8a7EWBj" width="100" height="45" alt="Kerr #1209" title="Kerr #1209: &quot;Ball game inside ball-court.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=1209" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 245, page 106) notes that "Depictions of Precolumbian ballplayers in ancient Maya art often show the lower arms wrapped with<br />
a protective device." Image #1209 above, "Ball game inside ball-court," from Justin Kerr's database of Maya vases, offers one such example.</p>

<p>Arm protectors are one of the five fine objects that adorn the Hero Twins as they journey to Xibalba.</p>

<p>The others are leather, yokes, feather headdresses, and face bands.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pak&#039;am</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>702</nid>
    <key>PAKAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xulupacam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xulupacam </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Patan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>682</nid>
    <key>PATAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>patan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>patan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Paxil</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>748</nid>
    <key>PAXIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> paxil</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>paxíl </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the places (along with K’ayala’) where corn originates.</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 193, note 454): “<em>Paxil </em>means ‘broken, split, or cleft.’ Father Coto wrote that it refers in particular to the breaking in two of an ear of maize. <em>Paxil </em>is described as an ‘excellent mountain’ filled with the maize that would eventually be used to form the flesh of humanity (p. 194; lines 4886–4889). This was a widespread belief in ancient Mesoamerica, particularly among Maya (Freidel, Schele, and Parker 1993, 138–139). According to the Central Mexican <em>Codex Chimalpopoca, </em>it was Quetzalcoatl himself who brougth the first maize out of the mountain Tonacetepetl (the mountain of our flesh and of our sustenance) from which he created the first men (León-Portilla 1980, 122 n. 42). The Pipil of Guatemala relate that maize was discovered when the mountain in which it was hidden was split open by the youngest of the rain dwarfs (Schultze-Jena 1935, 31–33). Contemporary Mam still identify one of their local mountains as Paxil, saying that it is ‘where a flea brought the first grains of maize through a narrow crevice to give our ancestors corn.’”</p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 145) has maize originating in “Split Place” (Paxil) and “Bitter Water Place” (K’ayala’). In modern K’iche’, <em>paxik </em>means “to break, split open.” </p>

<p>De Paxil y K’ayala’, Colop (p. 128, nota 190) dice: “Estos lugares mitólogicos han sido asociados a varios sitios, conforme a Recinos (1953:174) Bancroft opinaba que estaban en la región de Palenque y el Usumacinta y de acuerdo con Brasseur en la región de Tabasco… El nombre <em>Paxil </em>se ha mitologizado y de esa cuenta aparece la historia del origen del maíz en distintas áreas.” Colop esprime acuerdo con la etimologia de Tedlock.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pedro Apiano</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1065</nid>
    <key>PEDRO_APIANO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Doctor Po. Apíano</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Peter_Apian.png?itok=CTsCz_y6" width="62" height="100" alt="Petrus Apianus (1495–1552)" title="Petrus Apianus (1495–1552). Wikimedia Commons." /></image>
    <description><p>Petrus Apianus, o Pedro Apiano (1495–1552), citado por Ximénez como el "cosmógrafo de el emperador Carlos quinto," era un cartógrafo y matemático alemán. Apianus dedicó su obra maestra, <em>Astronomicum Caesareum</em>, al emperador. Ximénez hace referencia a su <em>Liber cosmographicus</em>, mejor conocido como <em>Cosmographia de Petrus Apianus</em>, que se publicó en 1524 y pasó por muchas ediciones en los siglos siguientes.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pekul</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1040</nid>
    <key>PEKUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>pecul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>pe cul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 173) identifies it with Volcán Acatenango, but cites Tedlock as identifying it with Volcán de Agua.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pekul</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>662</nid>
    <key>PEKUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>pecul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>pecul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Piedras en hilera</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1162</nid>
    <key>PIEDRAS_EN_HILERA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>las píedras sobresalíentes en rínglera</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cholochic abah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of two names for what may be one or two places along the K'iche' forefathers' path across the sea from Tulan to the highlands. </p>

<p>Colop (página 151, nota 243) explica que "este 'pasaron del mar' no debe tomarse de manera literal. Es una figura para explicar el paso entre determinados lugares que se anegan en la época de la lluvia, o como dice Tedlock (301), 'en efecto, los nombres describen una calzada como las que cruzan lagos o áreas temporalmente inundadas para conectar varios sitios Mayas de las tierras bajas.'</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pléyadas</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1052</nid>
    <key>PLEYADAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>motz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>motz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>An astronym for the constellation known as the Pleiades in English and in K'iche' as <em>M</em><em>otz. </em>According to Christenson (page 104, note 198) this word means "to gather together in large numbers." The<em> Popol Vuh </em>states that the Four Hundred boys became this constellation after their defeat by Sipakna, "but perhaps this is merely a fable."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Popol Winaq chi T&#039;uy</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>849</nid>
    <key>POPOL_WINAQ_CHI_TUY</key>
    <ximenez_spa> popol vínac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>popol vinac </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Popol Winaq pa Jom Tzalatz&#039;</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>851</nid>
    <key>POPOL_WINAQ_PA_JOM_TZALATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> popol vínac pahom tzalatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>popol vinacm pahom tzalatz </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pujuy</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>700</nid>
    <key>PUJUY</key>
    <ximenez_spa>puhuyu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>puhuyu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Pusbal Chaaj</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>746</nid>
    <key>PUSBAL_CHAAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>donde echaban la zeniza</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>pucbal chah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>This toponym is variously translated. Christenson has "Crushing Ballcourt," Tedlock "Place of Ball Game Sacrifice," Colop "Lugar del Sacrificio," and Ximénez "donde echaban la zeniza."</p>

<p>Christenson (page 125–126, note 270) explains: "The root verb for <em>puk'b'al </em>has a variety of possible interpretations. It may mean to crush, to grind to a very fine consistency, to kick up dust, to sift, to beat, to spill, to spread about, to scatter, to disentangle, or to card wool.<em> Puk'b'al </em>may thus refer to the dustiness of the ballcourt or the tendency to kick up dust during vigorous play. It may also imply that this ballcourt is where opponents are 'ground down, beaten, or sifted.' This latter inteprretation is intriguing, beause 'to crush' s often used in the text to refer to the destruction or violent death of people. Father Coto notes that a synonymous word for 'to crush,' <em>k'ajb'ik, </em>refers specifically to human sacrifice, which is the likely implication here as well. It is also possible that this word should be read as <em>pukb'al, </em>which also has a variety of meanings depending on context. It means literally 'to fall from overripeness or decay (fruit, flowers, teeth), or to be plucked out (hair, feathers).' Metaphorically the word when applied to humans means 'crestfallen, melancholy, disdained, comtemptible, or scorned.' In this case such an interpretation may refer to the humiliation and misery of those who lose in the ballcourt. Both interpretations may apply here considering the Maya's fondness for plays on words and puns. Alternatively, the word may be a scribal error for <em>puzbal </em>(place of sacrifice), a reading whcih fits the context of this passage well." </p>

<p>Colop (página 71, nota 101) parece estar de acuerdo con la última explicación de Christenson, como dice, "[e]l texto K'iche' dice <em>Pusbal Chaaj. Pusbal </em>quiere decir 'lugar del sacrificio,' y <em>chaaj </em>'juego de pelota.'" No menciona que interpretar el original como <em>Pusbal </em>requiere que sea un error del manuscrito.</p>

<p>Ximénez's translation, "donde echaban la zeniza" is perhaps the strangest at first glance, and to modern eyes may give the impression that Hun Hunahpu and Vucub Hunahpu were thrown on some sort of garbage dump. Some light may be shed on it by Christenson's translation of <em>puk'b'al </em>as "the dustiness of the ballcourt or the tendency to kick up dust during vigorous play." Ximénez may have directly translated a metaphor without an easy Spanish (or English) equivalent.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;alel Achij</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>873</nid>
    <key>QALEL_ACHIJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> v ꜫalel achih</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ꜫalel achih </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;alel Ajaw</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>819</nid>
    <key>QALEL_AJAW</key>
    <ximenez_spa> ꜫalel ahau</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ꜫalelahau </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;alel K&#039;amja</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>855</nid>
    <key>QALEL_KAMJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> calecamha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cale camha </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Este tercer señor de los Nija'ib tiene un nombre que significa "ministro o capitán", del cual se deduce su importante rol "en función de canciller" (Colop 2008: nota 335, página 251-2).</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 760, p. 256): "<em>Q'alel K'am Ja</em> (Magistrate Reception House)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;alel Saqik</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>865</nid>
    <key>QALEL_SAQIK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ꜫalel zaquic</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ꜫalel zaquic</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;aq&#039; Laqam</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>990</nid>
    <key>QAQ_LAQAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Caꜫlacan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Caꜫlacan</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 879, p. 285): "<em>Kaq' Lakan</em> (Red/Fire Banner)."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 401, página 217) sugiere que "<em>q'aq' </em>puede ser 'fuego' o <em>kaq</em>, 'rojo.' <em>Laqam</em> 'bandera' conforme Basseta."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;ukumatz</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>635</nid>
    <key>QUKUMATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>gucumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>gucumatz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;ukumatz_Persona</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>866</nid>
    <key>QUKUMATZ_PERSONA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>gucumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>gucumatz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Q&#039;umaraq Aj</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1261</nid>
    <key>QUMARAQ_AJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>cumarcaaj</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cumarca ah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 732, page 251) translates the name of the settlement <em>Q'umarkaj</em> as "Ancient/Rotten Canes/Reeds." He explains: "The name of this citadel has generally been translated 'Place of Rotten Canes' (Recinos 1950, 215, D. Tedlock 1996, 183). <em>Q'umarik</em>, however, also refers to something ancient, while aj can be used for a wide variety of reeds. The more likely translation of the citadel is thus 'Place of Ancient Reeds.' This ties the city figuratively with the ancient place of their origin at Tulan (Place of Reeds). Following the Spanish conquest, Cumarcah was renamed Utatlan by the Tlaxcalan allies of the invaders. In the Tlaxcalan dialect of Nahuatl, this name means 'among the reeds,' a close translation of the Quiché name (Carmack 1981, 143). Cumarcah was the capital of the Nima Quichés.</p>

<p>En la versión poética escrita en idioma k'iche', Sam Colop (2004: nota 320, página 180) confirma la interpretación de Dennis Tedlock. En la estrofa el destacado traductor k'iche' escribe "Q'uma'r kaj", pero explica en una nota marginal que "Quizás Tedlock (1996: 320) está en lo correcto al decir que la identificación del lugar debería ser <em>Q'umaraq aj</em>."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Quetzalcóatl</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>723</nid>
    <key>QUETZALCÓATL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> quítzalcuat</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>quitzalcuat </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>R.P.F. (Reverendo Padre Fray) Francisco Ximénez</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1061</nid>
    <key>XIMENEZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>R.P.F. FRANZÍSCO XIMENEZ</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>R.P.F. FRANZÍSCO XIMENEZ</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Fray Francisco Ximénez, O.P. was a Dominican friar born in Écija, Spain in 1666. He is the author of the manuscript known as <em>Ayer MS 1515</em>, housed at the Newberry Library in Chicago. <em>MS 1515</em> includes the text presented here, "Empiezan las historias del origen de los índíos de esta provinçia de Gvatemala tradvcido de la lengva qviche en la castellana para mas commodidad de los mínístros de el Sto. Evangelío," or the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, and its attendant "Escolios." Ximénez compiled the work in 1701 and 1702 during his time as a parish priest in Santo Tomás Chichicastenango. In the prologue, he claims to have transcribed the K'iche' text from various indigenous sources and translated it into Spanish himself.</p>

<p>Ximénez arrived in Guatemala in 1688 and was ordained in 1689. Besides the text now known as the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, his works include a three-part linguistic study of K'iche', Zutujil, and Kaqchikel entitled <em>Tesoro de las tres lenguas</em> (1701–1704); <em>Historia de la provincia de San Vicente de Chiapa y Guatemala de la Orden de Predicadores</em> (1715); and <em>Historia natural de Guatemala</em> (1722). His writings are based on the knowledge of Mayan cultures and languages that he acquired as a parish priest and administrator over his approximately four decades in various Guatemalan towns, including Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, Rabinal, Santo Domingo de Xenacoc, Sacapulas San Raimundo, and Candelaria.</p>

<p>As Néstor Quiroa crucially notes, "Francisco Ximénez composed all of his works as a contribution to his order’s objective: to convert the native population to Christianity. Thus, it is not a coincidence that Ximénez placed his 'ethnographic' work on the Maya-K’iche’ religion within an ecclesiastic treatise, nor is it an accident that scholars have chosen to examine his text as if it existed apart from this religious context."</p>

<p>Ximénez died circa 1729.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Rabinal</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1113</nid>
    <key>RABINAL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>rabinal</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>rabinal</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Rabinal refers both to the Achí ("man"), a group related to the K'iche' and to their town, which remains to this day.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Rabinaleb</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>796</nid>
    <key>RABINALEB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Rabanal</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>rabinaleb </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the thirteen allied lineages, associated with the <em>tinamit </em>of Rab’inal. </p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 354) identifies the <em>Rab’inaleb’ </em>as “the people known today as Achí [“man” in K’iche’] who speak Achí (a dialect of Quiché) and whose principal town is Rabinal, on the northeast frontier of what was once the Quiché kingdom. They belonged to a group of thirteen allied tribes the Quichés regarded as having come (like themselves) from the east. One of the Rabinal citadels, Spilt Water, was conquered by the Quiché lords duirng the reign of Quicab.”</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 204, note 510): “Akkeren (2000, 248) translates the name of this lineage as ‘Place of the Lord’s Daugther,’ based on the Kekchi <em>rab’in </em>(daughter of male/princess) and <em>-al </em>(place of). Their principal center of occupation was the area around present-day Rabinal.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Rajpop Achij</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>874</nid>
    <key>RAJPOP_ACHIJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> rah pop achíh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>rahpop achih </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Rajtz&#039;alam Achij</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>875</nid>
    <key>RAJTZALAM_ACHIJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> rahtzalam achíh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>rahtzalam achih </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Raxa Kakulja </title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>14</nid>
    <key>RAXA_CACULHA</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Raxa Kakulja </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Raxa Kaqulja</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>646</nid>
    <key>RAXA_KAQULJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>raxa caculha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>raxa caculha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Río de Podre</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1059</nid>
    <key>AGUA_PODRIDA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>--</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>puch chi a</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>A river of pus crossed by Hun Hunahpu and Vucub Hunahpu appears in all the translated versions, but not in Ximenez's Spanish manuscript (folio 14r). Both Christenson (Literal Poetic, page 72, note 45) and Colop (page 68, note 96) assert that the K'iche' manuscript's <em>puch </em>is a scribal error<em> </em>for <em>puj </em>"pus." This may have caused Ximénez confusion during the translation.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Río de Sangre</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1058</nid>
    <key>RIO_DE_SANGRE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vn río q’ era de sangre</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chiquiquia</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Two of the obstacles traversed by travellers into Xib'alb'a were rivers of blood and pus, both of which, the narrative suggests, are deadly to drink. Neither One and Seven Hunahpu nor their children are stopped by them. Christenson (p. 122): "Then they arrived at Blood River. They were able to pass through, because they did not drink from it." Ibid (p. 160): "And again they passed over Pus River and Blood River. In their hearts, the Xibalbans had intended these as traps. But they were not troubled. They just passed over them, floating on their blowguns."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>River Scorpion</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1057</nid>
    <key>JA_SIMAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>palos puntíagudos</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ha zimah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The idea of a "river of scorpions" is present in Christenson's and Tedlock's translations, but Ximénez, Colop, and Recinos find other ways of expressing the concept in Spanish. </p>

<p>Ximénez transcribes the K'iche' as "chupan halhal ha zimah, maui ahílan zimah," which Christenson (<em>Literal Poetic Translation</em>, page 72) renders in modern orthography as "chupan jal ja'l: Ja' Simaj, Mawi ajilan simaj." He translates these words as "Into turbulent rivers: River Scorpion, not counted scorpions."</p>

<p>Ximénez's translation, on the other hand, reads "de allí al agua q’ se trueca; y pasaron donde todo era palos puntíagudos" (folio 14r.), and Colop (page 67) has "turbulentes y espinadas corrientes<em>." </em>This disagreement is likely due to an ambiguity in the K'iche' source text.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saint Thomas Aquinas</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1145</nid>
    <key>AQUINAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Thomas</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/St-thomas-aquinas.jpg?itok=aWLgixWI" width="67" height="100" alt="Saint Thomas Aquinas by Carlo Crivelli / Wikimedia Commons" title="Saint Thomas Aquinas by Carlo Crivelli / Wikimedia Commons" /></image>
    <description><p>Saint Thomas Aquinas was a Dominican friar, theologian, and philosopher who was the most prominent thinker in scholasticism and the father of the Thomist tradition.</p>

<p>Santo Tomás de Aquino era un fraile dominicano, teólogo, y filósofo quien era el escolástico más prominente y el padre de la tradición tomista.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Salmanasar</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>924</nid>
    <key>SALMANASAR</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Salmanasar</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Salmanasar</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>"Salmanasar" is the Latin iteration of the name of Shalmaneser V, king of Assyria from 727–722 BC. The second book of Kings details his conquest of the kingdom of Samaria, after which he expelled and deported the population of Israelites later known as the "Ten Lost Tribes" of Israel. Ximénez believed that the K'iche', like other indigenous peoples of the Americas, descended from these tribes. In his <em>Escolios</em>, he writes that the K'iche' "conseruaron algo de el líbro de el genesís, dado q'desçendíesen de las díez tríbus q'en tíempo de Salmanasar, se perdieron".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>San Anton Ilocab</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>923</nid>
    <key>SAN_ANTON_ILOCAB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>S Anton ílocab</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>S Anton ílocab</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>This is a reference to San Antonio Ilotenango. According to Ruud van Akkeren, "En este pueblo colonial se asentó la rama ilocab [<em>Ilokab'</em>] de los quichés [<em>k'iche's</em>]. Aparentemente, tenían un lienzo que Ximénez pudo estudiar" (218).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>San Juan Bautista</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1081</nid>
    <key>SAN_JUAN_BAUTISTA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>S. Juo. Baptísta</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Saint John the Baptist was a prophet and a preacher, and the cousin of Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>San Juan Bautista era un profeta y un predicador, y el primo de Jesucristo.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>San Pablo</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1073</nid>
    <key>SAN_PABLO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>S. Pablo</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Saint Paul the Apostle was an apostle of Christ in first-century Asia Minor and Europe. Of the 27 books of the New Testament, 14 are attributed to him.</p>

<p>San Pablo el Apóstol era un apóstol de Cristo en Asia Menor y Europa en el primer siglo. De los 27 libros en el Nuevo Testamento, se atribuyen 14 a él.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>San Vicente Ferrer</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1144</nid>
    <key>FERRER</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Ferrer</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/ferrer.jpg?itok=J3y8H6jh" width="80" height="100" alt="Vicente Ferrer, Wikimedia Commons" title="Vicente Ferrer, Wikimedia Commons" /></image>
    <description><p>Vincent Ferrer (1350–1419) was a Dominican priest and canonized saint.</p>

<p>Vicente Ferrer (1350–1419) era un fraile dominico y un santo canonizado.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>sangre de sacrificio</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>696</nid>
    <key>SANGRE_DE_SACRIFICIO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>lotzquíc</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>lotzquíc</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Santa Cruz</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1016</nid>
    <key>SANTA_CRUZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Sta Cruz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Sta. Cruz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 892, page 287) helpfully glosses the history of the place name and its role in the Spanish conquest of Mesoamerica. He writes: "Bishop Francisco Marroquín blessed the ruins of Cumarcah in 1539, renaming it Santa Cruz (Spanish: 'Holy Cross'). In about 1555, the Spaniards founded a new administrative center three miles to the east, which they also named Santa Cruz del Quiché (Spanish: Holy Cross of the Quiché). This was likely carried out under the direction of Alonso de Zorita who administered affairs in various Guatemalan provinces beginning in March 1555, including the area of Utatlan. Akkeren suggests that this compilation of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> was carried out in conjunction with the abandonment of the old capital (Akkeren 2003). The resettlement process, which the Spaniards called congregación (congregation), followed a uniform pattern throughout Guatemala (García Peláez 1943, 161-166; Betancor and Arboleda 1964). First, a church was erected at the center of the proposed site fronted by an open plaza, or atrio, for large assemblies to gather for public ceremonies and indoctrination. The rest of the town was organized into squares divided by streets laid out to the cardinal directions. While the new settlement was under construction, families planted their maize on plots the Spaniards assigned to them in the nearby countryside. When the crops were ready to harvest, the older Precolumbian structures were destroyed to prevent reoccupation, and the people moved into their new homes. Christian missionaries staged elaborate dances and festivals to celebrate the event 'so that they would forget their ancient dwellings' (García Peláez 1943, 163)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saqajib</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>799</nid>
    <key>SAQAJIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> zacahíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>zacahib </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the thirteen allied lineages.</p>

<p>Christenson (p. 204 note 513) derives the name of this lineage from <em>Saq Aj </em>“White Ear of Unripe Maize.”</p>

<p>Tedlock (p. 360) glosses it differently as <em>saq k’ajib’, </em>or “White Cornmeals,” saying “they must have settled in the area of the present town of Salcajá, called <em>Saqk’aja </em>in Quiché.”</p>

<p>Ximénez’s spelling, <em>zacahib, </em>is ambiguous, as his orthography would likely not distinguish between -<em>q- </em>and -<em>qk’-</em>.</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saqi Nim Aq Sis</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>633</nid>
    <key>SAQI_NIM_AQ_SIS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Zaquinima tzÿz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Zaquinima tzÿz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 17, p. 52) translates the name<em> Saqi Nima Aq</em> as "Great White Peccary"; Colop pairs <em>Saqi Nima Aq </em>with the word <em>Sis</em> in the following line. Christenson explains the etymologies and symbolism as such: "The word saqi may be translated as 'light, bright, or white.' Later in the text (p. 98; line 1055), this same god is described as having very white hair due to his advanced age; thus 'white' is the most likely translation here. In that same passage, 'Great White Peccary' is given as one of the names or titles of the patriarchal creator god Xpiyacoc mentioned in the next paragraph. There are two species of peccary, or wild pig, living in Central America—<em>Peccari angulatus yucatanensis</em> (Collared Peccary) and <em>Tayassu pecari </em>(White-lipped Peccary). The latter is perhaps intended here because it is the larger of the two and is decorated with white facial markings."</p>

<p>En cuanto a la primera mención del divino <em>Saqi Nima Aq</em>, Sam<em> </em>Colop (2011: nota 4, página 201) observa que "los adjetivos <em>saqi nim</em>, 'blanco grande', están omitidos del segundo verso paralelo; pero líneas más adelante aparecen completos. Aquí la referencia zoomórfica es más directa y aclara que son la pareja de ancianos (tiempo) que acompañal el proceso de creación. Son los mismos que acompañan a Junajpu y Xbalamke a vender a Wuqub Kak'ix. Recinos (1953: 82) relaciona a <em>Saqi Nim Sis</em> como 'diosa madre' y a <em>Saqi Nim Aq</em> como su 'consorte'".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saqik</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>825</nid>
    <key>SAQIK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>zaquíquíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xuxic qui</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 333, página 250) afirma que "El linaje Saqik conforme <em>El Título de Totonicapán</em> vino a sustituir al de Ik'ibalam, que no dejó descendencia. Ese título literalmente dice: 'Señor Sakic Ts'utujá el sustituto de Iquí Balam' (Carmack y Mondlock, 1983: 189). Entre estos dos linajes parece haber una conexión lingüística: <em>saqik</em> puede provenir de <em>saq</em>, 'claro, blanco'; <em>ik'</em>, 'luna', 'luna clara', mientras que el nombre de Ik'ibalam, como se dijo en capítulo aparte, significa 'jaguar luna'".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saqikas</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>694</nid>
    <key>SAQIKAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>zaquícaz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>zaquícaz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Saqkabaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>827</nid>
    <key>SAQKABAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>zacabaha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>zacabaha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>A town, idenfitied by Colop (p. 200, n. 344) as “el actual pueblo de San Andrés Sajcabajá” and the people associated with it.</p>

<p><em>Saq </em>means “white,” <em>kab’ </em>“sugar” or “honey,” and <em>ja </em>“house.” Thus a possible translation of this name is “white honey house.”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Satanás</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1074</nid>
    <key>SATANAS</key>
    <ximenez_spa>El demonío</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>In Catholicism, Satan is a being who tempts humans to sin against God. As a demon, he is characterized as an angel (that is, an entirely spiritual, not physical, creature) who rebelled against God. Ximénez refers to him interchangeably as "la bestia infernal," "Satanas," and most frequently, "el demonío."</p>

<p>En el catolicismo, Satanás es un ser que tenta a los humanos a pecar contra Dios. Como un demonio, se caracteriza como un ángel (es decir, un ser creado totalmente espiritual sin cuerpo físico) quien se rebeló contra Dios. Ximénez refiere a él como "la bestia infernal," "Satanas," y más frecuentemente, "el demonío."</p>

<p><em>Please note that our use of the label "deidad" applies to supernatural agents in general.</em></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Señores de Xibalba</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>687</nid>
    <key>SEÑORES_DE_XIBALBA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> SSres delínfierno</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>conohel rahaual xibalba </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Serpiente Emplumada</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>648</nid>
    <key>SERPIENTE_EMPLUMADA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> tepeu y gucumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tepeu qucumatz </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Most translators (Christenson 2007: 17, lines 145-146; Recinos 2012: 23) translate the concept of the name "serpiente emplumada" (feathered serpent) into the proper name of the divine figure Q'ukumatz (or Gucumatz, in Recinos's orthography), more commonly known as the Mesoamerican god, Quetzalcoatl. But K'iche' translator and scholar Sam Colop offers a different interpretation, which we represent below in Spanish. English-language readers will find that Dennis Tedlock's translation is close to Colop's, in that Tedlock distinguishes between "Sovereign Plumed Serpent", or Quetzalcoatl, and the "Plumed Serpent," mentioned here. Tedlock (1996: 64) writes, "They are there, they are enclosed in quetzal feathers, in blue-green. Thus the name, 'Plumed Serpent.'" In an endnote (#64, page 222) he adds: "This is <em>pa q'uq', </em><em>pa raxon</em>, in which <em>q'uq' </em>is the primary term for quetzal or its feathers and <em>raxon</em> is identified by PG [Pantaléon de Guzmán, <em>Compendio de nombres en lengva cakchiqvel</em>, ed. René Acuña. México (UNAM, 1984)] as an alternative term for the same thing. <em>Raxon</em> is a nomal form of <em>rax</em>, a color adjective covering the blue to green range."</p>

<p>En vez de escribir el nombre del dios creador "Q'ukumatz," Sam Colop (2011: página 26) prefiere expresar el nombre así: "Dimanaban luz / estando en vueltos de plumas de quetzal / en plumas azules / de ahí la nominación de 'Serpiente Emplumada.'" Explica la traducción de esta manera en las notas al pie (notas 18-19, página 204): “El texto k’iche’ dice <em>saqtetoj e k’o wi</em> donde <em>saqtetoj</em> quiere decir ‘luz que sale de entre las plumas’ donde estaban envueltos. Ésta es una lectura inversa fundada en Basseta quien traduce <em>saqteoj</em> como ‘la claridad que entrap or los risquieros’, es decir entre los resquicios. Asimismo, el texto literalmente dice que estaban ‘enterrados’ entre plumas verdes y azules. La palabra <em>q’uq’</em> significa quetzal, pero también así se llaman sus plumas. <em>Razxon</em> es otra ave de plumas color azul que está asociada al quetzal. En el diccionario de Basseta se dice: ‘<em>Q’uq’</em>: la pluma verde y el pájaro que le cría. <em>Raxon</em>: pluma azul y el pájaro.”</p>

<p>De esta forma Colop (2011: nota 19, página 205) observa que en la siguiente línea, "Aquí se aclara por qué se dice 'Serpiente Emplumada.' Es por la luz o blancura que escapa de entre las plumas de quetzal en medio de la oscuridad. Si vemos a esta ave de frente, debajo de sus plumas verdes tiene unas blancas y en k'iche' la palabra para 'luz' es la misma que para 'blanco.' La metáfora, entonces, está asociada al ave."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Silisib</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>833</nid>
    <key>SILISIB</key>
    <ximenez_spa> pazílízíb</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>pa zilizib </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>At this place the K’iche’ people extracted the hearts of their sacrificial victims, who were tricked into “giving the breast,” (Colop (p. 165) has “ofrec[ir] la piel”) a “play on words whereby the nations were tricked into offering to <em>tu’nik </em>(give the breast, suckle, nurture), a metaphor for nurturing or giving sustenance. In reality, however, they were being tricked into offering their own breasts in the form of heart extraction sacrifice” (Christenson, p. 237, note 627).</p>

<p>Christenson defines <em>Pa Silisib’ </em>as “staggering, shaking” (p. 237, note 628). Tedlock (p. 165) has “stagger.”</p>

<p>Colop (p. 165, n. 271): Silisib’ “viene del verbo <em>silobik </em>que significa ‘meneo’ o ‘tembladera.’”</p>

<p>In modern K'iche', the verb <em>silab'ik </em>means "to move," which fits with Colop's explanation. This form is derived from a positional root <em>sil, </em>which is related to small, shaking movements. The descriptive form <em>silisik </em>is derived via reduplication, from which the instrumental form <em>silisib' </em>is created by means of the suffix <em>-b'. </em>The meaning of this form is "place of movement, place of trembling."</p>

<p>Colop asocia este nombre con el terror de “el hecho de cuando los pueblos temblaban de frío y por el terror que se avecina” al atender su matanza en sacrificio a Tojil.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Sipakna</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>657</nid>
    <key>SIPAKNA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>zipacna</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>zipacna</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Sipakna is killed when the Hero Twins trick him into being crushed by a mountain (Meawan). Christensen (page 96, note 168) suggests that a toponym associated with Sipakna still exists. "This is a long hill in the center of the Rabinal valley roughly the shape of a crocodile. It is still called Sipak and the people of Rabinal associate it with a crocodile (Akkeren 2000, 60)." Since Meawan is also near Rabinal, it is not impossible that Sipak represents Sipakna's actual body underneath the layer of stone that crushed him.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Sotz&#039;i Ja Chimalkan</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>725</nid>
    <key>SOTZI_JA_CHIMALKAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa> tzotzíha, chímal cam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tzotziha chimalcan </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Su Majestad</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1095</nid>
    <key>SU_MAJESTAD</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Su Magestad</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Though "His Majesty" ("Su Majestad") is a general title for the Spanish king, Ximénez's references to "sus leyes de índías" (escolio 3 recto, line 27) make this most likely a reference to Charles II of Spain, whose 1680 compendium of the Laws of the Indies was the most prominent edition. When Ximénez was compiling this manuscript (1701–1702), Charles II had only just abdicated to Philip V, and the transition was a long enough process (both politically and in terms of transatlantic news dissemination) that the reference is somewhat ambiguous.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Su&#039;</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1255</nid>
    <key>SU'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/4629_0.jpeg?itok=uZGvDntZ" width="100" height="38" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=4629" title="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=4629. Kerr #4629, &quot;Masked dancers playing flutes over an offering&quot;" /></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Suywa</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>751</nid>
    <key>SUYWA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>--</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>--</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the names of the city of Tulán, often referred to as Tulán-Suywa (or Tulan-Zuyua). The name Suywa does not appear on its own.</p>

<p>    Tedlock (p. 362): “In Yucatec Maya, the term <em>suyua t’an, </em>‘twisted (or deceptive) speech,’ refers to riddles whose answers were demanded of pretenders to lordly positions.”</p>

<p>    Christenson (p. 210): “<em>Suy, </em>in lowland Maya languages, is a ‘whirlpool,’ or something twisted. <em>Suywa </em>is ‘confusion,’ and <em>suywa t’an </em>is ‘figurative or rhetorical language.’ In the <em>Book of Chilam Balam of Chumayel, </em>the ‘language of Suywa’ refers to a series of riddles and plays on words that only true lords were able to solve prove their legitimacy. In Nahua, <em>Zuyua </em>is ‘Bloody Water,’ a reading that is specifically recognized elsewhere in the <em>Chilam Balam of Chumayel. </em>The <em>Annals of the Cakchiquels </em>agrees with the <em>Popol Vuh </em>in locating this area with the ‘Tulan in the East.’ In the Yucatec Maya <em>Books of Chilam Balam, </em>Zuyua is identified with Xicalanco, an ancient port city on the shores of the Laguna de Términos in the Mexican state of Tabasco.”</p>

<p>Given the meaning of <em>Suywa, </em>it is possible that the name references the confusion of languages said to have occured there (folio 41 recto).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tamasul</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>693</nid>
    <key>TAMASUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tamazul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tamazul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tamub</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>814</nid>
    <key>TAMUB</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tamub</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tamub</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tecolote Cabeza</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>686</nid>
    <key>TECOLOTE_CABEZA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tecolote cabeza</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tecolote cabeza</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tecolote de una Pierna</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>684</nid>
    <key>TECOLOTE_DE_UNA_PIERNA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tecolote de vna pierna</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tecolote de vna pierna</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tecolote Flecha</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>683</nid>
    <key>TECOLOTE_FLECHA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>saeta tecolote</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>saeta tecolote</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tecolote Guacamaya</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>685</nid>
    <key>TECOLOTE_GUACAMAYA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>guacamaya tecolote</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>guacamaya tecolote</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tekum</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>877</nid>
    <key>TEKUM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Tecum</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Tecum</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Según observa Allen Christenson (2007: nota 849, página 276), el nombre Tekum, "is likely 'enthroned' based on the Nahua tecalli (throne, seat). Tedlock cites a Quiché dictionary compiled by Fermín Joseph Tirado in 1787 which lists tekum as a 'large, black butterfly that flies with great speed' (D. Tedlock 1996, 333 n. 195)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tepepul</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>842</nid>
    <key>TEPEPUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Tepepul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Tepepul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Tepepul first appears in the list of Kaweq K'iche' rulers in his association with Iztayul, in the sixth generation. Subsequent ruling generations share his name: Tepepul (who ascended in 1475) and Iztayub form the eighth generation, and Tukum and Tepepul are the ninth generation.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tepew</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>634</nid>
    <key>TEPEW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tepeu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tepeu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tepew Oloman</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>812</nid>
    <key>TEPEW_OLOMAN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tepeu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tepeu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tepew Q&#039;ukumatz</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>636</nid>
    <key>TEPEW_QUKUMATZ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tepeu, qucumatz</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tepeu, qucumatz</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2011: nota 5, páginas 201-202) observa que "Tepew es una palabra náhuatl que significa 'conquistador' o 'victorioso' y se compone de los términos <em>te- </em>'gente' y <em>-pew</em>, 'conquistar' (Campbell, 1983), que en este caso es el adjetivo, y Q'ukumatz es el nominal. La expresión ha sido traducida como 'majestad' (Edmonson, 1971: 4) y 'soberana' (D. Tedlock, 1996: 63). En este contexto es una metonimia de Quetzalcóatl. Q'ukumatz es mi escritura porque Recinos lo escribe <em>Gucumatz</em>. Para mayor claridad, Recinos dice: 'es la versión quich'e de <em>Kukulcán</em>, el nombre maya que <em>Quetzalcóatl</em>' (Recinos, 1953: 82) y que significa 'majestuosa serpiente emplumada'". Cita a Lyle Campell, "Préstamos lingüísticos en el <em>Popol Vuh</em>". En <em>Nuevas prespectivas sobre el Popol Vuh</em>, editado por Robert M. Carmack y Francisco Morales Santos. Guatemala: Editorial Piedra Santa, páginas 81-86 y Munro Edmonson, <em>The Book of Counsel: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute. Publicación número 35. New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971.</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: notes 19-20, pages 52-53) breaks the terms <em>Tepew </em>and <em>Q'ukumatz</em> into two entities, noting, "<em>Tepew</em> (Sovereign) is one of several words in the <em>Popol Vuh</em> that were borrowed from the central Mexican group of languages, Nahua, variants of which were spoken by both the epi-Toltec and Aztec nations. This word is the Quiché form of the Nahua tepeuh, meaning 'conqueror' or 'majesty' (Campbell 1970, 4). Coto and Basseta record that in the Colonial era, the Quichés recognized the word as referring to 'majesty, dignity, lordship, power.' Tedlock and Recinos translate the word as 'sovereign,' which I prefer to the more descriptive 'majesty' used by Edmonson."</p>

<p>In the note for <em>Q'ukumatz</em>, he remarks: "The male quetzal’s tail feathers were highly prized by Maya royalty for their beauty and size, often reaching three feet in length. The unique coloration of the bird carried profound religious significance for the Maya. Its predominant blue/green feathers represented sky and vegetation, both symbols of life. Its red breast represented fire, the force that quickens life. Kumatz is a general term for “snake” or “serpent.” The serpent was a common Maya symbol for regeneration or rebirth because of its tendency to periodically shed its skin to reveal a newer and brighter one. The combination of an avian lord of the skies with a serpentine lord of the earth and underworld gave this god power over all levels of the Maya universe. He is undoubtedly related to the well-known god Quetzalcoatl (Nahua for “Quetzal Serpent) worshiped by the Aztecs of Central Mexico."Citing: Lyle Campbell, Nahua Loan Words in Quichean Languages, <cite>Chicago Linguistic Society </cite>(1971) 6: 3-13.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tinamit Quiché</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1038</nid>
    <key>TINAMIT_KICHE</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el pueblo de quiche</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tinamit quiche</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (page 59; note 7) says: "based on <em>tinamit</em>, a Nahua-derived word meaning 'fortified town, citadel, or fortification wall' (Campbell, 1983, 85). Although in modern Quiché, "tinamit" simply refers to a town or city, the word is used in the <em>Popol Vuh </em>to specify fortified centers occupied by ruling lineages (Carmack 1981, 23). Here the citadel of the Quiché people is also called Quiché, apparently referring to the heartland region of their nation. This would include the capital city, Cumarcah [Q'umarkaj], as well as its surrounding territory."</p>

<p>It is worth noting that the very last line of the <em>Popol Vuh </em>states "xere k'u ri mi xutzinik chi konojel K'iche', Sta. Cruz u b'i'" ("but therefore this was completed now all Quiché, Sta. Cruz its name.") This turn of phrase suggests that the initial "tinamit" reference may in fact refer to Santa Cruz del Quiché, the relocated site of Q'umarkaj/Utatlán, in particular. Or, it may be one of many words whose meanings change over the course of the narrative. We present multiple viewpoints so that readers may interpret the meaning in their own ways.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tojil</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>717</nid>
    <key>TOJIL</key>
    <ximenez_spa> tohíl</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tohil </ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Tohil%201.jpg?itok=FL0BMPKf" width="64" height="100" /></image>
    <description><p>According to Christenson (2007: 198), "In the Quiché language, <em>tojil</em> refers to a 'payment, debt, obligation, or tribute.' This is consistent with this god’s demand for tribute and sacrifice. Toj is one of the named days in the highland Maya calendar. During divination ceremonies the day Toj implies the need to pay a debt in a metaphoric sense."</p>

<p>In contrast, Coe and Houston (2015: 226) reference "the Temple of Tojil, a Jaguar deity connected with the sun and rain."</p>

<p><img alt="" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="1" data-fid="228" data-media-element="1" height="260" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/tojil%202.jpg" title="" width="400" /></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>tres Casas Grandes</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>824</nid>
    <key>TRES_CASAS_GRANDES</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tres casas grandes</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tres casas grandes</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Three family lines represent the Three Great Houses of the <em>Popol Wuj</em>: Kaweq, Ajaw K'iche', Nija'ib.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tujal Ja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>802</nid>
    <key>TUJAL_JA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tuhal ha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tuhal ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tujal Ja_Lugar</title>
    <type>lugar</type>
    <nid>785</nid>
    <key>LUGAR_DE_TUJAL_JA</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tuhal ha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007, fn516): "The Tujal Ja (Sweatbath House) occupied the area surrounding the modern community of Sacapulas (Recinos 1950, 171 n. 6; Fox 1978, 76). Fox suggests that the settlement of this lineage may be identified with the ruins of Chutinamit, located just across the river and north of present-day Sacapulas, which once controlled the valuable salt springs nearby (Fox 1978, 81). The Tujalhas were conquered by Lord Quicab in the early fifteenth century at the same time as the rest of the Sacapulas Valley (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 93; 1957, 141-143; Carmack 1973, 369-371)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tulán</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>750</nid>
    <key>TULÁN</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tulan zu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tulan zu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez describes "tulan zu" (<em>tulan zuiva </em>in the K'ich'e) as a "monte" (<em>huyub</em>). This may reflect the K'iche' practice of building fortified <em>tinamit </em>(citadels) on hilltops.</p>

<p>There are various possibilities for the identity of Tulan. Christenson explains its etymology as "Nahua <em>Tullan </em>or <em>Tollan</em>: 'Place of Cattail Reeds'. In the Quiché language, <em>tulan </em>is a 'palace, or manor-house' (Basseta), while <em>tolan </em>is a city or house that has been abandoned, perhaps referring to the ruins of once great cities that dot the region and that belong to the legendary ancestors of the Maya people. In Aztec theology, Tollan was a mythic place located near Coatepec (Snake Mountain) where the ancestors of the Mexica received their patron god Huitzilopochtli. In this myth, Tollan was inhabited by the Toltecs, great sages who invented the sciences of astronomy, calendrics, agriculture, and medcine, as well as the arts of writing, painting, sculpture, metalwork, jade carving, and weaving. Throughout Mesoamerica in the late Postclassic era (ca. 1200–1524), the legendary Toltecs where the bearers of political legitimacy. The Aztecs used the name <em>Tollan </em>to refer to thier own legendary palce of origin, as well as a general term for 'city.'…The Tulan mentioned here [in the <em>Popol Vuh</em>] was likely either Chichen Itza, a major center of power during the Terminal Classic (800–900) and early Postclassic (900–1200) periods, or its successor Mayapan. Both would have been "across the sea" (the Gulf of Mexico) with respect to the Guatemalan highlands as described in the Popol Vuh."</p>

<p>Colop (página 141, nota 223) identifica <em>Tulan </em>con Tula de Guerrero, hoy día un pequeño pueblo en el noreste del estado Mexicano de Guerrero.</p>

<p>Tedlock (page 359) identifies Tulan as "a town in the east that was like the Classic Maya site of Copán in having a bat as its insignia. The lords of the Quiché, Cakchiquel, and other 'mountain people' gathered there, paying tribute and acquiring their respective patron deities. by the time they found their own places to rule, Tulan had been abandoned. The site was probably not called Tulan until after its demise."</p>

<p>Tedlock also lists Suywa and "Seven Caves, Seven Canyons" as other names of Tulan.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tz&#039;aqol</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>627</nid>
    <key>TZAQOL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tzacol</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tzacol</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Colop (2008: nota 1, página 201) observa que el nombre divino, aquí escrito en forma de quiasmo, significa "Literalmente el 'constructor' y 'creador'. <em>Tz'qa</em> y <em>bit</em> son raíces verbales 'construir' y 'crear'. <em>Tz'aq</em> quiere decur 'construcción' y <em>bit</em> 'creación'. El sufijo <em>-ol</em>, en ambos sustantivos, es marcador agentivo."</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: 36) calls the relationship between Tz'aqol and Bitol, translated as "Framer" and "Shaper," respectively, "associative parallelism," or the use of the literary device of parallelism to show complimentary elements. Specifically, Tz'aqol and Bitol, "Framer and Shaper," are an example of "functional association," a poetic device "in which two elements act in a similar manner."</p>

<p>In the text proper, Christenson (2007: note 12, p. 51) writes, "<em>Tz'aqol</em> (Framer) refers to one who makes something by putting things together (i.e., a building from stone or adobe, a meal from various ingredients, or a woven cloth from individual threads)."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tz&#039;u&#039;m</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1233</nid>
    <key>TZ'U'M</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>As Allen Christenson (2007: 106) explains, athletic prowess is symbolically passed down to the Hero Twins from their fathers through the physical objects used to play the ballgame (<em>kik'</em>): yokes (<em>b'ate),</em> kilts or hides (<em>tz’u’m)</em>, armguards (<em>pach' q'ab')</em>, panaches of feather (<em>yachwach</em>), headbands (<em>wach sot</em>), and the ball itself (<em>kik’</em> or <em>cha’j</em>). These are collectively called their “implements” (<em>chokonisan</em>) or “equipment” (<em>etz’ab’al)</em>. </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tz&#039;ununija&#039;</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>710</nid>
    <key>TZUNUNIJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>tzununíha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>tzununíha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Tz&#039;utuja</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>864</nid>
    <key>TZUTUJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Sor. tzutuha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ahau tzutuha </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ub&#039;aqib&#039;al q&#039;aq&#039;</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1256</nid>
    <key>B'AQ_Q'AQ'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Uch&#039;abaja</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>803</nid>
    <key>UCHABAJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vchabaha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vchabaha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Uchuch K&#039;amja</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>852</nid>
    <key>UCHUCH_KAMJA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vchuchcamha</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vchuchcamha</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 752, p. 256): "<em>U Chuch K'am Ja</em> (Its Mother Reception House)."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252) añade que el nombre de esta quinta persona en la línea de sucesión de los Nija'ib significa "asesora" o "consejera de cancillería".</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Uk&#039;u&#039;x Kaj</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>643</nid>
    <key>UKUX_KAJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> el corazon de el zielo, q’se llama huracan</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vqux cah huracan </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Uk&#039;u&#039;x Kaj Uk&#039;u&#039;x Ulew</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>647</nid>
    <key>UKUX_KAJ_UKUX_ULEW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>el corazon de el zielo, y el corazon de la tierra</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>el corazon de el zielo, y el corazon de la tierra</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Uk&#039;u&#039;x Ulew</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1035</nid>
    <key>UKUX_ULEW</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>cah vlew</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Ximénez also writes <em>vqux vleu</em> (Folio 2r; Christenson Prose, p. 73).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>una persona</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>883</nid>
    <key>UNA_PERSONA</key>
    <ximenez_spa> (Demonío q’les hablaba)</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>(Demonium loquens cis) </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: 202) notes that this Latin-language parenthetical aside, which he translates into English as "Demon speaking from here on," represents Ximénez's only explicit commentary in the text.</p>

<p>In his <em>Literal Poetic Translation</em> (2004), Christenson (2004: 192) adds, "This is a singular instance in which Ximénez glosses the text with a brief comment in Latin, referring to the messenger from Xibalba as a demon, or devil. That Ximénez chose to do this only once and in Latin argues for the overall accuracy of the Maya text as he transcribed it."</p>

<p>This is supported by Ximénez's own account in his <em>Historia de la provincia</em>, where he claims (emphasis ours):</p>

<blockquote>
<p>determiné el trasuntar de <strong>verbo adverbum</strong> todas sus historias como las traduje en nuestra lengua Castellana de la lengua Quiche en que las halle escritas desde el tiempo de la conquista, que entonces (como allí dicen) las redujeron de su modo de escribir al nuestro</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For their parts, Colop (2008) and Recinos (1949: 113) translate Ximénez's note, "(Demonium loquens cis) / (Demonío q’les hablaba)" (36v) as "una persona" (a person) and "el mensajero de Xibalbá" (the messenger from Xibalba).</p>

<p>Como así apunta Sam Colop, "Aquí y entre paréntesis, aparece una inserción latina que dice: 'Demonium loquens eis", lo cual es un agregado de Ximénez dentro del texto k'iche' y que en la columna en español traduce como "demonio que les hablaba". Esta asociación demoníaca por parte de Ximénez debe derivarse de que el <em>Popol Wuj</em> se habla de un personaje alado, como un murciélago venido de Xibalba, lugar que Ximénez traduce como 'infierno'" (nota 232, página 235).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Utza&#039;m Achij</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>876</nid>
    <key>UTZAM_ACHIJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa> v tzamachíh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vtzam achih </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>El nombre U Tza'm Achij significa, en inglés, "Their Point Warriors" (Christenson 2007: 285).</p>

<p>Como observa Christenson en su traducción en prosa (2004: 284), "<em>Achij</em> is 'man' but may also refer to 'warriors,' as in this case" (nota 284).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>vac</title>
    <type>animal</type>
    <nid>1120</nid>
    <key>PAJARO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vac</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/uccello.jpg?itok=1Crc5uoQ" width="100" height="56" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: 45) uses the name of this bird, <em>vac</em>, as an example of K'iche' linguistic features: "Long and short vowels are treated as separate letters in Quiché and should be distinguished when written. The Ximénez transcription of the Popol Vuh seldom makes such distinctions. For example, the word transcribed as <em>vach</em> might be read with a long vowel <em>vach</em> ('my companion'), or with a short vowel <em>väch</em> ('my face')."</p>

<p>Tedlock includes a picture of the Vac/Pájaro in his edition of the <em>Popol Vuh. </em>This is the picture that has been selected for this entry.</p>

<p><em> </em></p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Volcán de Acatenango</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1039</nid>
    <key>VOLCAN_DE_ACATENANGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hunahpu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hunahpu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. From Christenson (page 96, note 172): "Edmondson and Recinos identify this volcano as Volcán de Agua, also located in the district of Sacatepequez, southeast of Antigua. Tedlock identifies it with Volcán de Acatenango, located in the same district. In either case, it must be a volcano located near Chigag as the <em>Annals of the Cakchiquels </em>describes it as 'standing abreast' of Chigag."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>volcán de Acatenango</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>661</nid>
    <key>VOLCÁN_DE_ACATENANGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>hun ahpu </ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>hun ahpu </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Volcán de Fuego</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1041</nid>
    <key>VOLCAN_DE_FUEGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>chicac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 171) translates the name Chigag as "Mouth Fire" (Chi'q'aq'), and says, "a volcano in the district of Sacatepequez, Guatemala, nineteen kilometers southeast of Antigua."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>volcán de Fuego</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>660</nid>
    <key>VOLCÁN_DE_FUEGO</key>
    <ximenez_spa>ri chicac (¿?)</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ri chicac (¿?)</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wach Sot</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1250</nid>
    <key>WACH_SOT</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/0761.jpeg?itok=ARPYJjdy" width="100" height="40" alt="Kerr #761: &quot;A Hero Twin make an offering or reading gesture with a bundle and feathers and a codex.&quot;" title="Kerr vase #761: &quot;A Hero Twin make an offering or reading gesture with a bundle and feathers and a codex.&quot; http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=761. " /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: 106; 2004: 66) translates the term as "headdresses," one of the five fine objects that adorn the Hero Twins as they journey to Xibalba. The others are leather, yokes, arm protectors, and face bands.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wajxaqib K&#039;am</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>878</nid>
    <key>WAJXAQIB_KAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa> Vahxaquí caam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Vahxaqui caam </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wak</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>695</nid>
    <key>WAK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vac</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vac</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Winaq Balam</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>1002</nid>
    <key>WINAQ_BALAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Vínac bam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Vínacbam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Escribe Colop (2008: nota 407, página 217): “Comparto el criterio de Edmonson (ibidem) que aquí debe ser <em>Winaq Balam</em> ‘persona jaguar’ en lugar de <em>Bam </em>(que no tiene ningún sentido). Esta traducción conforma un verso paralelo con el nombre precedente, ‘puma.’ Cita a Munro S. Edmonson, <em>The Book of Council: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute Publication vol. 35 (New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971).</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: notes 885-886, p. 285) translates <em>Winaq </em>and <em>B'am</em> separately, as "Person" and "Counselor/Doer," preserving K'iche' aesthetics of complementarity and balance.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wok</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>721</nid>
    <key>WOK</key>
    <ximenez_spa> vox, hun ahpu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>voc hunahpu </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wub&#039;</title>
    <type>herramienta</type>
    <nid>1240</nid>
    <key>WUB'</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/blowgun-vucub-caquixcrop_0.jpg?itok=gVWnXhhy" width="100" height="76" /></image>
    <description><p>Perhaps the most omnipresent of technologies in the <em>Popol Wuj</em>, the blowgun – <em>wub’</em> – plays a significant role in the tale.  At nearly every turn in the Hero Twins’ story, blowguns have a central part in the events, or it is at least noted that they would go “with their blowguns over their shoulders” (<em>ki wub' xkitelej).</em></p>

<p>Blowguns enable Juajpu and Xb’alanke to provide for their family; they allow the Hero Twins to defeat Wuqub’ Kaqix; one even provides them refuge in the House of Bats (Casa de Murciélagos), sheltering them from danger for the night. As the names <em>Junajpu </em>(hunter) and <em>Xb’alanke </em>(predatory animal jaguar) suggest, hunting and the use of the blowgun seem to be a divine calling for the boys, as it was for their fathers before them.</p>

<p>For example, when Wuqub’ Kaqix is defeated using the blowgun, it is said: "Xa u tzij ri u K’u’x Kaj/ Ta xkib’ano (they merely accomplished the word of Heart of Sky)."</p>

<p>The deities are pleased with the Twins’ use of the <em>wub’ </em>to put Wuqub’ Kaqix in his place in response to his haughtiness. The blowgun also comes in handy when receiving messages from the <em>wok </em>(falcon), carrying layers of animal messengers in his stomach, is brought down by the <em>wub’</em> and able to relay information from the underworld.</p>

<div> </div></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wuqub Aj</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>998</nid>
    <key>WUQUB_AJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Vucub ah</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Vucubah</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 882, p. 285) translates <em>Wuqub' Aj</em> as "Seven Reed/Cane," so-named for the "day in the traditional 260 day calendar."</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 404, página 217) explica que el nombre <em>Wuqub Aj </em>quiere decir el "Día del calendario '7 caña'."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wuqub Junajpu</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>668</nid>
    <key>WUQUB_JUNAJPU</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vvcub hun ahpu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vvcub hun ahpu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wuqub Kak&#039;ix</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>654</nid>
    <key>WUQUB_KAKIX</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vvcub caquix</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vvcub caquix</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%200637%20wuqub%20kakix.jpeg?itok=-9j_DeNz" width="100" height="29" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=637" title="Kerr #637 Early Classic bowl with the image of ITZ&#039;AM YEJ (itzam ye) aka Vucub Caquix" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 150, page 78) notes that "The scarlet macaw (Ara macao) is a large species of parrot with beautiful, bright-red plumage. Seven Macaw is portrayed as a boastful individual whose ultimate downfall is ordained by Heart of Sky because of the excessive pride he had in his glorious appearance."</p>

<p>Tedlock (1996: 355-356) interprets the two meanings -- spiritual and earthly -- of the name <em>Wuqub Kak'ix</em> as such: "<em>Wuqub' kaqix</em>, a god who falsely claimed to be both the sun and moon during the era of the wooden people; husband of Chimalmat and father of Zipacna and Earthquake. In his earthly role he is a scarlet macaw (<em>Ara macao</em>), while his celestial role is that of the seven stars of the Big Dipper. At the request of Hurricane, Hunahpu and Xbalanque bring Seven Macaw down out of his tree, opening the way for the great rain that destroys the wooden people who worshipped Seven Macaw as the sun. In the same way, the period during which the Big Dipper is in descent or below the horizon for most of the night coincides with the hurricane season in the latitudes of Mesoamerica and the Caribbean (mid-July to mid-October)."</p>

<p>Sam Colop (2011: nota 47, página 209) añade que el nombre literalmente es "Siete Guacamaya, siendo el numeral 7 parte del nombre", y <em>Kak'ix</em>, guacamaya. "A Wuqub Kak'ix se le asocia también con la 'Osa Mayor' como está traducido en el diccionario de De León (1955: 33), lo cual coincide con el número de estrellas que integran dicha constelación y cuya luz es efectivamente tenue. Recuérdese aquí que conforme al mito k'iche', el Cielo está siendo literalmente 'sembrado' de astros por los dioses." De esta forma el texto marca el contraste entre la gente de madera, o el pueblo que crees "que Wuqub Kak'ix era la única luz que les proveía de claridad", y la gente de maíz (nota 28, página 209).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wuqub Kame</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>673</nid>
    <key>WUQUB_KAME</key>
    <ximenez_spa>vvcub came</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>vvcub came</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Wuqub No&#039;j</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>879</nid>
    <key>WUQUB_NOJ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Vucub noh</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Vucub noh</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>With Kuwatepech, Wuqub' No'j forms the 11th generation of the Kaweq family, part of the K'iche' community. </p>

<p>Kuwatepech y Wuqub' No'j son los señores undécimos del linaje Kaweq.</p>

<p>La etimología náhuatl indica una larga historia de contacto entre el pueblo k'iche' y el imperio mexica. Como así observa Allen Christenson (2004: nota 853, página 277), "<em>Wuqub' No'j </em>(Seven Thoughts) reigned ca. 1500-1523. This is a day on the traditional 260 day calendar, and is likely the day on which this lord was born. His reign was marked by continued war with the Cakchiquels. In the year 1514, two wars were fought, the first at the <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Sotzil,+Guatemala/@15.6281513,-91.1058104,841m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m5!3m4!1s0x858b85af73f7f30b:0x6eee3e05f2a5a6c2!8m2!3d15.6274988!4d-91.103531">river Sotzil</a> and the second at Mukche. The Quiché Magistrate of War (Q'alel Achi) died in the latter conflict and many prisoners were taken. Carmack identifies this lord with Ahpop Tuh, the father of Yaxonkik who was soundly defeated in battle with the Cakchiquels in 1517 (Carmack 1981, 138). The Annals of the Cakchiquels claims that 'during this year our fathers and grandfathers destroyed the Quichés once again; they exterminated them as if by lightning' (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 114).</p>

<p>In his day, the Quichés also came into closer contact with the Aztecs of Central Mexico. In 1501, the Aztec king Ahuitzotl sent 'merchants and officials' to the court of Cumarcah, likely to demand tribute and/or vassalage. The Quichés ordered them out of their territory (Fuentes y Guzmán 1932-33, 6, 47). Apparently Vucub Noh did not feel as comfortable in his position by 1510, for in that year the Quichés began to pay tribute to the Aztec lord Moctezuma in the form of quetzal feathers, gold, precious stones, cacao, and cloth. These payments continued until the fall of the Aztec empire to the Spaniards (Recinos 1957, 84; Carmack and Mondloch 1983, 142).</p>

<p>These ties were strengthened by marriage ties. According to the Buenabaj Pictorials, recently discovered by Carmack in the Momostenango area, 'the lord Quiché... wed two of the daughters of Mendectzum [Moctezuma] called Malintzin' (Carmack 1973, 371). In 1512, Moctezuma sent an emissary named Witzitzil to warn the Quichés of the arrival of the Spaniards along the Mexican Gulf Coast. He warned them to prepare to defend themselves (Recinos 1957, 84-85). In 1519, a plague broke out at Iximche: 'First they became ill of a cough, they suffered from nosebleeds and illness of the bladder. It was truly terrible, the number of dead there were in that period.... Little by little, heavy shadows and black night enveloped our fathers and grandfathers and us also, oh, my sons! when the plague raged' (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 115).</p>

<p>The plague lasted at least until 1521 and, although Quiché records do not mention it, it is likely that it spread throughout the Guatemalan highlands. Edmonson suggests that this may have been an epidemic of smallpox, a disease brought by the early Spanish explorers (Edmonson 1965, 5).</p>

<p>A similar plague struck Yucatán in 1516: 'A pestilence seized them, characterized by great pustules, which rotted their bodies with<br />
a great stench, so that the limbs fell to pieces in four or five days' (Landa 1941, 42).</p>

<p>Perhaps in order to present a united front against the Spanish threat, Vucub Noh negotiated peace with the Cakchiquel lord Belehe Qat in 1522, ending the protracted war that had raged between the two nations since the time of Lord Quicab (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 118). This cessation of hostilities did not, however, prevent the Cakchiquels from allying themselves with the invading Spaniards against the Quichés.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xbalanke</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>10</nid>
    <key>XBALAMKE</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Xbalanque</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%202785%20hero%20twins%20lift%20the%20horns%20of%20a%20sacrificial%20deer.jpeg?itok=ZafovvgC" width="100" height="35" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=2785" title="Kerr #2785: The Hero Twins lift the horns of a sacrificial deer" /></image>
    <description><p>It is not entirely clear if the gender of Xbalanke is male or female. The prefix /x/ may be used to indicate the feminine or as a diminutive. (rca2t)</p>

<p>Sam Colop (2011: nota 52, páginas 209-210) destaca las varias e importantes interpretaciones del personaje divino. Escribe: "Una interpretación de este nombre es 'Pequeño Jaguar-venado' donde el prefijo <em>x-</em> indica el diminutivo, <em>balam</em> es 'jaguar' y <em>ke</em> es apócope de <em>kej</em> que significa 'venado'. Sin embargo, D. Tedlock (1996: 239) presenta una interesante traducción al identificar <em>balam</em> con 'jaguar' y 'oculto'; <em>Q'e</em>, 'Sol' en su fase nocturna de acuerdo con la tradición q'eqchi'. <em>Balamq'e</em>, 'dios Sol (el-Sol-de noche va como tigre al oriente...') (Haeserijn, 1979: 53), lo que a su vez se confirma al final del relato mitológico. El primer genelo se convierte en Sol y el segundo en la Luna, lo cual puede entenderse propiamente como el 'Sol escondido durante la noche' o su reflejo porque en k'iche' a la Luna también se le identifica como 'Sol nocturno'. Nótese además que es Xbalamke quien reconstruy e la cabeza de Junajpu, y eso ocurre durante la noche, y que en q'eqchi', <em>po</em> es 'Luna' o 'mes' con lo cual existiría un juego de sonidos con la sílaba final del término Junajpu".</p>

<p>Christenson (2007: note 164, pages 81-2) notes, "the derivation of the name Xbalanque is problematic. The prefix <em>x-</em> is a diminutive as well as a feminine indicator. Thus, depending on the context, it may mean 'young, small, little,' or it may be used as a female title, such as 'lady.' The latter usage has led to some speculation that Xbalanque may have been the twin sister of Hunahpu, acting as the female counterpart to the male powers of the hunter. This theory is not supported by the text, however, which consistently refers to the twins as 'sons' or 'boys.' Hunahpu himself often carries the <em>x-</em> prefix, although not as consistently as his brother (see lines 4307, 4550, 4576, 4586, 4646, 4725).<em> B'alan</em> is undoubtedly an archaic spelling of <em>b'alam</em> (jaguar), m/n letter substitutions being fairly common in Quiché. Indeed, Vico transcribed the name in his <em>Theologia Indorum as Xbalamquej</em> (Carmack and Morales Santos 1983, 6-8). Known for its ferocity and cunning, the jaguar is the largest predator in Mesoamerica. Rulers decorated their thrones with jaguar symbols and wore jaguar pelts to emphasize lordly power. In addition, the jaguar is associated with ritual powers of transformation and prophecy. The terminal <em>ke</em> is more difficult to interpret. The most likely derivations are <em>kej</em> (deer) or <em>q'ij</em> (sun or day). The latter possibility is intriguing. The Maya closely identified the jaguar with the sun, particularly in its journey through the underworld at night. The story of Xbalanque and his brother focuses on their passage through the underworld, where they defeat the lords of death, ultimately to become the apotheosed sun and moon in the sky. Father Bartolomé de las Casas was told in the sixteenth century that Exbalanquen was a god from the area of the Guatemalan Alta Verapaz who made war with the lords of hell and returned as a great ruler (Las Casas 1958, 427). The word for sun in the Kekchi-Maya dialect of the Alta Verapaz region is <em>q'e</em>, and Xbalamq'e is still remembered by the Kekchi as a sun god (D. Tedlock 1996, 239 n. 77). If this name is purely of Kekchi origin, Balamq’e may be read in that language as 'hidden sun, or the night sun' (Ibid.). The most likely translation of the name would therefore be 'Young Hidden/Jaguar Sun.'"</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xibalba</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>732</nid>
    <key>XIBALBA</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xibalba</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xibalba</ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/kerr%20578.jpg?itok=NhE-uQ3a" width="100" height="31" alt="Kerr Database #578. Available: http://research.mayavase.com/kerrmaya_hires.php?vase=578." title="Kerr Database #578, &quot;One of numerous scenes of the destruction of the Lords of Xibalba.&quot;" /></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (p. 114, note 231): “<em>Xib’alb’a</em> (place of fear) is the Quiché name for the underworld, ruled by lords of death and disease. Modern Quichés still use the word to describe an underground hell inhabited by demons who cause sickness.”</p>

<p>    Recinos (nota 6, segunda parte, p. 169): “Antiguamente, dice el P. Coto, <em>Xibalbay</em> significaba el demonio, o los difuntos o visiones que se aparecían a los indios. En Yucatán tenía los mismos significados. <em>Xibalbá</em> era el diablo y <em>xibil</em> es desaparecerse como visión o fantasma, según el <em>Diccionario de Motul</em>. Los mayas practicaban un baile que llamaban <em>Xibalbá ocot</em>, o baile del demonio. Para los quichés <em>Xibalbá</em> era la región subterránea habitada por enemigos del hombre.”</p>

<p>   The root <em>Xib’ </em>in modern K’iche’ means “fear,” while the instrumental suffix <em>-b’al </em>would here indicate “place.” The final -<em>b’a </em>may be a repetition of the instrumental element (Sattler, personal communication) or, as Stross (1987) argues, it may be a corruption of <em>b’e’ </em>“road.” Stross asserts that the form <em>Xib’alb’e </em>is not uncommon, and interprets the hieroglyphic inscription on Tikal altar 8 this way. In this (speculative) analysis, the name means “road of the place of fear” (see <em>Camino Negro</em>). On this basis, Stross associates the underworld of the Popol Wuj with a name used for the Milky Way in winter. He quotes Coe: “there are two words for the Milky Way, one (Sac Bey [Saqib’e’]) for summer, and one (Xibal bey [Xib’alb’e’]) for the winter, when it is bifurcated; the bifurcation is identified with the Underworld, and it is quite possible that the Maya, like many other American Indians, thought of the Milky Way as the road of the souls journeying to that region.” It may be relevant to this interpretation that One Junajpu and Seven Junajpu are defeated by the lords of Xib’alb’a when they arrive at a crossroads and take the black road.</p>

<p>On “Road of Xibalba” (<em>ri b’e xib’alb’a</em>), Tedlock (p. 354) notes: “As a celestial road it is the Great Rift in the Milky Way; as a terrestrial road it descends into Xibalba from somewhere near Great Hollow with Fish in the Ashes.” (See <em>Camino Negro</em>)</p>

<p> </p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xikiri Pat</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>674</nid>
    <key>XIKIRI_PAT</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xíc</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xic </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xōchiquetzal</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>1079</nid>
    <key>XOCHIQUETZAL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xuchínqueꜩalí</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>The Nahua goddess Xōchiquetzal was the mother of Quetzalcoatl. Ximénez equates Xōchiquetzal with the Maya goddess Ixkik'. He further states that his predecessors had, in his view, erroneously equated both goddesses with the Christian figure of Mary, the mother of God.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xpiyakok</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>641</nid>
    <key>XPIYAKOK</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xpiyacoc</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xpiyacoc</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: note 26, page 54) observes, "Xpiyacoc is the male deity, while Xmucane serves as the divine female principal that brings about the creation. The derivation of the name Xpiyacoc is problematic. Edmonson suggests that it is based on the Nahua <em>yex-pa-ococc(an-e)</em>, which he reads as 'thrice in another two places,' and relates it to the next phrase of the text in which this deity is referred to as 'twice patriarch.' Tedlock prefers that it should be read as a Quiché name, and that it is based on the verb <em>yekik</em>/<em>yakik</em>, which his Quiché collaborator interpreted as 'to be put in order, to be lifted up' with regard to the problems of clients who are under treatment by <em>aj q'ij </em>priests.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most likely derivation of this name is found at Rabinal where there is a design woven into textiles which locals call piyakok and identify as a turtle (Akkeren 2000, 207, 261- 264). Kok is 'turtle' in both lowland and highland Maya languages, making this an intriguing possibility. At Chichen Itza as well as Mayapan (both post-Classic sites likely contemporary with the early history of the Quichés), the aged grandfather earth deity (God N, Pauahtun, Bacab, Mam) wears a turtle carapace and bears up the sky (Taube 1992, 92-99; Schele and Mathews 1998, 214-218). Among the contemporary Kekchi and Pokomchi, this god is identified as the Mam (Grandfather), an earth deity who oversees the five day Uayeb period prior which precedes the beginning of the new year in the ancient calendric system. It is possible that Xpiyacoc is the Quiché version of this deity.</p>

<p>Ultimately, a definitive etymology is impossible to determine. When proper names are passed down through generations of time, they often tend to become altered in their pronunciation, and perhaps their original meaning as well. If Xpiyacoc is derived from a Nahua original, it had certainly become mangled to the point where an Aztec envoy at the Quiché court would have had a difficult time coming up with an obvious meaning for it in his language. The same is true for Yucatec, Cholan, or Mam derivations for the name. There are similar-sounding words in each of these languages, although none are a precise fit. It is thus possible that the Quichés of the sixteenth century preserved the archaic spelling because they saw it simply as a proper name, without necessarily preserving memory of its original derivation." Christenson observes similar processes of linguistic compounding and potential evidence of language contact in the names Junajpu and Xbalamque; he thus leaves these names untranslated in his prose translation.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xpurpuweq</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>699</nid>
    <key>XPURPUWEQ</key>
    <ximenez_spa>xparpuec</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xparpuec</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Xulu</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>701</nid>
    <key>XULU</key>
    <ximenez_spa> xulupacam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>xuluppacam </ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>En la nota 173 Colop explica, “En el diccionario de Basseta encontramos <em>ajxulu</em> como “adivino”, equivalente a <em>ajq´ij</em>. Conforme a Coto (1983: 140), <em>xulu</em> son “unos demoñuelos o familiares que se les aparecían junto a los ríos”. Conforme a Varea (1997: 358), “al que curaba con estos diablillos, llamaban aj-q´ij, aj-xulu”. Todo indica que Xulu es el “sacerdote del agua”. Pak´am parece derivar de <em>pak´alik</em>, “dar vuelta”, “boca arriba”, cuyo significado sería darle vuelta a lo que se mira. D. Tedlock (1996: 278) sugiere que <em>xulu</em> y <em>pak´am</em> son los que conforme a Coto (1983: 13) “adivinan el agua”. Esto está asociado a que en este pasaje [Colop 2011:96, Ximénez: folio 28 verso, linea 25], los gemelos “vuelven a la vida” como hombres peces” (2011:225).</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ya&#039; Xkanul</title>
    <type>toponymo</type>
    <nid>1043</nid>
    <key>YA_XKANUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>yaxcanul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>ya xcanul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 174): "Volcán Santa María, southwest of Quetzaltenango, Guatemala. <em>Xkanul </em>is also a general term for volcano in Quiché."</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Ya&#039;xkanul</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>663</nid>
    <key>YAXKANUL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>yaxcanul</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>yaxcanul</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Yachwach</title>
    <type>objeto</type>
    <nid>1248</nid>
    <key>YACHWACH</key>
    <ximenez_spa></ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc></ximenez_quc>
    <image><img class="img-responsive" src="http://live-multepal.pantheonsite.io/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/6457.jpeg?itok=i1g1OUq_" width="76" height="100" alt="http://research.mayavase.com/portfolio_hires.php?search=6457&amp;date_added=&amp;image=6457&amp;display=8&amp;rowstart=0" title="Kerr portfolio image #6457, &quot;Zapotec Urn. clay. height 17.3 cm. Seated figure with feather headdress.&quot;" /></image>
    <description><p>Feather headbands</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Yaki Tepew</title>
    <type>linaje</type>
    <nid>811</nid>
    <key>YAKI_TEPEW</key>
    <ximenez_spa>yaquí tepeu</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>yaquí tepeu</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Yakolatam</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>985</nid>
    <key>YAKOLATAM</key>
    <ximenez_spa>Yacolatam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>Yacolatam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson (2007: 284) translates the name as "Corner of the Reed Mat," noting in his explanation of Yakolatam Utza'm Pop Saqlatol that the name derives from Nahuatl.</p>

<p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252) indica que <em>yako</em> significa "levantar" en el idioma maya k'iche'.</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Yakolatam Utza&#039;m Pop Saqlatol</title>
    <type>persona</type>
    <nid>858</nid>
    <key>YAKOLATAM_UTZAM_POP_SAQLATOL</key>
    <ximenez_spa>yacolatam</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>yacolatam</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description><p>Christenson renders the name as "Yacolatam (Corner of the Reed Mat) Zaclatol," noting that Ximénez's use of the name, <em>Yakolatam, U Tza'm Pop Zaklatol</em> represents "a singular instance in the <em>Popol Vuh</em> text where a Nahua language title is supplied with a Quiché translation by the authors. Yakolatam is derived from the Nahua <em>yacatl</em> (point, edge) and <em>tam </em>(leaves). This is followed by a comma in the manuscript, a fairly rare grammatical mark which in this case may indicate a pause for the authors to give a translation of the preceding word into Quiché. <em>U tza'm pop</em> (Quiché: its nose/point/edge/border reed mat) is a rough translation of <em>yakolatam</em>. <em>Zaklatol</em> is a combination of the Nahua <em>zacatl</em> (grass) and <em>tollin</em> (reed), a translation of the preceding <em>pop</em> (reed mat)" (2007: note 756, p. 256).</p>

<p>Cabe señalar que este octavo señor de los Nija’ib, según afirma Sam Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252), deriva su nombre de otras fuentes. Escribe: “probablemente se refiera al ‘encargado de los puntos de avanzada’ viniendo su nombre de <em>yako</em>, ‘levantar’, <em>utz’am</em>, ‘orillas’ o ‘límites’; <em>pop</em>, ‘petate’ o la gente entrelazada en esta comunidad’ y <em>saqlatol </em>quiere decir ‘claridad.’”</p></description>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <title>Yolkwat</title>
    <type>deidad</type>
    <nid>722</nid>
    <key>YOLKWAT</key>
    <ximenez_spa>yolcuat</ximenez_spa>
    <ximenez_quc>yolcuat</ximenez_quc>
    <image></image>
    <description></description>
  </topic>
</topics>
